<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>policy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://newblog/tags/policy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in policy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 15:11:38 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://newblog/tags/policy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    <item>
      <title>NYSED says you don&#39;t need to know CS to teach CS</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/soce/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2023 15:11:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/soce/</guid>
      <description>The title might come of as hyperbole but it&amp;#39;s really true.
I&amp;#39;ll explain.
A few years ago, NYSED created a certification area for computer science. At Hunter, we&amp;#39;ve been running our certificate program for the past three years and taking current teachers and qualifying them to earn this new certification. This past Fall, NYSED finalized it&amp;#39;s grandfathering position and just the other day it opened up the portal to allow teachers to sign up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Public Education - Which side are you on?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/which-side/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 08:20:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/which-side/</guid>
      <description>My feeds have been inundated with post after post dealing with teacher burnout, teacher shortages, government attacks on teachers and public schools. In response to one video, a friend of mine commented:
This is going to be a crazy summer and fall. I wonder if we are witnessing the end of public education.
Teaching was always a high attrition profession but given the stress teachers have been under since the pandemic started it&amp;#39;s no surprise that teachers who can are leaving in droves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Will Online Influence Teaching</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/how-will-online-influence-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 08:53:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/how-will-online-influence-teaching/</guid>
      <description>I always enjoy Fred Wilson&amp;#39;s predictions for the new year over on his blog and this year was no exception.
I was inspired to think a bit on his education prediction:
K12 systems around the US (and around the world) faced with teacher shortages and desperate to erase several years of learning shortfalls, will increasingly adopt online learning services in the school building in lieu of and in addition to in-class learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Censorship, TOS, and a slippery slope</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/censorship/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 14:14:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/censorship/</guid>
      <description>Lots of chatter with Donald Trump being kicked off platforms left and right. On the one hand we&amp;#39;re getting a lot of &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s censorship, it&amp;#39;s unust&amp;#34; and on the other side we have &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s about time.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m of course in the &amp;#34;it&amp;#39;s about time&amp;#34; category but even so, there&amp;#39;s a cause for concern and a lot of meat for a discussion on tech policies.
What makes this interesting discussion fodder is that Trump was removed from different levels of the internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>School leadership and COVID, or not</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/covid-leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 09:48:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/covid-leadership/</guid>
      <description>Teachers are back and students will soon follow either in person or remote. In person means in person one or two days a week with the rest of the time from home.
This of course shows horrible leadership. It fails in terms of education, safety and even freeing up parents to get back to work. After all, if your kid is only in school one or two days a week it hardly allows you to get back to your own full time job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reopening Schools - de Blasio and Carranza throw kids and teachers under the bus.</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/reopening-schools/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 08:18:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/reopening-schools/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Bill de Blasio and Richard Carranza unveiled their open the schools in the fall plan. The plan is perfectly consistent with de Blasio and Carranza&amp;#39;s education policies and efforts in general - tone deaf, ineffective, and in this case, unsafe.
I know we were told that part of this came from survey results but we all know that surveys are super easy to fix. I mean, ask any teacher or parent &amp;#34;do you want schools to be open and in person in the Fall?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why are police held to such a lower standard than teachers?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teachers-police-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 12:36:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teachers-police-2/</guid>
      <description>My friend Neal Zupancic, actually former student, friend, and long time teacher Neal Zupancic posted this on Facebook. It&amp;#39;s 100% spot on. I&amp;#39;d add my two cents but Neal captured it better than I ever could. Take a minute to read it:
In my ten years of teaching, I&amp;#39;ve dealt with a number of situations that could have potentially turned dangerous. I&amp;#39;ve taught in public schools and private; urban schools and rural.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Future consequences of today&#39;s grading policies</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/grading-consequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 07:08:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/grading-consequences/</guid>
      <description>How are we going to deal with grades? This has garnered a lot of attention since COVID-19 struck. Over on the AP side people wonder if colleges will give credit? Do the tests mean anything? What about the material they won&amp;#39;t be testing? We also have had standardized tests canceled and a variety of grading policies.
I&amp;#39;m going to stay away from AP this time around - you all know my feelings about the college board.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest Post - Missing out on a great opportunity in education</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 06:53:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/guest-jonalf-dw/</guid>
      <description>Preamble I&amp;#39;ve never accepted a guest post before but when my friend and long time colleague JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver said he had something to say I was all for it. JonAlf&amp;#39;s one of the best teachers I know - he started at Brandeis HS and has been at Stuy forever. Really sharp guy, great teacher, and really perceptive. When he has something to say it&amp;#39;s 100% worth listening to. To JonAlf - since I know this is one of my blog posts you&amp;#39;ll actually read - you should set up a blog of your own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers Pay Teachers - part 2 - the report</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teachers-pay-teachers-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 10:03:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teachers-pay-teachers-2/</guid>
      <description>Continuing from yesterday, what about the article and report on pay and free teacher resources.
The report looked at three sources - one pay and two free. They came up with a number of results but I think they largely missed the point.
Their bottom line conclusion was that &amp;#39;Overall, reviewers rate most of the materials as “mediocre” or “probably not worth using”.&amp;#39; They also didn&amp;#39;t seem to find that neither the for profit or free sources were universally better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers Pay Teachers  - part 1 - should they</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teachers-pay-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 08:43:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teachers-pay-teachers/</guid>
      <description>There was a bit of buzz a couple of months ago when Amazon announced an online marketplace for educational resources. It wasn&amp;#39;t a new concept - on the pay side, Teachers Pay Teachers has been around for a while and in terms of free, there are many online resources but they&amp;#39;re not necessarily well organized or curated. What was the buzz? Should teachers be charging their peers for class materials or should they be providing them for free.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Education is not a spectator sport</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/education-not-spec-sport/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 08:07:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/education-not-spec-sport/</guid>
      <description>As many of you know, the CS Education programs I designed here at Hunter were finally approved by NY State late last year. We&amp;#39;re planning to get started this summer. I&amp;#39;ve received many questions about the program and will write up the details here sooner or later but one question I frequently get is &amp;#34;will it be offered online?&amp;#34; This is also something I&amp;#39;ve been asked more than once internal to Hunter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pushback To CS for All</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/pushback-to-csforall/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2020 08:27:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/pushback-to-csforall/</guid>
      <description>On the last day of 2019, Audrey Waters wrote a great piece on The 100 Worst Ed-Tech Debacles of the Decade. I agree with most of them but felt it was worth looking at a one in particular. Specifically number 6 - &amp;#34;Everyone Should earn to Code.&amp;#34; I might dive in to some others later but we&amp;#39;ll stick with number 6 for today.
I read over these right after reading two recent posts by Alina Adam&amp;#39;s son Gregory - a sophomore at Stuyvesant High School over on Alina&amp;#39;s blog questioning NYC&amp;#39;s CS For All initiative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheating on CS projects</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/cheating-on-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 17:33:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/cheating-on-projects/</guid>
      <description>Alfred Thompson posted today about cheating on CS class projects. It was in response to Garth Flint&amp;#39;s post on finding interesting projects which in turn referenced earlier posts by Alfred and me.
Garth laments that it&amp;#39;s hard to find projects that are both interesting and meaty but where solutions can&amp;#39;t easily be searched for online. Alfred notes that cheating will happen and that it&amp;#39;s an ethics issue. This is why I try to create a culture of sharing and acknowledging credit (that is, citing sources) but I&amp;#39;m not naive enough to believe there isn&amp;#39;t any cheating in my classes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Thomas Friedman&#39;s editorial on the College Board&#39;s Two Codes left me concerned</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/college-boards-two-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 10:20:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/college-boards-two-codes/</guid>
      <description>There was some buzz over this editorial about the College Board last week. The two codes every child needs - Coding and the US Constitution? Who could argue with that.
I&amp;#39;m not going to disagree. Civics and CS are important and can&amp;#39;t wait until college. The thing that left me chilled though was that nobody&amp;#39;s paying attention to the fact that the College Board - a private entity with its own interests has so much influence over American education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Jobs, Diversity, and Equity in the wake of the Amazon/NYC debacle</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 11:14:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/tech-jobs-amazon/</guid>
      <description>I was planning on either following up on how I use GitHub classroom or commenting on the recent NY Times opinion piece on the College Board but the follow up, fall out, and polarization from the Amazon NY thing has been stuck in my head so I thought I&amp;#39;d write a bit more about it.
Like my previous post, this isn&amp;#39;t really about Amazon but rather about the long game, equity, and diversity and how a lot of people are fooling themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No Amazon HQ2 in NYC</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/no-amazon-hq/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 17:57:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/no-amazon-hq/</guid>
      <description>That was the big tech news today. I know there was a good deal of vocal outrage about the deal but to be honest I was pretty surprised by the news. Normally deals like these get steamrolled through for better or worse.
I have decidedly mixed feelings about this. On the one hand, I have no problem with Amazon - I&amp;#39;ve got a bunch of former students working there. Mostly in Seattle but at least one in NYC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Ap Registration - it&#39;s, um, for the kids</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 08:08:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/early-ap-registration-for-the-kids/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon a thread over in the APCS-A Facebook group the other day. It seems that the College Board is making some changes in their registration timeline. In the past, students registered for the exam sometime in March with the exams administered in May. The new changes include requiring registration in November along with $40 late registration and cancellation fees.
The College Board is, of course, spinning this as for the student&amp;#39;s benefit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a school for CS</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/creating-a-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/creating-a-school/</guid>
      <description>Do we really need CS focused high schools?
That&amp;#39;s the question Alfred Thompson asked partly in reaction to my post talking about Bill Gates&amp;#39; visit to AFSE, a NYC public school with a CS focus.
On both posts, Michael Preston shared some important and good points about AFSE as a starting point and gateway that helped lead to CS4All in NYC and also specifically about AFSE.
In response to Alfred&amp;#39;s question I thought it was time I shared a bit about what I was pushing for AFSE back when I was involved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving control of NYC&#39;s specialized schools to a political appointee</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/shsat-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/shsat-part2/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio&amp;#39;s plans to &amp;#34;fix&amp;#34; the selection criteria for New York City&amp;#39;s specialized high schools. If you haven&amp;#39;t read the post, you can find it here.
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but there&amp;#39;s more to the story.
In spite of what BdB stated, it&amp;#39;s not enough for him to switch to another measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/shsat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/shsat/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined how he would &amp;#34;fix&amp;#34; our specialized schools. The schools he was referring to were the &amp;#34;big three&amp;#34; of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School for Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High School at York College, and Staten Island Tech.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should CS for All be implemented at the college level?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/csforall-in-college/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/csforall-in-college/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;#39;s been a lively discussion on pushback to CS for All at the K12 level over on Facebook. Mark Guzdial started a sub thread asking if CS for All should first be implemented at the undergrad level rather than K12.
It&amp;#39;s an interesting question and as good as anything to get me out of my month long non-blogging rut.
Mark was right when he said that if Colleges implement CS for All, K12 will likely do so to follow - just look at AP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is there room for CS for All</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/room-for-csforall/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/room-for-csforall/</guid>
      <description>A fear revolving around CS For All concerns where will the money come from and how will we fit in the new classes.
One suggested solution is to integrate CS into other subjects. I thought I&amp;#39;d write today about why I don&amp;#39;t think the fear is valid and while integrating CS into other classes can have value, it probably isn&amp;#39;t a long term solution for CS education.
Let&amp;#39;s start with the integration solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/unfunded-mandates/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/unfunded-mandates/</guid>
      <description>This morning, Mark Guzdial wrote about unfunded mandates and CS for All. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number of ways but in the long run, I don&amp;#39;t think it should have a severe effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number of CS courses we offer beyond that.
Mark relay&amp;#39;s a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn&amp;#39;t planning on hiring a new CS teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid>
      <description>About a week ago New York State&amp;#39;s new regulation creating a K12 CS teacher certification went live. Just the other day I was honored to be interviewed by Matt Flamm of Crain&amp;#39;s New York in a follow up piece about it.
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs that lead to certification is HUGE. In my view, it&amp;#39;s a game changer.
Let&amp;#39;s Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/atrs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/atrs/</guid>
      <description>In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool.
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to actually settle in a position.
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</guid>
      <description>Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members of the New York State Department of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A test result is just a test result</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>This past weekend was Catskillsconf - my favorite event of the year. I spent the weekend up in Ulster County with a bunch of my students. some great friends old and new, and Devorah. It was a great weekend but I was mostly offline.
As a result I missed a rather heated discussion in the CS Ed Facebook groups. The debate was over whether or not Strong AP CSP exam results are indicative of a good curriculum or good professional development (PD).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standards - Who are they for?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/standards-who-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/standards-who-for/</guid>
      <description>The big push at last year&amp;#39;s CSTA conference was the release of the new CSTA K12 standards. It seemed that every other session was pushing them in one way or another. I&amp;#39;ve been meaning to share my thoughts about them or, more specifically, learning standards in general for a while but with announcement about federal funding for CS coming from the White House last week I thought it was time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the new Secret Sauce ever better?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</guid>
      <description>I read this piece earlier today on Nancy Bailey&amp;#39;s blog.
TL;DR (although it really isn&amp;#39;t too long so you should read it) - it&amp;#39;s on Laurene Powell Jobs, her efforts to &amp;#34;reform&amp;#34; education and why she&amp;#39;s misguided as are most of the well to do non-educators working hard to change and in many cases privatize public education.
Laura posts a nice list of simple, common sense ways to improve education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Cost of AP Exams</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid>
      <description>Now that I&amp;#39;m back from vacation and summer&amp;#39;s winding down I thought I&amp;#39;d start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a few summer topics I want to write about – standards and side projects in particular but I&amp;#39;m also looking forward to talking more about the classroom since, after all, at my core, I&amp;#39;m a teacher. When I saw this article in my inbox this morning I thought I&amp;#39;d talk about it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on non educator  influences on CS Education</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday Mark Guzdial blogged about a NY Times piece discussing Silicon Valleys influence on education through Code.org.
Mark questioned the validity of the piece. If you don&amp;#39;t read Mark&amp;#39;s blog and you&amp;#39;re in CS Ed you probably should.
I tried to leave a comment on Mark&amp;#39;s blog - not about the NY Times article but rather my thoughts on why I think it&amp;#39;s important that we remain wary and vigilant to industry and outsiders influence and impact on CS education and on education in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Ed advocates should pay attention to greater ed issues</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/cs-ed-and-all-ed/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/cs-ed-and-all-ed/</guid>
      <description>For anyone involved in K12 CS education, the past few years have been a wild ride. When I first tried to make inroads in the DOE decades ago I couldn&amp;#39;t get through the door. Now, CS Education is everyone&amp;#39;s darling. It&amp;#39;s really amazing. It&amp;#39;s been a combination of grass roots efforts by teachers, non profit education efforts such as TEALS, advocacy of groups like Code.org and amazing individuals like Fred Wilson who has probably done more to move the needle of CS Ed in NY than any other 10 people combined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/dont-self-certify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/dont-self-certify/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;#39;ve probably seen an image like this:
It&amp;#39;s what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web site itself certified itself as being secure.
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we don&amp;#39;t see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted source.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teachers - teacher first or content first</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</guid>
      <description>Is it easier to take CS people and teach them to teach or is it easier to take teachers and teach them CS?
The question gets batted around from time to time.
This time via twitter:
Some think it&amp;#39;s easier to teach a teacher to teach CS than to teach a CS pro to teach. @alfredtwo is not one of them https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ
&amp;mdash; Diane Levitt (@diane_levitt) July 3, 2017 Agreed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Retaining Teachers</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</guid>
      <description>Back in February, I shared my thoughts on losing CS teachers to the tech industy. TL;DR - I don&amp;#39;t think it will be a CS Ed problem.
That said, I do think that it will be hard to find good CS teachers but the reason is because it will get harder and harder to find good teachers in general.
There are plenty of reasons why it&amp;#39;s harder to become a career teacher but I don&amp;#39;t want to talk about those today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mayoral Control - only when your guy&#39;s the mayor</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/mayoral-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/mayoral-control/</guid>
      <description>The hot debate this past week in NY Education circles is Mayoral Control. When I started teaching, New York City schools were controlled by the Board of Education. The board appointed a chancellor. The system was supposed to balance community control as well as some centralized decision making. The system was created in the late 60s and was entrenched through my schooling. By the time I was a teacher I think it was pretty much a given that the system didn&amp;#39;t work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will we lose CS teachers to industry?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/draft-will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/draft-will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</guid>
      <description>If we properly prepare CS teachers, won&amp;#39;t they just jump ship and take tech industry jobs?
I hear that a lot.
Tech pays big. Teaching? Not so much. Tech workers are respected and have flexible jobs. Teaching? Again, not so much.
Those chanting these refrains advocate the current simple teacher &amp;#34;training&amp;#34; - scripted lessons, minimal pedagogical content knowledge, even less real content knowledge. That will keep them in the classroom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should CS Ed be in bed with the College Board</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m guessing my views on this aren&amp;#39;t very popular -that&amp;#39;s OK, every community needs a curmudgeon.
A few years ago, I cautioned if we weren&amp;#39;t careful, once the big players got involved, CS Ed would go the way of other disciplines, and not in a good way. It looks like indeed we&amp;#39;re well on our way down that road.
I&amp;#39;ve ranted before about things like non-profits, drop in and summer programs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s not one issue, it&#39;s the President and his enablers</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/trump-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/trump-issues/</guid>
      <description>Like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, I generally keep this site clear of political issues with the exception of those that are directly related to education.
Also, like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, this week has provided a reason to break with that tradition.
Many people, including some friends, all more eloquent than I have already posted, tweeted, and Facebooked about the behavior of our President and government.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
