<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (misc)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 14:02:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Community Across The Years</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/community-across-the-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 14:02:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/community-across-the-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent last week in San Francisco. I didn&amp;#39;t leave my heart there but
the entire trip was indeed heartwarming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was there with members of the Stuyvesant Alumni Association for a
StuyCS/Tech meetup. As one might imagine, many tech inclined graduates
from any school end up in the Bay Area and Stuy is no exception. Sure,
the majority of StuyCS grads stay in New York and help drive New
York&amp;#39;s tech sector but plenty decid to &amp;#34;go west.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had a terrific meetup on Thursday with around 125 attendees -
mostly my former students but a few older tech alums from the early
90s, 80s, and even earlier. The meetup was amazing and it meant a lot
to me to see so many friends, friends who I don&amp;#39;t get to see nearly
often enough. Of course, the problem is that it was something like
being a parent hosting a Bar Mitzvah - since you know everyone there,
you don&amp;#39;t have a chance to spend quality time with anyone - it&amp;#39;s
mostly drive by greetings and at most a minute or two with any given
person at a time. Still, I had a great time. Around the event, I was
able to have a dinners with just a few former students but of
course, I didn&amp;#39;t have enough days to have the number of small group
gatherings as I would have liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about communities and alumni communities in
particular. After a career in teaching that lasted 33 years, the
StuyCS family might be the single thing I&amp;#39;m proudest of. Interestingly
enough, there&amp;#39;s nothing else like it at Stuy. I&amp;#39;m wondering if there&amp;#39;s
anything like it from other schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like any school, each graduating class is a coherent group - some will
be more active, some less but that&amp;#39;s the typical unit - the class of
XX. They all have the usual five year reunions and maybe other
periodic events. Not much crossover though, if any, between the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
StuyCS is different. It&amp;#39;s a network of people who took the StuyCS
classes regardless of whether they went into tech or not spanning the
years. It also includes older Stuy graduates who are in tech but
graduated prior to my starting Stuy&amp;#39;s CS program and Stuy grads who
found their way to tech after graduating. As a result, we also have lawyers,
doctors, authors and more as part of a community who&amp;#39;s graduation
years start in the 70s and continue through this past year. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Stuy, leaving CS aside, there are two other groups that I would
have figured would have a similar network - Stuy&amp;#39;s Chorus - a program
that accommodates a couple of hundred kids a year and spans all four
years at Stuy. There are chorus classes and they also do special
events in addition to the usual at school concerts. The other is
Stuy&amp;#39;s Speech and Debate program. Smaller, but still spans the
grades. I believe there&amp;#39;s at least one S&amp;amp;D class and there are after
school meetings and practices and plenty of events and trips. For most
of the past three decades, each was led by a top notch teacher with a
strong personality - someone who could really hold things together and
drive the programs - far more together than I ever was. Stuy has a few
other sizable communities like the theater community or maybe one of
the sports teams but these two would be the one&amp;#39;s that I would expect
would have a strong, active, coherent alumni network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Surprisingly, at least to me, Stuy Chorus alums might be connected to
their fellow chorus members but not, for the most part, spanning the
years. They feel an allegiance to Stuy&amp;#39;s chorus but mostly if not
entirely withing their class. Speech and debate seems similar, at
least to me based on my discussions with Speech and Debate grads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the meetup, a few StuyCS members noted that we&amp;#39;re the most active
and coherent Stuy alumni group. Active meaning connected with each
other and willing and able to help each other across the years. We
wondered why, particularly since we&amp;#39;re probably the most socially
awkward group of grads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was posited that yeah, we&amp;#39;re socially awkward but we&amp;#39;re &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt;
socially awkward so somehow we fit together and it works. This sounds
plausible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe it&amp;#39;s because we have critical mass in a couple of locations - NY
and San Fran. Maybe, but then NY has critical mass for any Stuy alumni
group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another possibility is that so many StuyCS people went into the tech
field so there&amp;#39;s a direct professional commonality and a pretty direct
way people across the years can help each other. Maybe. Not many
chorus members are professional singers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not really sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;re also an interesting group because we&amp;#39;re not affiliated with
Stuy&amp;#39;s alumni association. We grew organically. In the past, under
earlier Alumni Administrations, I actually avoided working with them
but now, the current crew is top notch and I&amp;#39;m hoping to bring my
community and the official Alumni group closer together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned, I&amp;#39;m really proud of this community. I&amp;#39;m wondering if
other schools have had similar groups develop. If so, that&amp;#39;s
awesome. If not, well, it&amp;#39;s never too late.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enemy Of The Good</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/enemy-of-the-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 11:14:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/enemy-of-the-good/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I usually listen to podcasts on my morning run. For the past couple of
weeks I&amp;#39;ve been listening to &lt;a href=&#34;https://99percentinvisible.org/&#34;&gt;99% Invisible&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s series on &lt;a href=&#34;https://99percentinvisible.org/club/&#34;&gt;The Power
Broker&lt;/a&gt;, Robert Caro&amp;#39;s incredible biography of Robert Moses. Arguably
the best book on New York City not to mention urban planning and
politics.  Amazing book. I read it a few years ago, well, actually
listened to it at the same time as Natan - our own personal father son
book club. We&amp;#39;ve done it with a few tomes  - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.robertcaro.org/the-power-broker&#34;&gt;The Power Broker&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don_Quixote&#34;&gt;Don
Quixote&lt;/a&gt;, and most recently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/09/16/books/review/wagnerism-alex-ross.html&#34;&gt;Wagnerism&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I highly recommend both the book and the podcast series but I&amp;#39;m not
going to talk about either really today. As part of the series, each
episode includes an interview with a guest. One guest was Michael
Schur, co-creator of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parks_and_Recreation&#34;&gt;Parks and Rec&lt;/a&gt;. During the podcast, he told a
story about how, when working on Parks and Rec, they interviewed a
city bureaucrat or civil servant. He wanted to rebuild a small local
park. He had all sorts of plans to return the park to its original
glory including magnificent columns. Schur noted that since we live in
a democracy, he couldn&amp;#39;t just start building but rather all sorts of
constituents had to weigh in. One group wanted less grass, another
objected to the ornateness of the columns and so it went on and on. By
the time the park was actually finished, it was a pale imitation of
the original plans. Sure, it was a new, rebuilt park, but the
 plans had been gutted, scaled back and otherwise twisted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of this, when asked, the civil servant said he was happy with
the results. Sure, he wanted his plans but he also knew how government
worked and in the end, he as happy that there was some progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I see the same thing happen time and time again. Traffic calming
efforts that would improve safety, air quality, and quality of life in
general for many New Yorkers shot down because a small group of people
(usually rich white ones) insist that the city can&amp;#39;t remove the free
public parking in front of their buildings. I won&amp;#39;t even get started
on the housing crisis in the city. If following our cited civil
servant&amp;#39;s point of view, the people pushing the positive changes in
the city should be happy with their baby step successes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve always had difficulty with this point of view. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying it has to be &amp;#34;go big or go home&amp;#34; but I&amp;#39;ve always tried
to do it right rather than do it enough to check the checkbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I remember when New York City was creating AFSE (The Academy for
Software Engineering). I was involved for a while until the Department
of Ed froze me out. The DOE insisted that the goal of the school was to
create industry ready software engineers right out of high school
based on what I had built at Stuy. I said &amp;#34;great, but to do that you
need to have an academic screen to get in&amp;#34;  knowing that you can&amp;#39;t get
to industry ready if the kids are coming in multiple years behind,
particularly in math. I also said that they could go without a screen
but they&amp;#39;d have to adjust their expectations (as well as messaging)
since without the screen and with students coming in at all levels,
the best they would be able to do is give some exposure to computer
science and if they did it right, prepare them for college CS or a
boot camp after high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I said they could go either way but I was pushing for the entrance
screen. Not anything like the Stuy test, but something to make sure
the kids entered with enough of a math background so that the school
could accomplish its goals. I really believed with a modest math
screen and the right resources, the school could be something special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, I lost that one. The DOE froze me out. The
created an unscreened school (again, I&amp;#39;m not saying this in and of
itself was bad) but they maintained the messaging that the kids would
get that top level software engineering preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course the students didn&amp;#39;t. The school was fine as a generic school
but in terms of Software Engineering and CS Prep, looking back, I&amp;#39;d
actually say that there were public NYC schools that already existed
that were doing as well or arguably better and I&amp;#39;m not talking about
test schools like Stuy here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In discussing this was friends, I was commonly told &amp;#34;don&amp;#39;t let the
perfect be the enemy of the good.&amp;#34; I get it but it&amp;#39;s something that
I&amp;#39;ve long struggled with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, I think I was right about AFSE for the students
that went there. If the school was honest about what it was, I think
it could have served its kids better. Alternatively, if it added a
nominal screen it could have fulfilled its stated objective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, I was also wrong. The schools existence along with
the Public Relations push and industry hype, all under the Bloomberg
administration probably helped pave the way for Bill de Blasio&amp;#39;s
CSforAll initiative in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, was I right or was I wrong? I don&amp;#39;t know. Without AFSE we might
not have had CSforAll so I was most likely wrong but part of me still
believes that they could have done the school right and at the same
time still built the hype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also been similarly on both CSforAll and CS teacher prep
programs. My position has always been that we need knowledgeable CS
teachers in CS classes and that knowledgeable means actually knowing a
fair amount of CS. Of course this would mean a long term ramp up and
funding to actually pay to prepare the teachers. The majority trend
and view is quite different - start teaching CS now even if teachers
don&amp;#39;t really know what they&amp;#39;re doing and we might work things out at
some later point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not going to address the people who feel that short form PD is
enough to make a strong high school CS teacher other than to say
they&amp;#39;re flat out wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My view is wrong in that the ramp up would take years - probably
decades. That means that potentially another generation of kids would
be denied any CS education. On top of that, the amount of time needed
would be far longer than typical government office terms and who knows
if initiatives would survive from one administration to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, doing it quick and dirty can also be wrong. I&amp;#39;ve
seen both teachers and schools who believe that once they have someone
in an APCS-P class - regardless of that teacher&amp;#39;s ability to actually
teach CS - as long as they have the seal of approval of having gone
through some rudimentary code.org style training, it&amp;#39;s good enough and
the school is set for life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is also a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An even worse problem is when a school is teaching CS badly and
either turning off students or teaching them things that are just
wrong resulting in kids getting turned off later on. I&amp;#39;ve seen this as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I&amp;#39;m still muddled on this. I find it very frustrating when I see
CS education at the school, district, city, state, or national level
moving in a direction that I think is, not wrong, but not optimal even
though I try to console myself with the fact that the movement is
positive in a lot of ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also remind myself of something Pete Seeger frequently said,
attributing it to Rene Dubos - &amp;#34;think globally, act locally.&amp;#34; I take
great pride in the results I&amp;#39;ve gotten when I have been able to do
projects my way with my team - Hunter, Stuyvesant, and an assortment
of others. That reminds me of something that a very smart friend once
told me years ago when the K12 CS movement was just starting. He
predicted that &amp;#34;there will be small pockets of excellence&amp;#34; - referring
to places such as Stuy but the mainstream will be mediocre at best. I
think the mainstream overall is doing a fair deal better than mediocre
but I think his point of view was pretty prescient. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any case, I do wear my naysayer hat as a badge of honor. I think
the movement needs people like me to try to keep the mainstream
honest. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What they remember</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-remember/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 15:10:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-remember/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t blogged for a few weeks. Part of the reason is that I
haven&amp;#39;t felt that I&amp;#39;ve had too much to say. That&amp;#39;s in part because
it&amp;#39;s summer time and in part because I&amp;#39;m no longer teaching so that
means no new experiences with students, no new stories, and, at least
right now, no new CS education adventures. Part of it could also just
be that I&amp;#39;m following the trend - fewer CS Ed bloggers blogging less
frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another part of why I haven&amp;#39;t blogged for a few weeks is that I&amp;#39;ve
decided to try to write a book. Since retiring I&amp;#39;ve had a few people
mention it to me so I thought I&amp;#39;d give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been writing a few sample chapters over the last there weeks
(around 35,000 words , 75 pages so far). The plan is to alternate
chapters - one with a story from my career followed by one on teaching
something in CS or some CS pedagogical technique. Rinse and
repeat. The &amp;#34;story&amp;#34; chapters will also have some educational message
but it won&amp;#39;t be topic or in class specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll see where it goes. Even if it comes together I have no idea how
I would go about trying to get it published&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since my memory isn&amp;#39;t what it was and even if it was, our memories are
malleable I decided to reach out to my network of former students. I
know that overall I&amp;#39;ve done a solid job as a CS teacher but what
specifically was memorable. I might have loved a topic or something I
did but maybe it was a flop. On the flip side, maybe there were things
that had a major impact - good or bad and I thought they were just
throwaways. I sent an email to my alumni list and posted to Facebook
asking for the stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I got as a result is what made me think about the title for this
post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of what I got wasn&amp;#39;t a surprise. The competitive kids enjoyed
things related to the USACO. Some talked about some of the bigger
themes in the advanced classes. Everyone loved Halloween!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was surprised though with other things that came up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A surprisingly large number of responses singled out my &amp;#34;Homer the
robot&amp;#34; lesson - my day one or two activity for new CS students. I used
to do &amp;#34;Homer the Robot&amp;#34; in APCS when students took AP without any
prior class and then moved it to Intro once that class was established
and a requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Basically, I would play the part of Homer the Robot, named after Homer
Simpson, largely due to Homer&amp;#39;s well known mental capacity and also
because I&amp;#39;ve always been a huge Simpsons fan - remember I started
teaching this lesson or a variant of it back in the mid to late
90s. I&amp;#39;d set up a simple scenario - instruct Homer so that he writes
today&amp;#39;s &lt;strong&gt;aim&lt;/strong&gt; on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They would shout out instructions and hilarity would ensue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea of course was to show that computers follow simple
instructions and follow them literally. As I always tell my classes
&amp;#34;computers are horrible at doing what you want them to do but they&amp;#39;re
great at doing what you tell them to do.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d interpret or rather, misinterpret the class&amp;#39;s instructions but
eventually we&amp;#39;d get an aim on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I know this isn&amp;#39;t a unique idea. I&amp;#39;m sure while I was coming up
with it in the 90s in New York City others were doing similar things
elsewhere. It&amp;#39;s like pair programming. Industry &amp;#34;invented&amp;#34; the idea as
part of agile programming but just about every CS teacher ever
invented a variation of pair programming prior to industry ever
dreaming of two people on one computer every time that teacher was in
a computer lab with more students than working machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays you can find similar unplugged exercises a simple web search
away - things like &amp;#34;the paper plane exercise&amp;#34; or the &amp;#34;peanut butter
and jelly sandwich exercise&amp;#34; come to mind. Still, I prefer my version
but if you want to know why, you&amp;#39;ll have to read my book if it ever
comes out :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When reading my student messages, I was surprised how often Homer came
up. Sure, it was fun and the class always got laughs but there were
plenty of other classes with more laughs. Maybe because it set the
stage. Many of the students who were subject to that lesson ended up
taking two and a half years of CS and many classes with me. Maybe
because it started to demystify computing. I can&amp;#39;t say for sure but
it&amp;#39;s something I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about. Why that lesson and not any
of the hundreds to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, it&amp;#39;s interesting what they remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another theme that came up in more responses than I would have
expected didn&amp;#39;t refer to a lesson, any particular activity, or
story. It had to do with the CS class, or in many cases, the CS office
area - room 301, being a &amp;#34;safe space.&amp;#34; Interesting because I don&amp;#39;t
think people even used that term back in the day. I found that
interesting because first, it again came from more students than I
would have expected. Second, it also came from some people who were
never my student but are now in my network. They were never in my
class but still found there way to the CS corner of Stuy. Third, I
never thought I did anything special or even really thought about
making a &amp;#34;safe space,&amp;#34; particularly since that can mean very different
things to different people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those were the two biggest surprises. Not that they were mentioned but
that they were mentioned more than I would have expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were plenty of other responses. Some I expected and some not and
lots of good memory triggers as I stroll down memory lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the new semester starting for teachers around the country it&amp;#39;s
worth spending a minute thinking about it - you&amp;#39;ll all have an impact
teaching your subject area but you&amp;#39;ll also have an impact in ways you
probably wouldn&amp;#39;t think about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Have a great semester everybody!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Communities of New York</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/hidden-communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 15:09:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/hidden-communities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;m not teaching CS every day, I find the desire to maybe
write about some other things. I&amp;#39;ve still got a bunch of CS and
education posts lined up, but for today, something different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was out for my morning run a couple of days ago. I usually leave my
apartment between 5:00 and 5:45, go to the Hudson River and run an out
and back. It&amp;#39;s still pretty quiet at that time. When I leave later,
the park is much more filled with runners, running groups, and bike
commuters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m heading south and walking north is an older couple. I
say older couple but let&amp;#39;s be fair, They&amp;#39;re probably around my age and
I&amp;#39;m just older than I care to admit although based on my current pace
and recovery time, I should know better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We wave good morning to each other and keep on our way. A little
later, I see a younger man walking and running south (it was really
hot and humid). We cross paths regularly but since we were going in
the same direction and frequently wave, I slowed to join him. I said
that after waving high for a couple of years, we might as well learn
each other&amp;#39;s names. We fist bumped, or rather he went for the bump, I
went for the handshake, we switched but then finally synced. So,
that&amp;#39;s how I met Chris. We chatted for a few minutes - we both live in
Chelsea, how we both get an energy boost whenever we see our &amp;#34;running
buddies&amp;#34; in the morning, and also about some of the other early
morning runners we&amp;#39;ve met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He named Vicky, who I&amp;#39;ve been waving to for three or four years. Then
I gave him Suki - the first person I started saying hello
to. Suki and I would cross paths near Stuy, her walking north, me
running south. She would greet &lt;strong&gt;everybody&lt;/strong&gt; with a warm smile, a wave and
a strong Good Morning! After a while, I slowed my run one day to get
to know here. We also talked about Priscilla, the Mayor of Hudson
River Park - at least to us early risers. Priscilla would always be
walking or running on the path along with her magnificent dog
Buddy. Unfortunately, Buddy passed about a year ago. We both lamented
that we haven&amp;#39;t seen Priscilla lately and we both hope it&amp;#39;s because
our schedules have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We talked of a few others and I noted that I really have to introduce
myself to that couple I passed earlier and then went we on to complete
our individual morning workouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got to thinking about this community. It&amp;#39;s not a normal
community. We don&amp;#39;t all know each others names and really very little
about each other but every morning, or at least a few times a week
we&amp;#39;ve come to expect to see each other and greet each other with a
smile, a happy hello, or a thumbs up or some other encouragement. We
get a boost when we do but we grow concerned when we don&amp;#39;t see our
morning amigos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In New York, we don&amp;#39;t have that small town everyone knows their neighbors
thing. Heck, I live in a 20 story apartment building and barely know
my neighbors. We also don&amp;#39;t have neighborhood schools and the mom and
pop store everywhere is a dying breed. Yet, we still have these weird
little communities that crop up. I look forward to seeing my running
buddies again early tomorrow morning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I have (and haven&#39;t) been up to</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-ive-been-doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 11:42:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-ive-been-doing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been about a year since I taught my last class. I miss working
with the kids and truth be told, I do miss working with other
educators and tech professionals on programs, policy items and related
but I don&amp;#39;t miss any of the bureaucratic nonsense, policies made by
people who don&amp;#39;t know what they&amp;#39;re doing, nor the record keeping, grading or
paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent the first few months in what I&amp;#39;ve been calling my retirement
hibernation but more recently it&amp;#39;s been time to emerge. Time to see
where, if anywhere, I now fit in the CS/Ed/Tech space moving
forward. That&amp;#39;s both in terms of where I&amp;#39;d like to be involved and of
course the flip side, if those places or people want me involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what have I been doing in that regards?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Connecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not me connecting with new people (although I love doing that, just
haven&amp;#39;t had new opportunities) but connecting other people. A big part
of this is connecting younger former students with older, more
experienced ones - frequently for referrals. I like doing this but to
be honest, I can no longer keep track of who&amp;#39;s where – too many
former students at too many companies. Still, this is an aspect of the
StuyCS and how HunterCS families that I&amp;#39;m really proud of building and
I really get nachas when more experienced family members are there for
the younger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also had a former student who decided to spend this summer mentoring
college kids who couldn&amp;#39;t get an internship - he&amp;#39;s between jobs and
wanted to give something back. Trouble is, he wanted to work with too
many kids than would fit in his apartment. Fortunately, I was
introduced a couple of months ago to someone who just opened a new
co-working/learning space and was looking to support worthwhile
projects. I put them together and it&amp;#39;s been a win win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been enjoying doing things like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Advising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is interesting, because I generally don&amp;#39;t actually give advice. I
try to repaint the picture of the advisee so as to be sure I
understand it and then I generally talk about the questions I would
ask if I were in that situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In one case, I was put in touch with a team building a workforce
exposure/entry experience for NYC high school students. They had a lot
of workforce program experience but little tech experience. I think I
was able to add value to their efforts given my tech background and
educational experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In another instance, a friend has been working on a new school
proposal. Now, I never actually started a new school but have been
involved in school design a few times and have certainly built out a
number of programs. It was a lot of fun talking to him about his
vision and school&amp;#39;s aspirations and to share with him my perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One other recent conversation was between me and a friend who&amp;#39;s been
building a company to help in both hiring and in leveling up
employees. This is someone who I really enjoy working with. She cold
emailed me around nine years ago when she was starting a direct CS
Education program and we&amp;#39;ve been friends ever since. I really enjoyed
this conversation because it wasn&amp;#39;t the usual &amp;#34;I want to start a
coding program&amp;#34; but was still something that, with my education
background and range from small kids through workforce, I think left
me with something of value to add.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I enjoy this type of &amp;#34;advising&amp;#34; or rather, as I look at it, talking
shop and I do think that my background - having been in multiple
levels of education from early grades through college as well as in
industry and having also build numerous programs lets me add
value. Maybe I should try to set it up as a consulting thing rather
than just being there for friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, then there&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;m not doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ll be less and less involved with the national aspect of the
CSTA. Note I&amp;#39;m talking here about the national CSTA. I&amp;#39;m looking
forward to continue to work with my local NYC and regional CSTA people
whom I both like and respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple of interactions this past year really rubbed me the
wrong way. Last year, they were looking for people to join their new
Imagining CS Pathways effort. I applied for one of the roles. I wasn&amp;#39;t
selected. Now, that&amp;#39;s fine. I mean, I personally felt, after I heard
who was selected, that I had more to offer than many but that could
just be my ego. What bothered me was that I was then sent an email
asking if I was interesting in participating in a capacity that I had
explicitly said I wasn&amp;#39;t. I also wasn&amp;#39;t particularly impressed with
the report once it came out. I felt it was lacking in actual
CS. Although I didn&amp;#39;t think about this at the time, I suspect the
people who built the committee already had an opinion as to what the
end report should look like and built the committee to match. If true,
not cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later, I decided to throw my hat into the ring to run as an at large
member for the CSTA board. Now, again, I didn&amp;#39;t figure I&amp;#39;d be
elected - I think I&amp;#39;ve pissed off a number of people over the years
but I was put off when I got an email saying that they elected to
place other people on the ballot. Why did this bother me? Because it
says that there are people within the organization who can basically
shape the board by only allowing certain people on the ballot. Again,
not cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, CSTA can of course do what they want. They&amp;#39;re the big players who
get the Google money. I&amp;#39;m just a retired educator but since the
organization appears to be going in directions that I think are wrong,
there&amp;#39;s no reason for me to continue my involvement or show support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s what I won&amp;#39;t be doing. I guess it also appears that I&amp;#39;m
blogging less frequently but that seems to be the norm these
days. I&amp;#39;ll probably continue apace until something clicks and I&amp;#39;ll
do a deep dive somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philadelphia Freedom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/philly-6-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 19:02:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/philly-6-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Time for another travel post. Figured that by posting here there&amp;#39;s
more permanence and search-ability than a Facebook or other post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, Devorah and I are spending a few days in Philly. We started coming
down here a year or so ago and this is our third trip. It&amp;#39;s a nearby
getaway from NYC and we&amp;#39;ve got friends here that we rarely get to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sports fans notwithstanding I&amp;#39;m surprised that Philly doesn&amp;#39;t get more
love from NYC people looking for relatively nearby travel. It&amp;#39;s under
2 hours away, is a very walkable city, and has the things we love, in
no particular order - food, culture, history, art, architecture, and
neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did a lot of the mainstream history, rah rah America stuff in our
last couple of visits along with such gems as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.barnesfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;Barnes Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.easternstate.org/&#34;&gt;Eastern State Penitentiary&lt;/a&gt; so this time we&amp;#39;ve been looking at
some less mainstream attractions so I thought I&amp;#39;d share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the way in, we stopped at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.americanswedish.org/&#34;&gt;American Swedish Historical Museum&lt;/a&gt; in
South Philly. Great museum in a gorgeous 100 year old building. The
museum covered the early Swedish/New World history (including, for New
Yorkers like me, interesting tie ins with Peter Minuet and Peter
Stuyvesant) but had so much more. They had a room on inventor John
Ericsson and another on Swedish Nightingale, Jenny Lind, brought over
to the USA by P.T. Barnum and played all over including at Castle
Garden (nee Fort/Castle Clinton) in lower Manhattan. Also lots more
including some sketches by painter Anders Zorn and a whole bunch of
artifacts. There was also a special exhibit on Swedish candy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The highlight for Devorah was an exhibit on Swedish weaving:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/swedish1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/swedish1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/swedish1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/swedish2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/swedish2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/swedish2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/swedish3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/swedish3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/swedish3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we started off at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nps.gov/inde/planyourvisit/benjaminfranklinmuseum.htm&#34;&gt;Ben Franklin Museum&lt;/a&gt;. Pretty cool but
nothing unexpected. I recently watched Ken Burn&amp;#39;s documentary on
Franklin so I was up on his life but it&amp;#39;s a nice little museum with
some neat artifacts and it was only $5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was a real gem - the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencehistory.org/&#34;&gt;Science History Institute&lt;/a&gt;. This free
museum has artifacts and the development of science from alchemy
through modern day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A special exhibit on dyes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-dye.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-dye.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-dye.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And education in science:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-kits.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-kits.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-kits.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-books.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-books.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-books.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, Devorah found the knitting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-knitting.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-knitting.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-knitting.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We were a little &amp;#34;museumed out&amp;#34; by the end so will have to come back
but this is a must visit museum!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up, a pit stop. We ended up at &lt;a href=&#34;https://shanecandies.com/&#34;&gt;Shane Confectionary&lt;/a&gt;. America&amp;#39;s
oldest continuously running candy store. They had some old-timey
candies but they&amp;#39;re really a chocolate place, making products from
bean to bar so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/shane3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/shane3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/shane3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/shane2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/shane2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/shane2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Had a great conversation with the person
working there, purchased way too much chocolate and headed off to our
next stop - another gem - &lt;a href=&#34;https://museumforartinwood.org/&#34;&gt;The Museum for Art in Wood&lt;/a&gt; - also another
freebie ($5 suggested donation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/wood.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/wood.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/wood.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/wood3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/wood3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/wood3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/wood4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/wood4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/wood4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, lunch time. We went to a hand pulled noodle shop that we had
visited two years ago. Really tasty and super inexpensive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/noodles.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/noodles.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/noodles.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our final stop was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fabricworkshopandmuseum.org/&#34;&gt;Fabric Workshop Museum&lt;/a&gt;. Lots of interesting
stuff going on behind the scenes but for tourists like us, think of it
as a general art gallery where the medium is fabric. There were a
couple of really neat exhibits and again, free ($5 suggested). Another
winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then picked up doughnuts for later at the Reading terminal market and
wandered back to our AirBnB. On the way, we saw a number of murals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/mural.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/mural.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/mural.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And also these people holding up a skybridge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/bridge.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/bridge.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spent the evening relaxing, having reheated leftovers for dinner from
yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope you enjoy some of these less known Philly attractions when you
get to town. Tomorrow we&amp;#39;re going back to the Philadelphia Museum of
Art for their special exhibit on Mary Cassatt and will also probabyl
hit the Rodin museum and then we&amp;#39;ll figure out Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Charleston days 3 and 4 - Plantation visits and more food</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston34/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 15:11:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csed-podcast-teaching-with-masters/&#34;&gt;CS-Ed Podcast&lt;/a&gt; post, yesterday was a
washout. Seriously scary storms. We ended up spending the entire day
in the hotel but was able to get to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.middletonplace.org/&#34;&gt;Middleton Place&lt;/a&gt; for dinner. The
original plan was to do the entire plantation during the afternoon but
that was a no go. Instead we got there a little before our reservation
time which did let us wander the grounds a little before heading in to
the restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/middleton.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/middleton.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/middleton.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did this based on advise of friends and I highly recommend it. We
weren&amp;#39;t able to explore everything they have to offer but we got the
flavor of the gardens and landscaping and didn&amp;#39;t have to pay any
entrance fee. The meal was also extraordinary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was much better. We headed off to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.magnoliaplantation.com/&#34;&gt;Magnolia Plantation&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s
on most of the &amp;#34;must see&amp;#34; in Charleston lists kown for beautiful
gardens. It was nice and there was some history thrown in,
particularly when taking their included tour of the slave cabins but,
maybe since the flowers aren&amp;#39;t in full bloom yet, I wasn&amp;#39;t
overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/magnolia1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/magnolia2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The limited parts of Middleton Place that we saw made a stronger
visual impact probably due to the greater amount of terracing and
landscaping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, Magnolia boasts a host of gardens incuding a bamboo garden
and a swamp garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Speaking of which, we did end up seeing a plethora of gators. So many
that I started to feel like Mick Dundee (gotta stay with  older
generation references rather than the slightly more contemporary Steve
Irwin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was a late lunch at the Mason Jar by Fatboys, Finally got our
fried chicken fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/chicken.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/chicken.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/chicken.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the big reasons we chose Charleston was for the food. Food,
history, and culture are our big three for vacations. Walk-ability also
comes into play. We ended up at least trying pretty much all the local
food that we wanted to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hush puppies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She crab soup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrimp and grits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheese grits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried chicken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perloo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biscuits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BBQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried green tomatos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrimp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Benne wafers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pimiento cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pickled okra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to get dinner at a seafood place shortly and then home tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall a solid first post-retirement trip.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Charleston day 2 - Wrought Iron and Religion</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 19:04:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We started day 2 with a walking tour. We&amp;#39;ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://freetoursbyfoot.com/&#34;&gt;Free Tours by
Foot&lt;/a&gt; or similar services. No fee or a small reservation fee up front
and then pay what you want at the end. We generally haven&amp;#39;t been
disappointed and also generally end up tipping voluntarily about the
same amount as what we&amp;#39;d pay for a pay up front tour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We walked around downtown getting more local and US history and
learning about the city. During one stop at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://charlestonstage.com/about-us/dock-street-theatre&#34;&gt;Dock Street Theater&lt;/a&gt; we
learned about Charleston&amp;#39;s preservation and architectural restoration
efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/theater.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/theater.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/theater.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also discussed Charleston&amp;#39;s history of religious tolerance, being
known as the Holy City due to the preponderance of churches and
acceptance of all religions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/church.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/church.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/church.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also got to see a whole lot of wrought iron created by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Simmons&#34;&gt;Philip
Simmons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/iron1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/iron2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/iron3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, Devorah and I visited &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kkbe.org/&#34;&gt;KKBE&lt;/a&gt; - America&amp;#39;s first reform
Jewish congregation. They give an interesting tour. Jews started
appearing in Charleston in the late sixteen, early seventeen
hundreds. They were of Sephardic descent. This was similar to the
first Jews in New Amsterdam who came for religious tolerance (but as a
New Yorker, I have to say that they got to us first :-) ). The first
reformers from Germany came to Charleston in the 1820s and KKBE, the
first Reform Congreation in America was formed in 1841.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/synagogue.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/synagogue.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/synagogue.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is interesting for two reasons. First, this congregation,
according to our docent didn&amp;#39;t specifically follow the lead of the
reform movement in Germany. Second, Isaac Mayer Wise is normally
credited with starting the Reform Judaism movement in America when he
settled in Albany in 1846, some five years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the tour, we walked around, saw this storefront:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/scribnered.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/scribnered.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/scribnered.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Neither of us knew what the old Kress building was, now housing an H&amp;amp;M
but Devorah and I both thought &amp;#34;Damn, they were Scribnered&amp;#34; (if you
know, you know).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that S.H Kress owned a series of &amp;#34;five and dime&amp;#34; stores
and one was in this building. The store there was the cite of a noted
civil rights protest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also saw some fountains in public parks including of course, the
Pineapple Fountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/fountain.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/fountain.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/fountain.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/selfie.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/selfie.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/selfie.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended the day passing the historic marker commemorating &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Smalls&#34;&gt;Robert
Smalls&lt;/a&gt;. How is there not a movie about this guy? I won&amp;#39;t tell the
story here but if you don&amp;#39;t know who he was go read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Smalls&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/smalls.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/smalls.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/smalls.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finished off with dinner back at the Glass Onion which was again
superb. If you get down to Charleston, defiantly have a meal or two
there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow was supposed to be plantation day but there are supposed to
be nonstop thunder storms so it looks like we&amp;#39;ll probably go museum
hopping instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neighbors, Community and David Bouley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/neighbors-community-bouley/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 12:57:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/neighbors-community-bouley/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I read this morning that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ny.eater.com/2024/2/14/24072381/david-bouley-death-bouley-montrachet-brushstroke&#34;&gt;David Bouley&lt;/a&gt; has passed away at
age 70. Bouley was an influential chef in New York city. A huge
influence on the fine dining scene that has developed in the last few
decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I, a retired computer science teacher writing about a decorated
chef? As fate had it, there are some connections between David Bouley
and Stuyvesant High School, specifically the new building, where I
spent most of my career. I started teaching during a teacher shortage,
particularly in math. Actually, had there not been a shortage, I never
would have been given an emergency license and who knows what career
path I would have gone down. This meant that I was younger than most
of the other teachers my departments. Somewhat at Seward and clearly
at Stuy. There was me and Bill in our twenties and most of the rest of
the department were in their upper forties or older. At some point that
switched, and Bill and I were the old farts towards the later stages
of my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was always a foodie but was never exposed to fine dining. This was
where &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich/&#34;&gt;Rich Geller&lt;/a&gt; came in. Rich taught calc and ran the math team. He
was also big into fine dining. Bruce Winokur, another much more
experienced math teacher had similar tastes. I don&amp;#39;t remember when but
we ended up going to Bouley&amp;#39;s restaurant &amp;#34;Bouley&amp;#34; - just a couple of
blocks form Stuy for a meal. It was a revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turned out that Rich was friends with David Bouley - I think it
just started with him frequenting the restaurant and asking to speak
to the chef and that turned into something of a Stuy math department
connection. We had a biannual tradition - once during the January
regents week and again in June of taking a long lunch at Bouley. Me,
Rich, Bruce, Dawn and a rotating cast of others. And of course going
with Rich meant we always got a few bonus deserts or maybe an extra
course. It was a highlight of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Stuy/Bouley connection went further. Rich, as I mentioned ran
Stuy&amp;#39;s math team. In Spring &amp;#39;95 he arranged a special luncheon -
Stuy&amp;#39;s math team at Bouley. If I recall, the entire team was too large
so it was only the seniors. Unfortunately I couldn&amp;#39;t crash the party
but now, many years later, I&amp;#39;m friends with a number of those team
members and it was quite a memorable experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to post 9/11. We had been displaced due to the attacks
and had spent a month as guests at Brooklyn Tech. About a month
afterwards, certainly before Halloween, we were back at Stuy. It was
the evening of parent teacher conferences. Usually that evening, the
parents association hosts a dinner for the teachers. It&amp;#39;s cafeteria
style and teachers come and go at various times as long as they make
it to their room by the start of conferences. Usually it&amp;#39;s mostly pot
luck from the parents. Usually pretty tasty and certainly
appreciated. This time, as I went down the line, I said to myself
&amp;#34;Hey, I recognize that beef dish…&amp;#34; Yep, that meal was catered by
David Bouley and we got many of his on the menu dishes - at least
those that lent themselves to prior preparation and transport to the
school. I don&amp;#39;t know if this was part of his general recovery work (he
did a lot to prepare food for the rescue/recovery workers), if this
was a special arrangement made by Rich or something else but it was
exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The years continued as did the regents week lunches. Unfortunately, we
lost Rich to Cancer in the fall of 2011 (tribute post &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Shortly before his passing,
David Bouley hosted a reception at Bouley for Rich, his wife Barbara,
his friends, and former students. A touching tribute for a master
teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I spending all this time about my friend Rich and David Bouley?
Well, it&amp;#39;s about community. Stuy isn&amp;#39;t a neighborhood school. In a
neighborhood or community school, teachers and students see each other
in passing. Not so at Stuy. Only a handful of teachers live in
Manhattan or even the five boroughs. The kids? Many have commutes well
over an hour each way. Yet still, here we had this little foodie math
community at Stuy. Mostly teachers, but students were touched as
well. While we lost Rich over a decade ago, reading about David
Bouley&amp;#39;s death really brought me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve had many fine dining experiences since Rich introduced me to
Bouley&amp;#39;s restaurants. I&amp;#39;ve had great food at Jean George, Daniel, and
Park Avenue Cafe and many others but my meals at Bouley have been
special - the best overall dining experiences. I also remember some
particularly special meals - Rich&amp;#39;s reception. The surprise lunch
for a special graduating senior, when Devorah and I took Jim and Helen
there to thank them for writing the kids college recs and a handful of
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that in a lot of cultures there&amp;#39;s a strong tie between food
and community and in this weird little circle community was created
between some CS people, Math people, a specialized high school, and a
great chef.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Israel, Palestine, and antisemitism</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/israel-palestine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 16:17:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/israel-palestine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was born and bred in NYC. Went to public school and worked mostly in
the public sector. I&amp;#39;ve lived my life among one of the most diverse
populations in the world. As a Jew, I&amp;#39;ve also only lived in a
communities pn which Jews, though a minority, are accepted and
frequently assimilated. Throughout my life I&amp;#39;ve rarely faced
antisemitism personally and feel that even in the greater USA, public occurrences of
antisemitism have been relatively infrequent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the Hamas atrocities of October 7, to my view, antisemitism has
reared its ugly head big time. Not merely the blatant calls for my
people&amp;#39;s extermination from neo-nazis and the like but more subtle
antisemitism cached in the call for Palestinian liberation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before you get too upset, let me be clear - Israel has a right wing
problem, a Netenyahu problem and for years, pro Palestinian voices on
settlements have been ignored. Many Jews, including myself have been
vocal for a while against some current and past Israeli policies but
these calls aren&amp;#39;t antisemitism. I&amp;#39;m talking about the &amp;#34;pro
Palestinian&amp;#34; talking points and rallies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll go into more details but the TL;DR is pretty simple. If there&amp;#39;s a
rally and it only talks about an immediate cease fire or other Israeli
acquiescence without calling for the release of the hostages and the
end of Hamas&amp;#39; terrorist actions then that rally is antisemetic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When the slogans and signs read &amp;#34;from the river to the sea,&amp;#34; that&amp;#39;s
antisemitism - it&amp;#39;s echoing the age old call to wipe the Jews from the
face of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even when some people &amp;#34;try&amp;#34; to be balanced and say that Israel has a
right to defend itself, they follow up with a call for Israel to
immediately stop any retaliatory or defensive action knowing that
history has shown that this only empowers terrorists like Hamas. The
talking heads never actual give a reasonable course of action for
Israel other than lay down your arms which reminds me of the line
originally attributed to Golda Meir &amp;#34;If the Arabs put down their
weapons today, there would be no more violence. If the Jews put down
there weapons today, there would be no more Israel.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also worth looking at recent history. Multiple times,
Palestinians were offered a 2 state solution going back to the late
forties when modern Israel began. The Arab nations thought it better
to decline and try to destroy the Jews. This history repeated time and
again most notably at the turn of the century when Arafat said no to a
deal that would have given the Palestinians 95% of what they wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But let&amp;#39;s get back to the antisemitism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Beyond what I&amp;#39;ve already said you have to consider why nobody calls
out the Arab nations on their treatment of Palestinians (or even Hamas
who would rather build tunnels and rockets to kill Jews rather than
build infrastructure to support Palestinians). From 1947 to 1967, Arab
nations controlled Gaza and the West Bank. Where was the outcry for
Palestinian Independence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some people say that the Palestinians elected Hamas. Others note that
there hasn&amp;#39;t been a free vote in Gaza since 2006. Okay, but then why
aren&amp;#39;t there protests and rallies about that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It seems that if you&amp;#39;re Arab (or I guess European) you can abuse and
kill Palestinians and it&amp;#39;s okay, it&amp;#39;s only an issue if you&amp;#39;re Jewish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is all to say that from my point of view, a HUGE amount of the
pro Palestine posturing is thinly veiled antisemitism - no more, no
less. If people truly cared about Palestine and a two state solution
(as I do) they&amp;#39;d call out Hamas, work to rid Palestine of them, work
to establish self rule and at the same time call out Israel&amp;#39;s current
leadership and policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People have to be more aware of this and the inherent dangers but I
fear ignorance and hate are more the order of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Hague and an extra day</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/hague/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 11:18:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/hague/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last day of the trip we decided to take a day trip to The Hague. On
the way we passed through Haarlem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/haarlem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/haarlem.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/haarlem.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For some reason I couldn&amp;#39;t get this song out of my head&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kIFN13-a1iA?si=mKvczkvG-QG_6WJP&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had some time to do some wandering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/hague-canal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/hague-canal.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/hague-canal.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/palace.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/palace.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/palace.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and even stumbled upon their Chinatown:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/chinatown-hague.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/chinatown-hague.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/chinatown-hague.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
but the reason for the trip was the Escher museum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/museum.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/museum.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/museum.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cool museum in a beautiful mansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/echser1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/echser1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/echser1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/escher2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/escher2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/escher2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It had tons of Escher&amp;#39;s work along with his story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/escher3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/escher3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/escher3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/escher4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/escher4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/escher4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly liked that it had a lot of works that weren&amp;#39;t the usual
tessellations and impossible figures but of course it had those as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/escher5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/escher5.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/escher5.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/escher6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/escher6.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/escher6.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Getting back to Amsterdam we wandered around for a final time and
found their Chinatown as well&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/hague/chinatown-amsterdam.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/hague/chinatown-amsterdam.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/hague/chinatown-amsterdam.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we settled in to the hotel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We were supposed to come home today so we got to the airport nice and
early. No problem, at least until we boarded. Three hours later it was
determined that the plane had a bad part and they didn&amp;#39;t have a
spare. Even if they did it would have taken a few hours to replace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, we&amp;#39;re spending another night in Amsterdam. Just at a hotel airport
so that&amp;#39;s a little annoying. Not really the worst thing in the world
though. The hotel is fine, I&amp;#39;m assuming dinner and breakfast here will
be as well and these things happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was just hoping to get back home to Devorah and Natan after two
weeks and Batya&amp;#39;s probably sick of me already.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amsterdam days 3 and 4</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/amsterdam2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2023 09:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/amsterdam2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We started walking from our hotel to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vangoghmuseum.nl/en&#34;&gt;Van Gogh&lt;/a&gt; museum. On the way
we passed the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cowmuseum.amsterdam/&#34;&gt;Cow Parade&lt;/a&gt; store. This was pretty cool since we remember
the Cow Parade from back when it was in New York decades ago. Big
fiberglass painted cows at random spots in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/cows.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/cows.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/cows.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Van Gogh museum was pretty amazing (and also had wood
floors). While most of his best known works might be in other museums
around the world there were plenty of great ones to view and admire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/van-gogh.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/van-gogh.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/van-gogh.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were also plenty of work from his contemporaries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/monet.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/monet.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/monet.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was particularly interesting to see things like a gallery of his
influences or walls with his works surrounded by similar works by his
contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like the Rijksmuseum this is a must see. We did hear a couple comment
though while standing online that it always sells out so maybe book
tickets in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there we wanted to see the Ann Frank house&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/ann-frank.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/ann-frank.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/ann-frank.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With so much else to do we decided not to book the tour in advance and
that we&amp;#39;d just walk by. We already knew the story so thought we&amp;#39;d
rather spend the time in the WWII Resistance museum and the Jewish
Museum to learn about things we were less familiar with but would walk
by the house to see it and the neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the way we needed sustenance so we sought out a highly recommended
cookie shop but were thwarted by a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/cookies.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/cookies.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/cookies.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It looked like it would be well over a 45 minute wait. Sorry, we don&amp;#39;t
do that anymore. We found something else, walked by the Ann Frank
house, did some more wandering, had a great light lunch then took a
break back at our hotel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then the Jewish Museum. It had two parts with two additional ones
opening in March - the museum, on the site of former Ashkenazi
synagogues, the Portuguese Synagogue across the street and the two to
come pieces, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jck.nl/en/location/hollandsche-schouwburg&#34;&gt;Hollandsche Schouwburg&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jck.nl/en/location/national-holocaust-museum&#34;&gt;National Holocoust
Museum&lt;/a&gt;. The next post will cover the Portuguese Synagogue but to be
honest, the museum didn&amp;#39;t thrill either of us. The general Judaism
section was fine but not inspirational and the organization had you
jumping from station to station in what appeared to be random
order. They had some interesting artifacts and we learned a bit but it
wasn&amp;#39;t super engaging to us. The Holocaust section also was pretty
subdued. To be honest, the WWII Resistance museum painted a better
picture of the Holocaust as did the Brussels museum. I&amp;#39;d also rank the
NY and DC ones better. As to the straight Jewish part we also liked the
Brussels museum more and I&amp;#39;ll put in a plug here for the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theweitzman.org/&#34;&gt;Weitzman Museum&lt;/a&gt; in Philly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In all fairness though this isn&amp;#39;t counting the Portuguese Synagogue
which was included in admission but we couldn&amp;#39;t go to yet since it was
closed for Simchat Torah and who knows what the forthcoming two sites
will add to the overall experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Staying on our cultural theme, we&amp;#39;ve been noticing many bagel shops in
Amsterdam so we thought we&amp;#39;d try one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/bagel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/bagel.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/bagel.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended up taking out form &lt;a href=&#34;https://soupenzo.nl/&#34;&gt;Soup En Zo&lt;/a&gt;, a really good soup place
and pairing the soups with Bagels from Tony&amp;#39;s NY Bagels across the
street. The soups were great and the bagels were surprisingly
good. Not too large, good chew - better than some lesser NY ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was it for day 3. Day 4 started with the Amsterdam
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hetscheepvaartmuseum.com/&#34;&gt;Maritime Museum&lt;/a&gt;. Really interesting. Some good history of the region
as well as boat and boat history. I really liked the modalities
used. Many galleries combined wonderful art - paintings in particular
to tell the story of Amsterdam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/maritme.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/maritme.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/maritme.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also had a replica of an old 18th century trade ship that you
could explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/smallroom.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/smallroom.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/smallroom.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pretty cramped particularly when you consider that statistically
people form the Netherlands are the tallest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also had old maps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/map.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/map.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/map.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/maps.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/maps.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/maps.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ship models:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/gig.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/gig.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/gig.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For lunch we then walked out to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Java-eiland&#34;&gt;Java Eiland&lt;/a&gt; where we passed the Meta
offices but Batya didn&amp;#39;t go in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/meta.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/meta.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/meta.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And then back near the Hotel to finally visit the Portuguese Synagogue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/synagogue.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/synagogue.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/synagogue.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/synagogue2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/synagogue2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/synagogue2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wow. While we were disappointed in the Jewish Museum, this part, which
was right across the street made it super worth it. You basically
walked around the outer perimeter of the site going in and out of
buildings where various religious functions occurred and got to hear
about the function and specific history from past congregations. We
also went in to explore the sanctuary. Again, wow. Big, beautiful,
candle lit (that is, no electricity) and in fact is still functioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As much as the previous days museum visit was meh, this pushed the
overall experience over the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s it for today except for a new place for dinner which we&amp;#39;ll head
out for soon. Tomorrow, the plan is to go to the Hague for the Escher
Museum and then Wednesday, back to NYC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amsterdam, the first two days</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/amserdam1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 11:36:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/amserdam1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Final leg of the trip in Amsterdam. Train ride and hotel went smoothly
but we were hungry so got a quick bite across from the Rembranthuis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/rembranthuis.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/rembranthuis.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/rembranthuis.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After some wandering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/market.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/market.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/market.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/canal.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/canal.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/canal.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/amsterdam-selfie.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/amsterdam-selfie.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/amsterdam-selfie.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
we found our way to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.verzetsmuseum.org/&#34;&gt;WWII Dutch Resistance Museum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Great place to go if you want to be both proud and inspired and
depressed at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It contained propaganda from both sides&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/posters.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/posters.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/posters.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/foldup.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/foldup.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/foldup.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Photos of hiding people and equipment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/hiding1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/hiding2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/hiding3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/hiding4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/hiding4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/giraffe.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/giraffe.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/giraffe.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and relayed the horror and tragedy that occurred during the Holocaust
highlighting the brave acts of many to try to save lives as well as
the stories of those who acquiesced and for the most part, regretted
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It left an impact and if you&amp;#39;re in Amsterdam I highly recommend it,
particularly give the direction of things with the Republicans in the
United States these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dinner after that was a real treat. Batya and I got dinner with my old
student Artem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/artem.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/artem.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/artem.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Artem graduated Stuy in I think 2000 and I was marginally in touch but
hadn&amp;#39;t seen him since the early part of this century. When I announced
to my alumni community that I was heading to the Netherlands and
asking for recs, Artem chimed in and we coordinated. Such a treat to
reconnect with a former student in person. To be able to see him doing
well in life so many years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We got dinner at Entrepot and it was one of the best meals I&amp;#39;ve had in
years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/dinner.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/dinner.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/dinner.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was it for day 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Day 2 started with another Sandeman tour. Got an overview of the city
and learned some interesting things. One stood out. We learned about
these &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stolperstein&#34;&gt;Stumbling Stones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/stumble-stones.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/stumble-stones.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/stumble-stones.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
placed in front of houses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/ss-building.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/ss-building.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/ss-building.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
memorializing victims of the Holocaust. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also stopped by the former home of the Dutch West India Company&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/west-indies.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/west-indies.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/west-indies.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and talked about Dutch colonial times including New Amsterdam. It was
cool that our guide was into the Amsterdam/New Amsterdam thing and was
currently reading &amp;#34;The Island at the Center of the World&amp;#34; and had it
in his bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After that lunch at a pancake restaurant recommended by Artem. It was
in a repurposed carousel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/carousel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/carousel.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/carousel.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/nl&#34;&gt;Rijksmuseum&lt;/a&gt;. Many amazing artworks including
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/nl&#34;&gt;The Night Watch&lt;/a&gt; but here is a less famous one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/riijks2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/riijks2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/riijks2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All I can say is amazing place. Also props to the designers on the
wooden floors - much easier on the feet than stone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final treat we saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.grachtenrace.amsterdam/&#34;&gt;De Grachtenrace Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt; - a rowing race in
the canals. We wanted to catcht it but didn&amp;#39;t know exactly where or
when it was running - just the day. We saw around 20 boats race by
right after we left the museum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/amsterdam/rowing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/amsterdam/rowing.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/amsterdam/rowing.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Batya and I did this type of rowing and racing withe the &lt;a href=&#34;https://villagecommunityboathouse.org/&#34;&gt;Village
Community Boathouse&lt;/a&gt; out of pier 40 when she was at Stuy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was it for our first couple of days in Amsterdam with a lot more
to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antwerp in 24 hours</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/antwerp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 10:10:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/antwerp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Heading to Amsterdam this morning and we&amp;#39;ll be here until mid next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We spent yesterday in Antwerp but for a while we didn&amp;#39;t know if we
were going to get there. Unbeknownst to us when we planned our trip,
yesterday was the season&amp;#39;s first general strike in Belgium. When we
found out in Brussels we weren&amp;#39;t sure we&amp;#39;d be able to get out of the
city at all but it turned out that while the local trains would be out
the intercity ones were going business as usual. Since we couldn&amp;#39;t get
to the required train station easily our host Helen drove us be she
had to do so before work. This meant that we arrived in Antwerp at
around 8:00am. Not a big deal. It was too early to check into our
hotel but we were able to leave our heavier bags and set out for
breakfast and a day of exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, even before that, we came in to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerpen-Centraal_railway_station&#34;&gt;Antwerp Central Station&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/train1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/train1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/train1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/train2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/train2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/train2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s really amazing. The original station goes back to the mid 19th
century with the current one replacing it around 50 years later. The
facade and entry are gorgeous but going back to the track area is
equally amazing. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerpen-Centraal_railway_station&#34;&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; has more and better images so
check them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was also this elevator status wall noting the levels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/zero-index.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/zero-index.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/zero-index.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Gotta love the zero indexing of the floors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After breakfast we wandered around&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/building.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/building.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/building.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/buildings.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/buildings.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/buildings.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and among other things found this, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brabo_Fountain&#34;&gt;Brabo Fountain&lt;/a&gt; in front of city
hall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/statue1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/statue1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/statue1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/statue2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/statue2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/statue2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Very cool. We also passed the cathedral seen in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the side, we saw these builders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/builders.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/builders.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/builders.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and realized why cathedrals, including our local St. John&amp;#39;s the
Unfinished take so long - the builders are made of bronze and don&amp;#39;t
move!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was on our way to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Het_Steen&#34;&gt;Het Steen&lt;/a&gt; castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/selfie-castle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/selfie-castle.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/selfie-castle.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It had an old school instagram frame:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/insta-castle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/insta-castle.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/insta-castle.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/insta.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/insta.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/insta.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Inside was &amp;#34;The Antwerp Story&amp;#34; which had a nice overview of the city
and you could climb to the top as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there we tried to go to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://museumplantinmoretus.be/en/content/welcome-museum-plantin-moretus&#34;&gt;Plantin Moretus&lt;/a&gt; museum but were
thwarted - it was closed due to the strike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/closed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/closed.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/closed.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/closed-2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/closed-2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/closed-2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there it was to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antwerp_Zoo&#34;&gt;Antwerp Zoo&lt;/a&gt; - the oldest zoo in the
country. It was right next to the train station and just 10 minutes
from our hotel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We saw lots of animals including this meerkat just standing there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/meerkat.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/meerkat.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/meerkat.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He was just standing there on his hind too legs you know, like that
guy - you know the one who stands - Rory Calhoun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And also elephants:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/elephants.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/elephants.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/elephants.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And many more. There was also a nice little aquarium building where we
found Dory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/antwerp/dory.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/antwerp/dory.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/antwerp/dory.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After all of that we went back to the Hotel but they still didn&amp;#39;t have
our room so we wandered some more - by the Ruben&amp;#39;s house which is
closed for renovations and over to a local park. Then back to the
Hotel where they screwed up our room but we did finally get it
partially resolved - at least so that we had a roof over our head for
the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We finished off the day with a pretty awesome Ethiopian meal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning we got some more chocolate for the road and are now on
the train to Amsterdam where we&amp;#39;ll spend the next five days.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brussels</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/brussels/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 01:29:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/brussels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We spent the last few days in Brussels. Got in on the Eurostar at
around 1:00. We were crashing with a good friend - a teacher who
worked with Devorah back in the day but left NY and is now in
Brussels. The catch was that she wasn&amp;#39;t getting home from work until
5:00 so we had to occupy ourselves until then. Schelpping around
rolling suitcases usually isn&amp;#39;t a big deal but there were two
challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, schlepping around rolling suitcases is much harder on cobbled
streets, particularly when it&amp;#39;s unseasonably warm and most museums -
you know - tourist attractions with coat rooms are closed in Brussels
on Mondays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended up at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brussels-comics-figurines-museum.be/en/&#34;&gt;Brussels Comics Figurines Museum&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Very cool. The first featured comic strip was &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marsupilami&#34;&gt;The Marsupilami&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/marsupilami.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/marsupilami.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/marsupilami.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of figurines and a running cartoon. Fun stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were lots more:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/comic2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/comic2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/comic2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/comic4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/comic4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/comic4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/comic1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/comic1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/comic1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some I knew like Tintin and the Smurfs and some I didn&amp;#39;t. Lots of
interesting backstory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My favorite was, of course, Asterix (and of course Obelix):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/comic3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/comic3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/comic3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the museum we puttered around a bit, refueled on a waffle and
made it to our host&amp;#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/waffle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/waffle.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/waffle.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started off the next day with a free tour. Well, sort of. We went
on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.neweuropetours.eu/brussels-walking-tours/&#34;&gt;Sandeman&lt;/a&gt; tour. They&amp;#39;re free and request you tip based on whatever
value you feel you received. Devorah and Batya have used them before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand-Place&#34;&gt;Grand Place&lt;/a&gt; talked a bit about it&amp;#39;s and the city&amp;#39;s
history and walked and learned about Brussels for the next almost
three hours. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/gp3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/gp3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/gp3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/gp4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/gp4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/gp4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Batya and I both very much enojyed the tour. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kbr.be/en/ &#34;&gt;KBR&lt;/a&gt; museum. This was recommended by a friend. There was
some local history but mostly it was about illuminated manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/kbr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/kbr.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/kbr.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They had some history on Illuminated Manuscripts as well as on how
they were made and sported an impressive collection. The oldest we saw
was form the 900s. Extremely cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That evening we got dinner with our friend Helen and a bunch of her
colleagues. Helen is now teaching in Brussels so I asked her to set up
a dinner with her CS or related teachers. They don&amp;#39;t strictly do CS,
they do ICT which has some CS and coding in it but also trends to what
we would cover on the CTE side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I loved meeting and talking with all of them. Learned a bit about what
it was like for them and what&amp;#39;s going on in CS Ed in their school,
Belgium and other places in Europe and I hope I was also able to share
some interesting insights form our side. I might blog more about all
of this at some later date but it was really a highlight for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, our last day in Brussels we started at the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brusselsmuseums.be/en/museums/jewish-museum-of-belgium&#34;&gt;Jewish&lt;/a&gt;
Museum. It covered the expected intro to Judiasm, had a
Holocaust section and a few exhibits by and about Jewish artists from
or related to Belgium. I was particularly interested in the first two
things - I wanted to see how they were covered in Europe. Very
interesting and as with everything else we&amp;#39;ve seen, worth a visit. I
particularly liked the information about development and histories of
some of the congregations that formed in Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the afternoon we decided to go castle hunting with Helen. First up
was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.castles.nl/grimbergen-castle&#34;&gt;Grimbergen&lt;/a&gt;. Cool old castle but mostly ruins. We were able to walk
around and liked it but it was a short stop - not that much there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/castle1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/castle1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/castle1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then found our way to Chateau de Bouchout at Plantentuin
Meise. Cool castle but also in a botanic garden. We walked a couple of
the sections and went through a pretty amazing greenhouse. Plus
teachers got free entry. Another win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/castle4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/castle4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/castle4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/brussels/castle3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/brussels/castle3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/brussels/castle3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all three successful days of touring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We almost had an adventure the next day - this morning on our way to
Antwerp but I&amp;#39;ll save that for the next post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>~~Lost in the~~ Locked out of Amazon</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/lost-in-the-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 08:00:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/lost-in-the-amazon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A friend of mine reached out the other day, it turns out a friend of
theirs was all of a sudden locked out of Amazon. Couldn&amp;#39;t view videos,
couldn&amp;#39;t purchase, as far as I could tell and couldn&amp;#39;t get to their
paid for content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Amazon said that the user violated their terms of service but didn&amp;#39;t
specify how or when and after a couple of back and forths they
declared the case closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is actually pretty scary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Amazon is such a dominant player - there are plenty of things ranging
from their original content - books to ebooks to daily necessities and
food and even drugs these days. Just as Walmart has become the only
option for some, Amazon has become the only option for certain things
for others and to be summarily locked out with no warning and no
recourse is both scary and should be alarming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a result of both capitalism and tech. As single big players
take more and more control and the human element disappears more and
more both due to lack of storefronts and even lack of people
responding to calls and emails consumers are left in a precarious
spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t been locked out of Amazon but recently had my own similar
although less potentially damaging incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I docked a CitiBike at Union Square. The lock was good but their
server didn&amp;#39;t close the ride. I immediately called. The customer
support agent noted that the station was offline and that they&amp;#39;d make
a note of it on my account so that when things cleared up I wouldn&amp;#39;t
be charged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next day, I was charged. A couple of hundred dollars + $1000 more
since they said the bike was never returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent far too much time emailing and calling and while Lyft,
CitiBike&amp;#39;s parent company readily admitted that my account had the 
notation saying I did it right and that they were in error, they
refused to do anything. In the old days, you could usually get bumped
up to a higher level but current systems are much better at preventing
users from getting to people that can resolve problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ultimately, the only way I as able to get a response and resolution
was to publicly Tweet to Lyft and CitiBike with the problem and
complaint. Once I did that the problem was cleared up in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, mind you, the only way this got solved was by publicly shaming
the company on Twitter. That seems to be the only way to get real
customer support these days and with Musk killing Twitter that avenue
is sure to disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the state of commerce and in many cases living these days int
he US and those at the bottom economic rung are the most hurt - they
don&amp;#39;t have friends at companies that can help, alternatives to the
cheapest services, and can&amp;#39;t absorb the hit of &amp;#34;just paying the $2.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not directly related but it makes me think about how sad things are
when so much primary health care ends up being GoFundMe campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We have to do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those of us who teach CS and Technology though have a platform to do
better. As technology advances we have to ask more if we should rather
than if we can and as teachers we have to get that mindset into our
kids. In the short term I&amp;#39;m not hopeful for change but education is
the long term and we have to do a better job collectively on all those
things around the tech that drive policy and ways of implementing
things and ultimately greatly affect lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As an unrelated end note I&amp;#39;ve been trying to post at least once a week
these past few months. At least one blog post and one emacs
video. Tomorrow I&amp;#39;ll beheaded off to Utrecht, Brussels and Amsterdam
with my daughter for a couple of weeks so there probably won&amp;#39;t be any
new content until I&amp;#39;m back. Looking forward to the trip - I think this
will be the longest I&amp;#39;ve been away from home maybe ever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cleaning out the office</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-out-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 15:40:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cleaning-out-office/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, Devorah, Batya, and I drove up to Hunter to start to
clean out my office - the next step in officially becoming retired. I
wasn&amp;#39;t really looking forward to it. When I moved from Stuy to Hunter
it was something of a rush so I basically boxed everything up that I
thought I wanted to keep and moved it to the new digs. So, three
decades worth of accumulated crap to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had already gone through all the books trying hard to leave as many
as possible for other remaining faculty members and students but there
was still many books, personal computer equipment, puzzles and other
office decorations, the mini kitchen and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, packing up brought many memories and artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of the highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Yearbooks
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Stuy Yearbooks from 1995 - my first CS grads through 2015 and Stuy
Yearbooks are &lt;strong&gt;big&lt;/strong&gt;. I got one every year - a nice keepsake and I also
had a rule - when a student asked me to sign their yearbook, I told
them I would but only if the signed mine. The problem? No way do I
have room in my Manhattan apartment for what would be a HUGE shelve of
books. I decided to consolodate. The only thing I cared about was what
the students wrote so I cut out the signature pages and now the whole
bundle is thinner than one yearbook. Looking over them what&amp;#39;s cool is
just how many of those kids I&amp;#39;m still at least tangentially in touch
with today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s me in 1994:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/office/churl.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Okay, not really. This was given to me in the Spring of 1994 by one of
my math students. He doodled every day but it never prevented him from
being an active participant in class. Apparently other teachers gave
him a hard time. He said he appreciated it and gave me the sketch. His
family moved out of state that summer so I never saw him again but we
reconnected on Facebook years alter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
A really old mousepad
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/office/mousepad.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t used a mousepad in decades but still have this one. It&amp;#39;s a
picture of me and three of my students. They&amp;#39;re all graduating seniors
in the picture and I had just taken them out for a congratulatory and
thank you lunch at one of the 6th street Indian restaurants. Dave&amp;#39;s (one
of the students) father had the mousepads made for all of us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All four of those students have gone on to do great and interesting
things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
A frustrated student
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/office/line-drawing.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One day one of my students came in to my office rather frustrated and
this drawing was the result. An amazing student and an amazing person
who has also gone on to wonderful things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
A breakthrough
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/office/sched.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had to commemorate this. For years, I worked to bring CS to Stuy. I
had some success and some failures. One of the fights was to allow
Stuy seniors to take our senior post AP CS electives instead of a
tech/shop class. There were already excemptions from tech/shop classes
for band, orchestra, and chorus but not for CS. There were and are
some strong tech/shop classes but some were, quite frankly, joke
classes. Meanwhile the advanced CS classes were regarded as high level
and rigorous so this was frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This changed in February 2010 when we finally got the administration
to allow the substitution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Ticket printing
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/office/ticket.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This wasn&amp;#39;t a Stuy student memory but rather a personal one. At some
point during my Stuy career students started to invite me to Sing! and
other student productions. At one point I took notice of the
tickets. They were computer printed tickets and, as I suspected,
printed by the company Arcus Simplex Brown. This one was from 2012 but
I have one from a couple of years later as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, and this is purely coincidental, I wrote the ticket
printing program as my first coding gig when I was a senior in HS and
through college. That was back in 1984. It was written in compiled
Basic and ran on a small computer running CP/M. It drove a custom line
printer onto ticket stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was a great real life example of how you never know how long your
code will be running in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Misc stuff
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also found a bunch of old gradesheets from back before I started
using Google Docs for records as well as a bunch of those letters from
MIT and other colleges you get when a student identifies you as being
influential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been spending most of today trying to find places for all the
stuff and I hope I&amp;#39;ll be done soon since I have at least one more car
load to go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/office/remaining.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&amp;#39;s a lot of stuff and a lot of memories. Just wanted to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Affirmative Action</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/affirmative-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 16:48:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/affirmative-action/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today our Supreme Court ruled 6-3 to eliminate racial considerations
in admissions decisions or affirmative action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This will be celebrated by some and reviled by others even though it
probably won&amp;#39;t make a huge difference in terms of class makeup at most
&amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; institutions. Given my leanings and who I follow, you can
probably guess which views I&amp;#39;m seeing more of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The cases that have generally been brought against institutions
implementing affirmative action usually amount to &amp;#34;I was more
qualified than the affirmative action candidate you took&amp;#34; with public
cries of &amp;#34;you&amp;#39;re lowering standards.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Could either of these claims hold water?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at the lowering standards side. Either the accepted
candidate was set up and able to succeed in the school or they are
not. If they weren&amp;#39;t, well, that would have come clean long ago given
that we&amp;#39;ve had affirmative action for a long time. So, it would appear
that these candidates that &amp;#34;got in over me&amp;#34; are able to survive and
thrive. This could be because intuitions like Harvard are much harder
to get in than to graduate from but whatever. Doesn&amp;#39;t sound like a
standards issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we want to talk about lowering standards however, how about
athletes that &amp;#34;didn&amp;#39;t come here to play school&amp;#34; or legacy admits -
I can think of a couple of recent Presidents who were, well, let&amp;#39;s say
not high intellects but somehow attended our &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34;
institutions. Personally, if you eliminate my Stuy grads from the
equation, I&amp;#39;ve met as many dummies who went to the
Harvards of the world as I&amp;#39;ve met geniuses. Well connected dummies who
ran in the right circles and went to the right schools but dummies
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What about &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m more qualified?&amp;#34; Well, schools like Harvard or really
any elite school can pretty much shape their incoming classes however
they&amp;#39;d like. The pool of qualified applicants - students who will go
through four years and graduate successfully - dwarfs the size of the
accepted class. Just looking at Stuy numbers from when I was there,
for every student Harvard accepted, I could point to dozens who would
have fared just as well who were rejected. Now project that
nationally. There&amp;#39;s no doubt in my mind that affirmative action
candidates would be easily in the qualified pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It made me remember something I read that Malcolm Gladwell once wrote
or said. Something like that Harvard had so many qualified graduates
that if they really cared about being fair, they should take all the
qualified applicants and then select randomly. No athletes, no legacy,
nothing special. Of course, that would never happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I get that when you&amp;#39;re qualified and aren&amp;#39;t accepted you might
want to cry out &amp;#34;unfair&amp;#34; and maybe it is, but it&amp;#39;s not unfair because
of an affirmative action candidate. It&amp;#39;s unfair because it&amp;#39;s arbitrary
and tons of qualified applicants get turned away for no apparent
reason not because of affirmative action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The end result    today is that colleges are free to keep those legacy
admits, big donor admits, or whatever but heaven help you if you deign
to consider anything to help balance the scales for marginalized
groups or anything to try to help build equity in our country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I do have one issue with affirmative action. It can be a
distracter. Distract from what? The big picture problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Affirmative action can help but the students that they can admit are
qualified to be accepted to these elite institutions. That says that
either they&amp;#39;re from situations where they&amp;#39;ve had available to them
some or all of the advantages that the rich white kids have had or
that they&amp;#39;ve already rose above the challenges to make themselves
viable candidates. If so, good on them and good for rewarding them but
the issue has to be addressed much earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We have so many issues that have to be resolved with education,
poverty, health care, housing, all of which hits our vulnerable
populations the hardest and until as a nation we decide to address
those we&amp;#39;re not truly going to have a fair equitable
society. Unfortunately, a significant portion of our country doesn&amp;#39;t
want to solve these problems and injustices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime, a handful of students who, well, quite frankly,
deserved to be admitted to Harvard anyway, getting admissions as
affirmative action is nice for them but its no game changer. It&amp;#39;s feel
good window dressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not saying this to diminish the problems with today&amp;#39;s ruling but
we really have to attack the big problems and not just around the
edges. It&amp;#39;s like programs like Prep for Prep. Prep for Prep&amp;#39;s mission
is to &amp;#34;develop future leaders by creating access for young people of
color to first-rate educational, leadership development and
professional advancement opportunities.&amp;#34; They identify individual
students who they feel show promise and get them into elite private
schools (and pay the tuition). Great for those kids but it&amp;#39;s a small
number and it doesn&amp;#39;t do anything to fix any problems in the system as
a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s my two cents. I&amp;#39;m as angered by today&amp;#39;s ruling as the next
person but to me it&amp;#39;s a reminder that it&amp;#39;s not about getting a few
kids into &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; institutions. It&amp;#39;s about making the all the
institutions &amp;#34;elite.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Last Class</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/last-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 15:40:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/last-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, this morning I taught my last two classes as a full time
teacher. I still have grading for a few weeks and then some other
things to wrap up my programs and, due to my contract and how terminal
leave works I won&amp;#39;t officially be retired for a few more months but
today was kind of my last day of actual work, work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some approximate stats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taught approximately 290 specific course sections (probably a little more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taught somewhere between 6,000 and 12,000 different students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created more than 12 courses from whole cloth to go with new
version of a dozen or so more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started three major programs from scratch (StuyCS, Hunter honors CS, Hunter
CS Teacher Education) along with a non-profit and it&amp;#39;s programs
(CSTUY), Google CAPE, and aided in the design of others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;#39;m sure I&amp;#39;m forgetting things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today&amp;#39;s lesson was pretty cut and dry - managed pointers in C++ and
some advice for what my first year students could do over the summer
to prepare for what&amp;#39;s next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was asked in class if today felt weird, exciting, sad, special or
anything else given it was a &amp;#34;last&amp;#34; day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had to say no. It didn&amp;#39;t but maybe that was more of a reflection of
how I look at things than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today really didn&amp;#39;t feel much different than any last day of
semester. Why? Probably because I&amp;#39;ve never been goal oriented. It&amp;#39;s
always been the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I explained to the class after my student asked that just because I
was retiring from Hunter and moving on to some other ventures
(whatever they turn out to be) it really wasn&amp;#39;t different from other
years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a teacher, particularly a HS teacher of seniors, every year is an
ending. Every year, you say goodbye to a crop of students that you&amp;#39;ve
invested in, gotten to know, and many times, gotten attached to. Next
year, you begin again with a new group, or more likely, groups
overlap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of the graduates, some will keep in touch, some won&amp;#39;t. For those that
do stay in touch, the teacher and student continue to have a
relationship - I&amp;#39;ve been amazingly fortunate in the students that have
decided to stay in touch. For those that don&amp;#39;t, both sides have
memories of the shared time together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I left Stuy, it was the same as other years. I moved to Hunter
College and still got to work with terrific young people (and later
teachers). Of the Stuy kids from the year I left, some are still in my
circles, some are not - just like every other year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;m leaving Hunter, it&amp;#39;s the same with my Hunter kids (and
teachers). the only difference is that I won&amp;#39;t have a new crop come
the Fall and that&amp;#39;s alright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m looking forward to some time in the Fall when we&amp;#39;ll try to have a
big get together of my former students and I&amp;#39;m also looking forward to
whatever I decide to do next. I&amp;#39;ll look back, just like I always do
and think about the students I&amp;#39;ve taught (and while I can&amp;#39;t speak for
other teachers, yes, I do think about my former students and how their
doing a fair bit) but now, I&amp;#39;ll also look over my career arc as a
whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, nothing special for today just the next step in the journey. The
only difference is for the first time in a while I don&amp;#39;t know where
the journey leads.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m a fan of teachers but not of teacher appreciation week</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-appreciation-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 15:48:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-appreciation-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s once again teacher appreciation week. That&amp;#39;s a week late in the
semester ostensibly celebrating our teachers. Over the years there
have been a few highlight moments for me during these teacher
appreciation weeks but overall, I can&amp;#39;t say I&amp;#39;ve been a fan of the
&amp;#34;event.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Because it&amp;#39;s usually made up, superficial, and frequently patronizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some stores offer discounts. Staples and Office Depot offering
essentially discounts on supplies for the classroom that teachers
shouldn&amp;#39;t have to purchase in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other places offer a free beverage or discounts on whatever their
products were but hey, if teachers were paid reasonably to begin with
they wouldn&amp;#39;t need these discounts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Basically, my problem is that teachers are not generally appreciated
year round and they should be. Sure, it&amp;#39;s nice to have a &amp;#34;special day&amp;#34;
or week but when you spend all year dumping on, underpaying, and
overworking teachers it rings hollow. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the flip side, there have been some teacher appreciation week highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest highlight, although, to be honest, it&amp;#39;s just as special
when it happens at random times over the years has been when a former
student whom I haven&amp;#39;t been in contact with reaches out with a random
thank you. It&amp;#39;s usually not public and usually a short email or
similar but that&amp;#39;s pretty cool and pretty special. Sometimes the fact
that it&amp;#39;s teacher appreciation week spurs a student to reconnect so
that&amp;#39;s cool. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other was one particular appreciation day gift. At Stuy, over the
years, the principal and/or department chairs have frequently given
small gifts to their staffs. They&amp;#39;re usually small and frequently
useful like my math department umbrella but there was one year when
the gift stood out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I forget the year but Jinx Perullo was the principal. Instead of the
usual small gift, she got business cards for every staff member. We
all had email accounts at stuy.edu thanks to me and my student
sysadmins so every card had the teachers name, department, and
stuy.edu email. I had an office and a phone but I don&amp;#39;t know what was
on the cards in terms of phone numbers for other teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought it was a great little gift. As the profession has been under
attack since before I joined and teachers were always treated as less
than professional this was more than a gift. It was a sign of
respect. Most teachers didn&amp;#39;t really have many uses for business cards
but it made an impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s my take on teacher appreciation week. I&amp;#39;d be fine without
the week, better to treat teachers better year round.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The College Board wasn&#39;t cowardly</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-board-ap-aastudies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 08:52:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-board-ap-aastudies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
As I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;re aware, recently, in his latest racist, fascist
proclamation, Ron DeSantis threatened to stop offering AP African
American Studies (APAAS) in Florida because, well, we can&amp;#39;t actually teach our
children anything resembling our actual rather checkered history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;re also aware that the College Board just announced
changes to APAAS which basically removed everything DeSantis found
objectionable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been seeing articles, blog posts, Tweets and more all calling the
College Boards act a cowardly one. I disagree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be cowardly, the College Board would have had to have wanted to do
the right thing - stick to their current course but ultimately cave
under pressure. I don&amp;#39;t think the college board cared enough. If you
really look at the college board and its history. It&amp;#39;s not about
education and student opportunity. It&amp;#39;s always been about money and brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I remember correctly, the Florida government pays for AP exams (at
least it used to). This is a tremendous cash cow for the CB. For
them, the calculus isn&amp;#39;t &amp;#34;what should students study in APAAS.&amp;#34; The
calculus is &amp;#34;how much money do we stand to lose.&amp;#34; To them, this way
they get to keep Florida and other red state money and they&amp;#39;re
figuring that even the schools and districts who are claiming outrage
will still offer APAAS and other AP exams. The schools will vent but
ultimately say that they can teach a superset of the AP class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The College Board wins. DeSantis and the far right nuts win and only
the students lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have no doubt that some (many?) will disagree with my stance. Mostly
people who have bought in to the college board for years, and in some
cases worked for or with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One can try to rationalize and say that the capitulation was so soon
after DeSantis&amp;#39; proclamation that they had to have these changes in
the works already. True but does anyone really believe that DeSantis&amp;#39;
public statement was the first time the CB got wind that this was
going to be a PR issue they&amp;#39;d have to deal with?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the College Board offers two things - high
stakes exams and branding. That&amp;#39;s it. The more tests they sell and the
better perceived their brand, the better it is for the college
board. It&amp;#39;s no about education. If it were, then it wouldn&amp;#39;t be all
about a single test per subject. If it were, they wouldn&amp;#39;t have create
the PSAT 8 9. If it were, we wouldn&amp;#39;t see the pivot from being about
college level courses to APCS-P.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, people will say that APCS-P was all about increasing exposure,
diversity, and equity but you can&amp;#39;t deny that creating an easy AP and
keeping the same branding as college level classes all with a tech
boom going on was going to sell a lot of exams. Particularly when
schools, not students paid and more exams given means higher ratings
for schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides, a broken clock is still right twice a day. CB can be all
about CB and not about students but still from time to time do right
by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also reminded of a report I saw decades ago where the then leader
of the CB claimed that the only thing the SAT was a predictor of was
how you would do on future SAT exams. Somewhere down the line, that
changed to it was a college predictor. That&amp;#39;s now being put to the
test as more colleges are dropping the exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Truth be told, while having SAT scores on an applicants packet has
been useful as for baseline comparisons. Now that I&amp;#39;m on my second SAT
free cohort I can say that the SAT really isn&amp;#39;t important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While some of us have pushed back, the CS Ed community has been far
too accepting of the College Board as they&amp;#39;ve become more and more
influential in the K12 Ed Space. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, we should remember that the CB is a business and the
business is in selling exams. They&amp;#39;re not teachers. They might hire
teachers but they&amp;#39;re test makers and have their own agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s no reason to believe they care about justice or equity over
selling exams. They didn&amp;#39;t act cowardly. They acted in their own self
interest. As teachers, we work in our students best interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s a difference and we have to remember that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Layoffs and Workers Rights</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-layoffs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 10:59:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/tech-layoffs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Lots of layoffs in big tech recently. Overall lousy but I am
encouraged by the number of people trying to organize the local
community to be supportive in helping those affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Clearly this &amp;#34;correction&amp;#34; can turn current employees worlds upside
down and place individuals and families in precarious financial
situations but the effects also affect the incoming workforce. In
addition to layoffs, internships and offers have been canceled left
and right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Things are bad but are they bad enough to convince not only those
directly affected but also those who could be to make things better? I
hope so but I&amp;#39;m skeptical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I say those affected rather than the tech industry because I&amp;#39;ve been
thinking a lot about the state of labor recently and changes, just like
during the heyday of the labor movement, changes will only
come when demanded by the masses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I get it that when a market contracts, an economy turns down or there
are unforeseen shifts like a global pandemic, money doesn&amp;#39;t flow and
people lose jobs. I get it but that&amp;#39;s not really what I&amp;#39;m seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m seeing left and right that &amp;#34;profits are down.&amp;#34; Read that
carefully. &amp;#34;Profits are Down,&amp;#34; not losses are up. When you say profits
are down, you&amp;#39;re not saying you&amp;#39;re losing money. You&amp;#39;re saying you&amp;#39;re
making money, just not as much. It&amp;#39;s like the Wall Street mindset that
turned me off so many years ago. If you buy a stock, it goes
up, yo sell, you make money. If it then goes up more, the Wall Street
mind thinks you&amp;#39;ve lost money. That&amp;#39;s not healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If companies were just trimming the fat, that would be one thing but
that wouldn&amp;#39;t result in mass layoffs - that would happen over time
when a hire was found to be a bad fit. Sure. Some non-productive
employees are being let go but so are many really good people. If
a company is letting go of good people then that&amp;#39;s bad planning on the
companies part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that even though tech employees are relatively well
paid, they&amp;#39;re still cogs in the machine and ultimately, at will
employees. Maybe people will start to realize with all the perks
more often than not, they&amp;#39;re still just there to make money for the
corporation. At the end of the day, the company doesn&amp;#39;t care about
them. Even when we see the top execs taking cuts, we don&amp;#39;t see it
affecting their lifestyles. It&amp;#39;s a token gesture to ameliorate the
masses - make them feel like the top of the ladder is feeling the
pain. They&amp;#39;re not. They&amp;#39;ll say &amp;#34;I take responsibility&amp;#34; and then go on
in their bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Combine the recent corporate welfare (turned frequently into stock
buybacks), the layoffs, price gauging and still profits across
industries and maybe, just maybe, people will start to realize that
we&amp;#39;ve got to get back strengthening the worker. That the hard fought
gains of our parents and grandparents have been given back to the
rich. This goes back as far as I can remember with Reagan firing the
Air Traffic controllers even though their demands were not only
reasonable but in fact just about all are now in affect to Republican
led &amp;#34;Right to work&amp;#34; laws. Of course the Democrats only put up token
resistance if any at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If tech workers, and workers in general, had reasonable rights and
protections. The kinds that, dare I say it, a modern form of union
could provide then when times got bad, the pain would be shared
equally between ownership and worker. Workers wouldn&amp;#39;t be thrown on to
the street willy nilly but there would be a framework to provide a
safety net. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will the tech workers community act in any way not only to protect
themselves in the future but other workers in general? We&amp;#39;ll see. As I
said, I&amp;#39;m skeptical but there are some trying. I won&amp;#39;t mention names
but a handful of my former students have been active and vocal in
fighting for workers rights and equity in tech, sometimes at great
personal cost, and I couldn&amp;#39;t be prouder of them. I hope they prevail.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things they remember that we forgot</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/forgot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 06:43:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/forgot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Some time ago I wrote about some of the things our students remember
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/oldblog/blight-move/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; - sorry for the bad formatting). Lessons, concepts, stories, or
even small jokes I remember telling but had no idea that they left a
lasting impression on any students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to yesterday. I spent some time yesterday at a friend, a
former student&amp;#39;s company for their holiday get together. My friend was
telling a story about how I helped get him started - I won&amp;#39;t get into
details but while I do remember the overall impression of including
and encouraging him, I don&amp;#39;t remember the detailed specifics. Another
sign of getting old. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It made me think of not only the things they remember that we remember
but also what most surely be many things that as older teachers we no
longer remember yet may have stuck with our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve spoken to former students a few times and they&amp;#39;d tell me about
something they&amp;#39;ll &amp;#34;always remember&amp;#34; and usually it&amp;#39;s a pretty cool but
ultimately, just a small CS technique or work approach fact. Other
times, like the story that was told yesterday, it&amp;#39;s a reminder that at
times we can have a tremendous positive impact and sometimes we don&amp;#39;t
have to do much more than be decent human beings. Over the last few
years, I&amp;#39;ve been told a few times by older alums, just as a throwaway
comment how I created a &amp;#34;safe place&amp;#34; for them. Funny, I may have done
that by some throwaway comment or action by me and it meant a lot to
them. Now yeas later, I&amp;#39;m the one who&amp;#39;s greatly moved by their
throwaway comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, there are probably things I&amp;#39;ve inadvertently said or
done in my career that have adversely affected some students but for
better or worse, we rarely get feedback on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It goes to show the tremendous impact teachers can have even with
small gestures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even the good stuff, many teachers never hear about it. This is one
area that I feel both truly fortunate and humbled. Being in touch with
so many former students and with so many now friends, I&amp;#39;ve been given
the gift of hearing and seeing what I&amp;#39;ve done. I can&amp;#39;t say why, but I
think those of us who teach CS seem to get this opportunity more than
other teachers, even when our students go into totally unrelated
fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think about my old teacher, mentor, and friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher/&#34;&gt;Herb Greenhut&lt;/a&gt; - a
history teacher who made such an impact that he was frequently
included in his former students life events - weddings. receiving
birth announcements and so on and even got a Mayoral Citation in his
later years. I&amp;#39;ve been fortunate to get to enjoy some of these &amp;#34;gifts&amp;#34;
but I also know that many teachers, better than I and very well
regarded have not. I blame that on circumstance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing about this? Beyond yesterday&amp;#39;s reminder, I&amp;#39;ve been
reflecting more about my career as I prepare to leave the classroom
full time. It&amp;#39;s also important to point out to other teachers out
there that yes, our profession is in many ways thankless but there are
some rewards that money can&amp;#39;t buy and even if you&amp;#39;re not hearing about
the impact you&amp;#39;ve had, you&amp;#39;ve probably still had it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the younger teachers, it&amp;#39;s there, you just have to stick with it
long enough for your current students to go out in to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retiring part 3 - What&#39;s Next</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 19:40:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Links to the three posts in this series:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re seeing this before the previous two posts, I&amp;#39;d encourage you
to read post 1 and 2 first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;What was accomplished at Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said at the start of these three posts, I do want to stay in the
game. Maybe take a break and definately slow down but I still think
I&amp;#39;ve got something to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing this so that you can have it in the back of your mind in
case a great match appears either soon or somewhere down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I posses a somewhat unique set of skills and experiences. A
thirty year teacher with a strong CS/Tech background, I&amp;#39;ve taken students
from blank slate to industry, created entire programs, and worked with
educators from early grades through college level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also worked as a software engineer and have remained in touch and
connected with the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What might be appealing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Probably not full time and since I&amp;#39;ll be collecting my pension it&amp;#39;ll
be about fit much more than money. Still, I&amp;#39;d never say never on the
right opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d love the opportunity to travel more - even if just in the
region. I think that&amp;#39;s my biggest regret is that Devorah and I really
never had the opportunity or took the time to see the country or
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe if a company wants someone as a rep at conferences like all
those Ed Conference sponsors or who knows what else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d also be open to longer gigs elsewhere - a month, a semester, or
even a year on an interesting project where we can get to know a new
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I know the big tech companies work with colleges to try to help them
do what I did with Daedalus at Hunter. Given that none of them have
people with the range of educational experiences and successes I
have, they could do far worse than engaging me to help with these
programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maybe some colleges, universities, or governments have a side project
and they could use someone like me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, I don&amp;#39;t know but figured this was a good way to get the
word out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, thanks for reading and keeping me in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, back to our regular blogging program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Links to the three posts in this series:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;What was accomplished at Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retiring part 2 - Accomplishments</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 15:35:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Links to the posts in this series
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re reading this before the previous post, I&amp;#39;d recommend going
back and reading that one first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ve carved out a somewhat unique career. Never set out to be
a teacher and a couple of different turns here or there and things
could have been very different. When I started teaching, I thought I&amp;#39;d
probably, if anything  become a math chair and that was actually the
plan at Stuy until Richie Rothenberg, the math chair at the time
unexpectedly passed away in the late nineties. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
Pre Hunter recap
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just a quick recap. I started my career as a Programmer Analyst at
Goldman Sachs back in the day. I&amp;#39;d say Software Engineer but that
title didn&amp;#39;t exist back then. From there I went into teaching for two
decades, mostly at Stuyvesant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At Stuyvesant I built the CS program, created classes, trained teachers and
shepherded hundreds, perhaps thousands of students towards tech
careers. My continued relationships with these former students left me
in a unique position as someone with strong CS chops, strong teaching
and education chops along with professional programming experience and strong ties
to the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
During this time, I played my part in getting the
ball rolling for K12 CS Ed. Certainly at Stuy but I&amp;#39;d like to think
beyond it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
The Hunter chapter
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Almost seven years ago, I came over to Hunter to work on two major
projects. One was to develop and run an undergraduate honors computer
science program at the college and the other as to create and run
computer science teacher certification programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Undergraduate CS Honors
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Prior to my joining Hunter, they already had a long established CS
department and program. It was (and is) both as good as any other
program out there and as bad. There were though, a few particular
issues. First, Hunter&amp;#39;s program was either unknown to high school
students or had a poor reputation due to the misconception that a
liberal arts school can&amp;#39;t do good CS and, at the tech company end,
Hunter was a total unknown. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s program was a typical college CS program in that it did a
great job preparing strong applicants for grad school but did nothing
to prepare them for tech careers and there was no connection with the
NY Tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I started, top tech companies never recruited at Hunter and most
Hunter students never even applied for internships prior to
graduating - they didn&amp;#39;t know they were supposed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the past 7 years there have been tremendous changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My first cohort had 8 students. My latest has 64. My honors program and Hunter CS in general is
now a known CS destination in many NY high schools. Applications have
grown from around 50 to many hundreds and each year I field more and
more calls of students trying to decide between my program and other
top CS programs - I win some, I lose some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the exit side, my Daedalus students regularly end up at top tech
companies and the overall profile of Hunter CS is much greater and
more positive in the tech world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve created new classes that integrate software engineering practices
with traditional CS and built many unique partnerships and programs over
the past 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My trouble is that the Daedalus program is in full swing. It has to be
maintained but the job is basically done. At the same time, I don&amp;#39;t
have the ability to get the reforms I&amp;#39;ve brought to my program to the
greater Hunter CS population. Sure, I&amp;#39;ve gotten some initiatives
started that are available to all Hunter students but a lot of the
core stuff that I&amp;#39;ve worked into my courses are only available to the
Daedalus students and I don&amp;#39;t have a way of changing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I think I&amp;#39;ve done what I can do. The original goal was to create
this honors program and I think we&amp;#39;ve gone well beyond. Hunter, and
Daedalus in particular, has a higher profile with high schools and
employers and Daedalus students get the best of CS, the practical
software engineering skills they&amp;#39;ll need and unique partnerships with
the tech community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Teacher Certification
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My other major hat was on the K12 CS teacher side. First we had to
lobby the state to create the certification. I visited Albany a number
of times and spoke to my share of Regents but the real heavy lifting
went to Hunter&amp;#39;s President and the Dean of the Ed school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile, I created our masters and certificate programs while
doing my part in the whole K12 CS effort. I created new classes and
worked with some of my old teaching pals from Stuy to get ready to run
the program once the state approved everything. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Three years ago everything got really rolling. Hunter had the first active
certificate and masters programs in the state. Thanks to the generous
support of Gotham Gives, we were able to start a cohort of 21 working
teachers towards CS certification. They were joined by 2 masters
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A year later, New York State had its first certified CS teachers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following year, again with support from Gotham Gives, this time
joined by Google, we started another 24 working teachers along with 5
more masters students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now in our third cohort we&amp;#39;ve got another 56 working through the
programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By the time our third year ends, we&amp;#39;ll have around 100 certified CS
teachers in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m equally proud of the fact that we&amp;#39;ve got five teachers from the
Fingerlakes region in our program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been pretty vocal over the years as to what I think a good CS
teacher looks like and I&amp;#39;m super proud that our brand of CS teaching
can now be found across the city and in fact across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you
think about the number of students these teachers reach each year,
that&amp;#39;s pretty amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m equally proud of the fact that these cohorts are still in touch
and forming a new community of CS teachers in the city and state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that we&amp;#39;re rolling, what&amp;#39;s next? The program needs to continue to
run but I don&amp;#39;t see major changes. There are more things to get done
at Hunter and in the state. Things like getting the state to separate
HS from early grades in terms of certification and integrating some CS
teacher prep in our elementary school programs but, right now, I don&amp;#39;t
see a path for the former and don&amp;#39;t have the energy for the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Other hats
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve also done a number of other one offs or side projects while at
Hunter. Some of them have been:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was on the executive committe and a lead author in creating the
NY State K12 CS standards. Something I find ironic since I&amp;#39;m not a
fan of &amp;#34;state standards.&amp;#34;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mentioned earlier that I was a big part of Hunter winning and
administering the CUNY2X grant. Got to work with some great people
and that whole grant was huge in helping move the needle on Hunter
CS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was also fortunate enough to work on a project funded by the
Robin Hood foundation on CS in the primary grades. It also allowed
me to work with some great people while dipping my toes in CS Ed
research and early grade work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prior to Covid we were also well on our way in developing a nice
little K12 CS teacher community hosting monthxly meetups at tech
companies like Google and Digital Ocean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there it is, the major initiatives I&amp;#39;ve been working on at Hunter
and what I think I&amp;#39;ve accomplished. I&amp;#39;m proud of the work and in all
cases I think we went farther than we originally set out for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s next? I&amp;#39;m not entirely sure. I&amp;#39;ll share some thoughts in my
next post. I hope all my friends read it and keep an ear open if the
right opportunity presents itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Links to the posts in this series
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;#39;m retiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>After 7 years at Hunter College and 33 in NYC public schools, time for a change.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 06:43:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been dropping mentions of this here and there for a while now but
I think it&amp;#39;s time to come out more formally -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m planning on retiring from Hunter at the end of this Spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This doesn&amp;#39;t mean getting out of the CS or CS Ed game entirely - I
could stay on in a part time capacity and, after some decompression I
think I still have things to offer but the plan is retire, collect my
pension, and then see where I can continue to be contribute to the
Ed/CS Ed scene. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why now? Largely burnout but there are a number of reasons. I&amp;#39;ll talk
about them below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also posting this with two other posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One talking about what I feel I&amp;#39;ve accomplished here at Hunter (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another talking about the types of opportunities I think I&amp;#39;ll be
looking for next (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d love it if people could read those - particularly the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the rest of this post, why it&amp;#39;s time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, burnout is at the top of the list. What from? Largely from
having too much on my plate. When I started at Hunter, neither of my
programs existed. We started undergraduate CS honors (the Daedalus
program) the following fall and that grew at a consistent pace until
it was a full time job. The CS Ed program took longer to get running
since we needed to get the state to create the license and get our
programs through governance but once they started, that was another
full time job. Add to that the assorted other responsibilities that
ended up on my plate and I&amp;#39;ve been doing two to three full time jobs
for the past three or so years - not sustainable. For the burnout,
Covid and the state of the world certainly hasn&amp;#39;t helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What does burnout mean? Well, I&amp;#39;m not enjoying my classes. Sure, there
are fun times but I don&amp;#39;t get up in the morning looking forward to it
and in class, I&amp;#39;m as likely to get annoyed by something as not. Part
of this is that I have students who refuse to mask - something I see
as a direct sign of disrespect but there&amp;#39;s more. All in all, this is a
good sign that it&amp;#39;s time to get out or at least take a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another factor, and a big one is that I&amp;#39;ve accomplished everything
I&amp;#39;ve set out to accomplish at Hunter and then some. I&amp;#39;m normally not a
&amp;#34;goal guy,&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m more about process and journey but in the case of
Hunter, I also had a set of goals and I&amp;#39;ve gotten there and
beyond. There are new challenges at Hunter but not challenges that I&amp;#39;m
as excited about. More on this in my accomplishment post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I&amp;#39;ve got health and family reasons. Health isn&amp;#39;t anything
immediate but I do have indications of heart disease. Combine that
with the fact that my mom died when she was 72 and my dad at 44 and
well, now that I&amp;#39;m 55, if we can financially handle it, maybe it&amp;#39;s
time to give more time to myself and my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, Devorah&amp;#39;s also retiring - she put in the paperwork the other day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For those of you who read this blog, I&amp;#39;d love for you to keep your
ears open for potential next steps so I&amp;#39;d love for you to read my next
post on what I think I&amp;#39;ve accomplished at Hunter and what I bring to
the table and the one after that where I&amp;#39;ll muse about what I think I
might be able to get excited about and where I think I might be able
to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Links to this post  and the other two posts:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 1: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-1-why/&#34;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 2: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/&#34;&gt;Recap of what was accomplished at Hunter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post 3: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/retiring-3-whats-next/&#34;&gt;What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crafting a new major for tech</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-major/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 09:42:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/new-major/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Hunter College, like most colleges and universities is facing
unprecedented demand for CS. It&amp;#39;s the hot major. Being a public
college, we have an obligation to provide the best education possible
to as many students as we can in our locality. This means we can&amp;#39;t
just put a GPA requirement or other cap on the major and we can&amp;#39;t do
things I&amp;#39;ve heard &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; schools do like essentially making
applicants apply to the major direct from HS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This had led to the usual problems - more large lectures, fewer
electives offered, challenges for space etc.. This is nothing unique
to Hunter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another problem, though is that Hunter offers a traditional CS major -
similar to the majority of institutions across the USA and the
traditional CS major is not really servicing many of our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unlike many other majors, the students in CS by and large want to work
in Tech. Unfortunately, most CS programs aren&amp;#39;t set up for this. Rather
they are set up with the assumption that all CS majors want to go on
to PhD programs which is most certainly not the case. Sure, CS
students learn programming and some other career useful things but
they also learn a lot that most ever use. Theory is important but not
as much as many have to study. Far too much proof, How about calc 2
and sometimes 3? Sure these topics can be useful and even important to
some but I&amp;#39;ve talked to countless tech people in the business world
ranging from entry level programmers to top executives and everyone in
between and by and large the CS major is poorly set up for the CS
career. What&amp;#39;s more, the only career that many CS majors only somewhat
prepares students for is programming and even then just to a certain
extent and there are many non-programming heavy tech opportunities out
there waiting for our students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think many in academia acknowledge this as well. I&amp;#39;ve spoken to some
high up people at some of our most prestigious institutions and, at
least, privately, they&amp;#39;ve agreed with me on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it stands, not all Hunter CS students can get through the major and
for those that do, they&amp;#39;re just as well set up for career as graduates
of the &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; programs but truth be told, it&amp;#39;s not the institutions
that are setting them up well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hunter&amp;#39;s trying to do something about this. At recent department
meetings there&amp;#39;s been discussion of creating a new major - something
that maybe dumps the unnecessary stuff and replaces it with material
that is both more relevant to the students career while also providing
additional support in areas that the students need. The challenge is
to also keep the academic rigor at the same time and not just become a
jobs program for the flavor of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was a lot of talk asking &amp;#34;what do other colleges do and what are
they planning?&amp;#34; but I didn&amp;#39;t like that talk. Who cares what other
colleges are doing? Who says they&amp;#39;re doing it right. Every institution
has a unique situation. Hunter - a liberal arts college in the heart
of NYC which is part of the CUNY system should be figuring out what&amp;#39;s
best for itself, not what may or may not work for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I suggested talking to the tech community, particularly in NYC - what
jobs are out there now and what will be out there in the next decade
and how can we structure a program to inform students as to the
possibilities and to prepare them on their paths?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, I&amp;#39;ve got tons of former students in all areas of tech and
we&amp;#39;ve been talking for the past few weeks and trying to figure this
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Originally, some of the Hunter faculty were considering things like
network admin / sys admin type roles and thought to explore there but
that&amp;#39;s not what I&amp;#39;ve been getting from my network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big obvious one was software engineering. This could be great for
those meant to follow the programming path but not for tech minded
people who don&amp;#39;t want to spend their days in code. Project management
kept coming up but there were more than a few concerns that to be a
great PM you really have to have some real world experience so a PM
major wouldn&amp;#39;t be serving students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that came up was the idea that developers in many cases
do have more control over their infrastructure which would lead to
requiring knowledge in administering their own systems, some network
wherewithal as well as some knowledge of container technologies and
the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There was also a lot of talk about which current major classes were
useful and which really weren&amp;#39;t and there was discussion of a lot of
other things like software architecture (something never taught but
much needed), technology integration, and things like soft skills
(presentations/writing) ethics and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also glad &amp;#34;the family&amp;#34; got the idea that we wanted to teach
academic classes and not just how to use tools. I was heartened this
morning when one of my former students recalled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 90s when I was in your systems class I remember you
saying that you weren&amp;#39;t teaching us Intel Assembly. We were learning
how computers worked and that we were &lt;strong&gt;using&lt;/strong&gt; Intel Assembly as a tool
to explore to accomplish that learning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Made me feel good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all, I&amp;#39;m really grateful for my StuyCS Family (or as some say,
the StuyCS Mafia) - got all the info I needed from which I think I&amp;#39;ll
be able to craft a very strong and useful new proposed major. I don&amp;#39;t
think it&amp;#39;ll focus on just one possible career but I think it should
get a student ready for a variety of entry level tech jobs including
programming related ones. What&amp;#39;s more, it will educate them as to the
possibilities - something else current majors don&amp;#39;t usually do. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will the CS department like it? Who knows but I&amp;#39;m convinced that it
will be a great option for Hunter students if they do.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>College Recommendation Season</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-recs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 20:42:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/college-recs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s fall so for HS teachers who taught juniors last year it&amp;#39;s
recommendation writing season. For many of those teachers, they&amp;#39;re
already well into the season with early decision deadlines being as
early as November 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Writing recs is one thing I don&amp;#39;t miss now that I&amp;#39;m working at the
college level. Sure, it was always an honor to be asked but it was a
lot of work. Now I&amp;#39;m on the other side and reading the recs. On one
hand, much easier but on the other hand, getting worthwhile
information from a college rec as an application reader can be its own
challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When reading recs, I see the same things that I knew were going on as
when I was on the writing side. Some teachers do a crap job and some
teachers put their all into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the bad side, you get the generic rec - pretty much the same thing
for every kid. We all know some teachers do this. From the reader
point of view, you see these a mile away and when a lot of kids apply
with the same teacher writing, it&amp;#39;s even worse. Sometimes this is
indeed lazy rec writing but other times it&amp;#39;s because the teacher&amp;#39;s
doing their best but just doesn&amp;#39;t have the material - I used to get
asked for recs all the time from that quiet kid who basically did a
good job but was quiet, and to be honest, somewhat generic in terms of
application portfolio. Nice enough kid but within the context of
class, not a lot to write. You know as a teacher that this is a good
kid who deserves to be represented and you&amp;#39;re porbably their best or
only option but there&amp;#39;s not a lot to write. It&amp;#39;s hard. Combine that
when, like me, you&amp;#39;re not a great natural writer and you can get a
generic rec even it you&amp;#39;re not trying to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the good side, you get writers who really write something unique and
descriptive for each kid. In order to try to do
right by my kids, I&amp;#39;d insist on having multiple weeks to write the
recs since I&amp;#39;d have to space them out - I couldn&amp;#39;t do more than one or
two at a sitting for fear of them becoming generic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any case, good recs take work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, I would always be very clear to my students. I&amp;#39;d tell them
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m making no effort at all to get you into any particular school.&amp;#34;&lt;/strong&gt;
I never saw that as the purpose of the rec. I&amp;#39;d tell them that my job
was &lt;strong&gt;&amp;#34;to paint a picture of them&amp;#34;&lt;/strong&gt; in the hope that the reader would
be able to determine if they were a good fit for a school. Afterall,
fit is what it&amp;#39;s all about. If an applicant or rec writer &amp;#34;fool&amp;#34; an
admission office into offering a bad fit, it won&amp;#39;t work out for
anyone. The majority of kids, in my experience end up in good places
and get good educations but the key is not getting in to the dream
school, the key is getting in to the right fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My son, in spite of an amazingly stellar application portfolio,
didn&amp;#39;t get into any of his first choice schools and went grudgingly to
Michigan - it turned out to be the best possible place for him. I
didn&amp;#39;t get in to my dream school back in the day and ended up at NYU
but that was indeed, the right place for me at that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s about fit and a rec can help paint a picture to see if there&amp;#39;s a
fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;ve been on the reading side for a number of years, that&amp;#39;s
what I look for. If I get a generic rec I don&amp;#39;t count it against a
student and if a rec isn&amp;#39;t well written I likewise try to look past
that. As I said before, I don&amp;#39;t consider myself to be a strong writer
so I understand the challenge. I do look for a rec to paint a
picture. Will this student be a good fit for my program. Will they
thrive and be a positive part of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, for teachers at schools where i have a track record, I&amp;#39;d
just as soon get short and sweet - &amp;#34;You remember so and so, well this
kid is like them but here are the differences&amp;#34; or even &amp;#34;Mike, you know
I&amp;#39;ve written for a dozen kids in the past - you WANT this kid.&amp;#34; That
track record is important because over time, I get to know the schools
and the teachers and if they&amp;#39;re honest with me, their recs weigh more
heavily. On the other hand, if I read a bunch of over the top reviews
and later it turns out that the students weren&amp;#39;t fairly represented,
then those writers lose credibility with me in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This has made a difference for kids in the past. Every year, it seems
that I reach out to rec writers directly where I&amp;#39;ve felt there was
something, a spark in the application but I needed to dig deeper to
make a case to advocate for the kid. Sometimes it worked out,
sometimes it didn&amp;#39;t but building the track record and history
certainly help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I can&amp;#39;t speak for anyone else or any admissions office - in fact,
I have nothing to do with the Hunter admissions process, I just have a
major voice in advocating for the students in my program and that is
indeed a very little corner of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, why did I write this? I was talking to a couple of friends who
stil teach high school and they were talking about rec writing and I
thought that even though I&amp;#39;m not directly involved in admissions and
in the greater scheme of things my program is very small and I&amp;#39;m just
one voice, I thought it might be interesting for teachers to read a
bit about how I look at and think about college recs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 55</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-55/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 15:15:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-55/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, I turned 55 today. Another year older. The changes? Well, I&amp;#39;m
seeing more doctors and seeing them more frequently and to be honest,
I&amp;#39;d love to have a day or two without some small niggling ache or pain
but that&amp;#39;s life. Like many people my age, we&amp;#39;ve got our health issues
but I&amp;#39;m pretty active and managing mine (hey, I had a great 8 mile run
this morning :-) ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still, 55 is a big one. Yeah, I know, it&amp;#39;s not 50 which ends in a 0
and is half a century so people seem to earmark it. It&amp;#39;s also not 62
or 67 when social security can kick in for most people. Nope. It&amp;#39;s
also not 65 when you get all those senior discounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fifty five, for teachers who started around when I did is that magic
age that, if you&amp;#39;ve put in enough years (which I have) you can retire
and start collecting unreduced pension benefits. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/&#34;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt; that I was starting to think about retirement as
a possibility. Of course, that doesn&amp;#39;t mean getting out of the game
entirely but if I go that route it means reducing my work obligations
be they at Hunter or elsewhere. Regardless of what I do, I think I
still have something to offer in terms of CS, the Tech Industry,
Education, and the intersection of the three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of what I decide to do, it&amp;#39;s been a tough few years, and
I&amp;#39;m feeling somewhat burnt out and it&amp;#39;s calming and relieving to know
that if I wanted to, I could now step back whenever it suits me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, now to do some hard thinking and have conversations about this
with family and friends (yes, dear reader, I&amp;#39;ll be reaching out to
some of you) while I work to make the experiences of my current
students as positive and rewarding as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masters of CS Education</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/masters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 06:45:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/masters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was in the middle of writing a post on how early and often we should
be teaching CS in our schools but had to jump in with a quick hit
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As any reader here knows, Hunter was the first institution with state
approved CS Teacher Education Masters and Certificate programs. Siena
had the first Bachelors program (Hunter doesn&amp;#39;t have undergraduate
education programs that lead to state certification).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ve been graduating certificate students for a couple of years
now. Those are professional teachers - working under another
certification area who are earning the new New York State CS
credential. We now have around 40 certificate graduates who are either
state certified or qualified to be state certified if they haven&amp;#39;t
filled out the state application. It was cool that we were the first
but more importantly that NY is getting qualified CS teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We passed another milestone the other day. Our first two Masters
students graduated this past June and I just heard from one of them
that she now possesses New York State Certification to teach Computer
Science. She should be the first newly minted Masters grad to have
earned certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another cool milestone passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I expect that in the coming years, the demand for Hunter&amp;#39;s certificate
program will go down as demand for the Masters program goes up. We&amp;#39;ll
see if I&amp;#39;m right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For now, just wanted to share a bit of cool news.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS - it isn&#39;t all that</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-all-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 11:52:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-all-that/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve dedicated my entire career - something like 32 years, to CS
education and the spread of CS education. So, while I try to be a
cheerleader I also think it&amp;#39;s important to call out things that we do
or say that are maybe not so great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I hope I don&amp;#39;t annoy too many people (or maybe I hope I do) with
this post and maybe a few more to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before diving into specific CS teaching methods, we started with some
general discussion. What is CS? Why study CS? Why it&amp;#39;s important to
offer etc. This is is really red meat for CS teachers so rich
discussion quickly ensued. Nothing particularly new, I&amp;#39;ve heard and
has been part these conversations so many times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lots of good stuff but there were a few things that always come up in
these conversations that I think are worth calling out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is creativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is problem solving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is making mistakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS is building projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students like CS, it&amp;#39;s fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;#39;t bad things and in fact are almost always good
things. What I want to call out is that they&amp;#39;re not CS and certainly
not exclusive to CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big thing I don&amp;#39;t like about this is that the good things here are
not exclusive to CS and are not always in CS. CS can teach problem
solving but so can Math. Creativity? How about writing or the
arts. Making mistakes? Science? Math. and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the flip side CS doesn&amp;#39;t necessarily have these and other good
attributes. CS is generally perceived as fun but then again we&amp;#39;re CS
educators. Math teachers think math is fun. Likewise, as long as CS
classes are populated by students electing to be there and as long as
the content is lightweight it&amp;#39;s not surprising that many kids think
it&amp;#39;s fun. When standardized testing sets in and teachers are
pressured to cover more with less in less time, this will probably
change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I will not infrequently say that something I&amp;#39;m teaching is &amp;#34;inherently
cool&amp;#34; but the truth is it isn&amp;#39;t. There are plenty of things that I
might think are cool or neat or fun but that doesn&amp;#39;t automatically
mean all our students will feel the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Problem solving and creativity? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said before, just about every other field can be about these but
CS might not. Back when the code school / bootcamp boom started in the
Ruby on Rails days, those code schools taught neither problem solving
nor creativity. They taught rote pattern programming to create a very
specific type of application to solve a specific problem that was in
demand in the early days of the second internet boom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS also isn&amp;#39;t also necessarily taught in a creative way in the
K-College classroom. I&amp;#39;ve seen many classes where student create a
game but they all code it together and the creativity consists of
students deciding on the sprite to use for the player. Yes, this
allows for a controlled form of creativity on the visual part of their
project but not on the problem solving side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t mean to be down on CS. CS can incorporate all these good
things and more but I think it&amp;#39;s important to recognize that other
fields can be these things as well and CS might not be all we think
it&amp;#39;s cracked up to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CS does, though have one edge over most other fields. As the new kid
on the block K12 CS education is not as highly regulated and
restricted as other fields. We don&amp;#39;t have standardized exams nor
standardized curriculum. The closest we have are APCS-A and
APCS-Principles. This means teachers are more free to teach what they
want how they want. This can be great with a well prepared, qualified
tearch or less great with a less ready one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As CS becomes more part of the system I expect teachers to have less
freedom in what they teach and how they teach. As a community we might
be able to steer the ship towards keeping the good stuff but then
again, we might not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s important, as a community of educators, that as CS becomes more
standardized that the teachers and not the curriculum providers, not
the standards makers, and not the gorillas in the room with the
oversized influence but none of the actual teaching or CS experience
have a voice to keep the good stuff and not go the way of other
disciplines that are no longer considered cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You can&#39;t workshop a lesson</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/workshop-a-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 10:02:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/workshop-a-lesson/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The other day, Natan scored tickets for us to see an interview with High
Jackman and Sutton Foster. We&amp;#39;ll be seeing them in &amp;#34;The Music Man&amp;#34;
come this fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was fun but it was the taping for a radio interview so nothing
earth shattering or surprising. Still, one thing stuck with me and got
me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jackman told a story about how, during rehearsals, he wandered down from
his dressing room to find  Foster was working with Jerry
Zaks, the director on &amp;#34;My White Knight.&amp;#34; He remained and observed,
entranced as Foster and Zaks spent an hour or so working on the song.
It reminded me of a Master Class taught by Maxim Vengerov, my favorite
current violinist that I caught on cable one day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking about how horribly pathetic our model of teacher
observation, support and improvement is and that you can&amp;#39;t have a
master class for a lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The two things in teaching that would be closest to a master class
would be either teaching a mock lesson to a colleague or supervisor or
an observation. Mock lessons rarely occur outside of teacher
interviews but colleagues will observe each other. The problem is,
those aren&amp;#39;t Master Classes. In a Master Class, you have an immediate
feedback loop. You perform, stop, get feedback, rinse and repeat. When
teaching, you get some feedback at the end of the lesson and even if
it&amp;#39;s good you generally can&amp;#39;t implement any changes until next
year. If you&amp;#39;re lucky, next semester. Sometimes you might be able to
rush try things in a class later that day but usually not. Of course,
if and when you do try that change you likely won&amp;#39;t be getting any
feedback on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is, you can&amp;#39;t stop the lesson in the middle becuase, you
know, the students and you certainly can&amp;#39;t then go back  and reteach
the last 10 minutes again to them to see if it&amp;#39;s better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although there are many similarities between teaching and performing
there are of course crucial differences. The bar for a performer is
pretty simple - will the audience get something out of the
performance - enough to think positively about it. That&amp;#39;s pretty much
it. To get there, Sutton and Zaks worked on a challenging song. There
wasn&amp;#39;t any audience feedback but rather they worked to achieve the
director&amp;#39;s vision. When Vengerov runs his class, he&amp;#39;s working with his
students on their interpretation of the work. These work in performance
becuase first, presumably they know what works with an audience and
second, an audience may very well go to something to see or hear an
artists interpretation. Personally, I&amp;#39;ll go to one violinist or
anther&amp;#39;s performance of a work specifically to hear their
interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When teaching the bar is harder to define, at least if you&amp;#39;re serious.
about education. My first chairman kept it simple. He said, when you
observe a class, just keep asking yourself &amp;#34;is learning going on?&amp;#34; And
then figure out where and how. I always liked that and always lived by
that.  Of course these days observations aren&amp;#39;t about learning but
about teacher evaluation using garbage metrics like Danielson where
it&amp;#39;s all about checking off the boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, good teachers do work to improve their lessons. They try
different techniques, work within the extremely slow feedback loop and
they work with their colleagues even though they&amp;#39;re never given the
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
None of this really means anything. Just something I found interesting
to ponder. Would a master class work for teachers? Maybe. Maybe you
could run a department meeting as one with one teacher presenting and
the rest of the department playing students, both good and bad. That
would actually be pretty interesting. If anyone tries this, let me
know.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put It In The Books</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/put-it-in-the-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 17:20:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/put-it-in-the-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Just finished entering grades closing out my 32nd year teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Whew!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a hard year for me and I&amp;#39;m sure even harder for the K12
teachers out there. Still this year I&amp;#39;m really missing what I was oh
so many years ago - a regular teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Teaching from September through June is a beast and from my first day
on the job I had to work ten times harder than I ever had to as a
software engineer and was commensurately exhausted. In spite of what
the &amp;#34;real world&amp;#34; says teachers need their summers to recharge the
batteries. This isn&amp;#39;t to say that teachers don&amp;#39;t work over the
summer - they lesson plan, attend PD and in fact a bunch of them will
be with me, working towards their NY State CS teaching certification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m also technically on a school year contract so why do I wish I
was a regular teacher? Because once you enter those final grades, you
put the past to bed. Once I clicked on &amp;#34;post grades&amp;#34; in CUNYFirst I
thought about that. Early in my career, before I had to deal with
building Stuy&amp;#39;s CS program and otherwise getting involved in the
movement, once those grades were entered I was done. I could mentally
turn off. My responsibilities to student and school were done and I&amp;#39;d
have a couple of months before the next go around. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I noted that I should have been feeling that but wasn&amp;#39;t. Why not?
Because I&amp;#39;m still immersed in dealing with issues for my advanced
certificate program - working on scholarship issues, getting the
teachers, making sure they&amp;#39;re up to speed, finding instructors under
some draconian restrictions placed on me by both Hunter and the staet,
andto be honest, the self imposed stress of feeling responsible for
making everything work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been a while since I&amp;#39;ve &amp;#34;just taught&amp;#34; and maybe would like to get
back to that but even then, all this is making me seriously think
about that possible (probable?) retirement in a year to scale things
back or change things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, ploughing ahead with the teacher certification program
this month to get things in order and then teaching through
July. Should get a week or two of downtime in August so that&amp;#39;ll be the
time to reflect on the year in depth. Until then it&amp;#39;s nose to the
grindstone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Mass Of CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/a-critical-mass-of-cs-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 13:38:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/a-critical-mass-of-cs-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
A big difficulty with creating CS opportunities for all our students
is the lack of CS teachers. New York City addressed this problem with
their CS4All program - quick form PD to get teachers into CS
classrooms in a hurry. One can debate if that was the best way to go
but it enabled NYC to create a whole lot of CS classes in a very short
period of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, these teachers, by and large, only have that short form PD
so I&amp;#39;d argue that this isn&amp;#39;t a long term solution. I mean, you
wouldn&amp;#39;t want your entire language program taught by people who
barely knew Spanish 1  or Math taught by teachers how don&amp;#39;t know
beyond the basics of Algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A number of institutions, including Hunter are working on rectifying
this via our CS Education programs. Some programs are legit, and some
practically as superficial as the short form PD but the legit ones are
trying to address the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I want to talk about why Hunter&amp;#39;s Advanced Certificate program, a
program, that I might add, is currently accepting applicants for this
summer, is critical to the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Right now, you could place K12 CS teachers into one of the following
buckets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People with strong CS backgrounds. CS Majors or people with
industry experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hobbyists who learned some CS on their own and developed an
interest or passion for the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volunteers who are game for the challenge who heard about CS4All
and answered the call.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teachers who were voluntold who are taking one for the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of the home-brew CS programs in the city started with teachers
from the first two categories but currently the vast majority of
teachers teaching CS are in the last two. Eventually, CS classes in
NYC will all or mostly all be taught by qualified, certified CS teachers
but how we get there will make a difference in terms of the community
and culture we create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of the approved certification programs in NY state award either a
Bachelors degree or a Masters. That is, they&amp;#39;re designed for new
teachers just entering the profession. At Hunter we run a Masters
program. Our first cohort had 3 students, our second 6 and right now
there are 3 applicants for our third cohort. I haven&amp;#39;t done any
advertising or outreach but over time we&amp;#39;ll get more and more
applicants. It will be a slow process but eventually we&amp;#39;ll have
comparable numbers as for our math and science ed programs. I&amp;#39;d
imagine that other programs across the state will have a similar
growth curve. As these programs graduate teachers, the voluntolds and
volunteers that aren&amp;#39;t up to speed will return to their other
subjects. Some will continue to teach a section or two of CS which
is fine provided that by then their base of knowledge of CS and CS
pedagogy is well beyond the canned training that DOE currently
provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While eventually this will normalize, there is a problem. We&amp;#39;re
basically asking our new CS teachers to also be our master CS
teachers, our CS teacher leaders. They&amp;#39;ll have deep CS knowledge and
they&amp;#39;ll have studied the CS pedagogy so it&amp;#39;ll all be on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The trouble is that it&amp;#39;s hard enough surviving as a new
teacher. Asking them to be the master teachers and the leaders at the
same time is just not right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s where my Advanced Certificate program at Hunter comes in. Right
now, we&amp;#39;re the only such program in New York state. The program&amp;#39;s an
18 credit masters level program that teaches the CS and the CS
pedagogy but understands that the participants are already experienced
teachers in some other subject area. It&amp;#39;s a program that takes an
teacher who&amp;#39;s already experienced, albeit in another subject area and
fills in the CS content and CS pedagogy gaps. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned earlier that I&amp;#39;ve done zero outreach for our masters
program and that&amp;#39;s because all my outreach has been for the Advanced
Cert. I think it&amp;#39;s vitally important that we  build a critical mass of
highly qualified CS teachers as soon as possible. Taking current,
experienced teachers and bringing them up to speed in CS and teaching
CS is the way to do this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Other subjects already have their teacher leaders. In most schools, at
least in larger schools, there will be one or two &amp;#34;go to&amp;#34;
teachers. The ones that know the subject matter more deeply and how to
teach it, the ones who are up on the latest and greatest in the field
and in teaching, the ones who attend the conferences and bring back
best practices. I&amp;#39;m working to jump start that for New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, I&amp;#39;m not alone and our friends at &lt;a href=&#34;https://gothamgives.org/&#34;&gt;Gotham Gives&lt;/a&gt; and Google
are supporting our program by providing scholarships to pay the
tuition for qualified applicants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first cohort graduated in May of 2021 and with that, New York City
(and state) had it&amp;#39;s first 21 certified computer science
teacher. They&amp;#39;ll be joined by 23 more two months from now. That&amp;#39;s 44
teachers that have both the subject knowledge and the pedagogical
knowledge to match in the system. Part of their scholarship agreement
is for them to give back. Take part in CS education efforts in the
city so they&amp;#39;re already helping to shape the community and culture of
K12 CS Education in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m hoping for an even larger cohort this year. Imagine if we could
get 60 or more into our program this summer. That would mean in three
short years we&amp;#39;ll have gone from zero to 100 qualified certified
teachers and we&amp;#39;ll be well on the way to that critical mass of teacher
leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we get closer to that critical mass of qualified teachers, interest
in programs like my certificate program will wane but at the same
time, there will be more demand from teaching newcomers for our
Masters program as there will be a career path for young CS minded
teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again it&amp;#39;s the long game but that&amp;#39;s what it takes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;re a New York City CS teacher and are looking for state
certification, come join us. All the information can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.huntercs.org/teacher_ed/summer-2022.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE2022 - Things I plan to blog about</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse2022-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 20:07:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse2022-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been up in Providence RI since this past Wednesday for
SIGCSE2022. The big Computer Science Educators conference. Also, my
first in person conference since pre-covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t sure how I was going to feel about this big in person
gathering but as it&amp;#39;s turned out, it&amp;#39;s been pretty comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So far, I&amp;#39;ve attended two terrific keynotes. One by Barbara
Liskov and the other Barbara Ericson, some really interesting sessions
and some less interesting ones and have had a great time discussing CS
education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big highlight has been seeing friends in person and being able to
talk. Sitting down for coffee with a friend or having a rount table
discussion around a well, round table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of those friends I was delighted to see was Alfred
Thompson. Alfred&amp;#39;s already sumarized his &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2022/03/sigcse-2022-day-1.html&#34;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.acthompson.net/2022/03/sigcse-2022-day-2.html&#34;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; day
experiences so there&amp;#39;s not reason for me to write much the same so I
figured I&amp;#39;d just quickly list out a few of my highlights and in
particular things I plan to write more about when I get back to NYC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Language choice for APCS. There was a panel that considered why
change to Python or why stick with Java. I didn&amp;#39;t attend this
session but talked at length about it with a number of people. It
had me reconsidering my opinions and I&amp;#39;ll certainly write about this
in the near future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I saw an interesting talk by Sam Lau in which he discussed how
statisticians and computer scientists differed in their views as to
how and what should be taught in a data science course. This got me
thinking about developing CS offerings at the high school level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I attended the &amp;#34;It seemed like a good idea at the time&amp;#34; session for
the first time where teachers discussed their failures. This was a
&lt;strong&gt;great&lt;/strong&gt; session hosted by two more friends I haven&amp;#39;t seen since
pre-covid - Dan Garcia and Jim Huggins. One topic brought up there
was dealing with late assignments as well as alternative
grading. This too is something I plan to write about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PD For CS Teachers and teacher prep programs. This is clearly
something I care deeply about and there were some sessions on this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also spent a good amount of time catching up with my friends Jim
and Robin from Siena College. They&amp;#39;re doing some cool thing up there
so that&amp;#39;s another thing I&amp;#39;d like to write about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also had some good discussions with vendors in the exhibit hall as
well as some great hallway tract talks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My thoughts on the hybrid format of this conference&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a big list - a lot of things to write about. I hope to get on
this when I get back to NYC on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime, if you&amp;#39;re in providence for tomorrow&amp;#39;s last day of
SIGCSE, please find me and say hello!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First live conference in 2 years</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 08:13:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow I&amp;#39;ll be driving up to Providence Rhode Island for SIGSE 2022,
basically the largest computer science education conference out
there. I guess ITSE, a conference I&amp;#39;ve never attended, is larger but
that&amp;#39;s really EdTech with some CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The last in person conference I went to was two almost exactly two
years ago - also SIGCSE. I arrived in Portland and went to a
pre-conference session and on the morning of the big start, about three
hours before I ran my session, I saw an email saying we were
canceled. I flew home and a few days later we began our shelter in for
covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In spite of the latest CDC release, SIGCSE is still requiring
masks. This is something I support. I have no problem taking a
conservative view on health, particularly at an event that brings
together people from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The sessions should be comfortable. Everybody will be vaccinated and
should be masked so it&amp;#39;s no different than attending a concert in
NYC. I am curious though about the lunches and big reception. Will
everyone just dump the masks for food since we&amp;#39;re all vaccinated? Will
there be some trepidation? We&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also curious to see the overall attendance. The last SIGCSE had
well over 1,500 attendees. What will this one be like? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are some sessions I&amp;#39;m really looking forward to. There are some
on K12 teacher preparation and professional development. I feel pretty
confident that the approach I&amp;#39;m taking at Hunter is the right one but
it&amp;#39;s always good to see what other people are thinking about and
trying - always happy to steal better ideas. I&amp;#39;m also looking forward
to some of the sessions that deal with teaching more advanced CS
concepts. This is something that&amp;#39;s lacking in CS Ed. The CSTA
conference which focuses on K12 is more about actual teaching but
since K12 CS is still in its infancy, most schools are still dealing
with intro level stuff and conferences like CSTA really have to work
to support our new teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most importantly though, I&amp;#39;m looking forward to seeing people that I
haven&amp;#39;t seen in a couple of years. Both those that I consider real
friends and also the many acquaintances I&amp;#39;m friendly with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also looking to see the breakdown of K12 and higher ed
people. Over the years the number of K12 teachers at the conference
has grown and it&amp;#39;s interesting to see the differences in the
camps. The teachers, by and large know far less CS but are much
stronger teachers while the professors know the topic but while they
might research teaching, they don&amp;#39;t nearly have the depth of teaching
knowlege that K12 teachers posess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a probably unfair oversimplification but you could say that teachers teach
the student and professors teach the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This can make for an interesting dynamic. I hope over time, the
teachers become stronger in the subject material and that the
professors realize that teaching is an art and a craft and that what
one does at an elite institution is worlds away from the inner city
middle school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, enough yammering. For those of you who&amp;#39;ll be in providence
this week, make sure to say hi. I&amp;#39;m sure we&amp;#39;ll all learn a lot and have
a blast doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Problem Solving And Crosswords</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/programming-problem-solving-and-crosswords/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 17:37:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/programming-problem-solving-and-crosswords/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I used to do the New York Times Crossword puzzle. I don&amp;#39;t remember
when I started - some time late in Eugene Maleska&amp;#39;s tenure as the
editor. I continued on a few years into Will Shortz&amp;#39;s puzzles. I
stopped when the Times wanted to charge me for both print and
online. I preferred reading the physical paper but liked printing the
puzzle from their online site. I was also pissed at the Times coverage
of a number of issues at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I picked up the puzzle again when Covid started and have only missed a
few days since. I&amp;#39;m pretty sure the puzzle is easier these days. Way
back when, I&amp;#39;d sometimes complete or almost complete a Saturday puzzle
but more frequently I&amp;#39;d just fill in a smattering of words. On this
run, I&amp;#39;ve completed every puzzle I started except one. I say the
puzzle must be getting easier because if anything, I&amp;#39;m getting dumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was doing the puzzle the other day and it got me thinking about the
advice I give my students when I first meet them. I tell them it&amp;#39;s one
of the true secrets of success. Of course, I know it&amp;#39;s my job as teacher to tell
them these critical secrets and it&amp;#39;s their job as student to ignore
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tell my students that regardless of when they do an assignment they
should read over it the day they get it. It doesn&amp;#39;t matter if the
assignment isn&amp;#39;t due for two weeks -  read it and give it a bit of
thought the day you get it. Even if you don&amp;#39;t work on the assignment
right then and there, your brain will start working on it in the
background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I do the crossword, particularly Friday and Saturday, but
sometimes other days as well, I start the puzzle with my first cup of
coffee. Sometimes I&amp;#39;ll get a good amount done but on those Saturday
puzzles, I&amp;#39;ll sometimes get stuck with the fewest of words. I&amp;#39;ll look
at clues and, well, have no clue and think &amp;#34;guess I won&amp;#39;t be finishing
this one.&amp;#34; At some point I stop - do something else. I check my email,
read some blogs in my feeds and a little later go back to the
puzzle. Invariably, I&amp;#39;ll read some clues that while opaque just a few
minutes earlier are trivial now. Hitting another wall I take another
break. I&amp;#39;ll come back after breakfast and fill in some more. So far,
this has just about always resulted in a solved puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking of a few things. One, the break is giving my
brain time to work in the background while focusing on something
else. It also lets me look at the puzzle with fresh eyes when I pick
it up again. A last little point that&amp;#39;s neither here nor there is that
it is a manner of perseverance (no, I won&amp;#39;t use that term grit which
I hate).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me this was a really clear and concise example of exactly what I&amp;#39;ve
been preaching to my kids for decades. Not only read the assignment
early but also when you hit a roadblock, take a break - clear your
head. Come back with fresh eyes. Work smarter not harder. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, I don&amp;#39;t think this example is more relatable to my kids
than the other ways I try to share this wisdom with them but I still
think it&amp;#39;s a great example.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pension Consultations</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pension/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 17:41:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/pension/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Devorah and I just got off a Zoom pension consultation. Very
enlightening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m 54 so regardless, can&amp;#39;t retire for another year but Devorah hit 55
last November and the DOE can really kill ones spirit and grind you down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall I&amp;#39;ve been pretty happy at Hunter but I&amp;#39;ve written before about
the fact that I&amp;#39;ve been feeling some burn out and have been basically
doing 2+ full time jobs myself at Hunter for the past few years and
that&amp;#39;s just not sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not saying I know what I&amp;#39;m going to do  but it&amp;#39;s important to know
your options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wasn&amp;#39;t sure what our retirement benefits would look like but when I
came in to teaching, looking at the older tier 1 teachers, I felt that
back then there was something of a societal pact, at least in NYC. As
a teacher back then, you weren&amp;#39;t going to get rich. In good times,
you&amp;#39;d do okay - not great but okay. On the other hand, in bad times,
you wouldn&amp;#39;t do terrible. You&amp;#39;d be able to have a decent home and
while you couldn&amp;#39;t jet set you&amp;#39;d be able to vacation reasonably and at
the end of it all, you&amp;#39;d have a comfortable retirement. Again, you
wouldn&amp;#39;t be rich, but you wouldn&amp;#39;t have to worry about making ends
meet either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the course of my career, I saw that pact erode, even in NY. Young
teachers don&amp;#39;t earn enough for the housing market and the workload and
work pressures have just exploded. For the newest teachers, the
retirement end of the deal has also gotten worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what does it look like for us after putting in and paying in for
30 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With 30 years in, it turns out that pension will net me just a few
hundred dollars less than my current net. It&amp;#39;s much closer than I
thought it would be. Devorah doesn&amp;#39;t do quite as well. Her difference
is greater but that&amp;#39;s because she hasn&amp;#39;t crossed the 30 year barrier
yet. If she stays one more year, she will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Add to that a substantial TDA and we&amp;#39;re actually in really good
retirement shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lot of older teachers say they finally &amp;#34;had&amp;#34; to retire because based
on tax benefits and other factors, they were actually losing money by
not retiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Based on the differences I mentioned above we&amp;#39;re not there yet but
when you factor our housing, we might be, or if not it&amp;#39;s really
close. We currently live in what&amp;#39;s known as a &amp;#34;limited equity coop.&amp;#34;
It&amp;#39;s a coop but it receives local and state tax benefits. In return,
there are earning caps on the residents. We currently earn well over
the cap so pay a significant surcharge on our monthly maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we retire, our lower incomes will result in a much lower
surcharge or maybe it will remove the surcharge entirely - we&amp;#39;re
working on figuring that out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Depending on how that plays out we might actually be losing money if
we don&amp;#39;t retire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll have to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said at the top. I&amp;#39;m basically happy at Hunter and I think I&amp;#39;ve
accomplished a lot so I&amp;#39;m not saying I&amp;#39;m out the door as soon as I can
walk. We&amp;#39;ve got to lower my workload but they&amp;#39;ve known that for a
while so hopefully are working to solve the problem. Devorah and I
also have to figure out what we want to do in our next phase. I do
know that regardless, I think I&amp;#39;ve still got something to give in the
CS Ed space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For any young teachers out there - make sure to max out on that
TDA. It seems like nothing at first but when you look back after 20 or
30 years it&amp;#39;ll surprise you - that + the defined pension are what
allow you to have a few years of leisure at the end of a life of
service. And don&amp;#39;t let anyone tell you that you don&amp;#39;t deserve it or
that it&amp;#39;s an entitlement. You&amp;#39;ve paid into it for your whole career
and are just getting back what you&amp;#39;ve earned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 54</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:59:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/turning-54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, tomorrow, October 19, is my birthday. The big 5 4. Okay, maybe it&amp;#39;s not a
traditionally big one. It doesn&amp;#39;t end in a zero or a five but I think
it rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why? Because it&amp;#39;s one shy of 55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s the magic age when I can retire collect my pension should I
choose to do so. It&amp;#39;s what you get when start young and put in over
30 years of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Will I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago I would have given an emphatic &amp;#34;no.&amp;#34; Now, I&amp;#39;m starting
to think &amp;#34;maybe.&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;ve written a few times here about feeling some
burnout and a lot less joy. Part of that&amp;#39;s covid and part of it&amp;#39;s doing
more than two full time jobs. Another factor is that by summer 2023,
actually, summer 2022, I&amp;#39;ll have pretty much accomplished everything
I&amp;#39;ve set out to do here. On top of this, Devorah will be able to
retire before I can so that also weighs in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong. There&amp;#39;s a lot I like about Hunter and a lot I
still enjoy about my job but there&amp;#39;s stuff that&amp;#39;s just wearing me
down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of what happens, I plan to stay in the game in some
capacity. I want to figure out a situation where Devorah and I can
travel more - my one big regret, but I think I&amp;#39;ve still got something
to contribute to the CS Ed world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we can trim down my workload at Hunter and eliminate the things that
stress me out, I could be there a long time. If not, well, we&amp;#39;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the time being, I&amp;#39;ll enjoy tomorrow. Nothing particularly
special - normal work day followed by a family dinner. Actually,
whole family dinner is always special, just not unusual for us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No CSTA conference for me this year</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 17:08:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/no-csta2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Today is the start of CSTA&amp;#39;s annual conference. Like last year, it&amp;#39;s
virtual. Unlike the past few years, this year I won&amp;#39;t be attending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a big fan of the CSTA conference. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jakebask&#34;&gt;Jake&lt;/a&gt; and team have done an
amazing job growing the conference and it&amp;#39;s been a highlight of my
year every time I&amp;#39;ve attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could say that I&amp;#39;m not attending due to my schedule - I&amp;#39;m pretty
much spending all day every day during July teaching in my CS Teacher
Certification program and at the end of the day I&amp;#39;m wiped. This is
true but it&amp;#39;s not the only reason. The truth is, I&amp;#39;m pretty burned
out. Part of it is doing too many things. At this point, the
teacher education part of my portfolio is a full time job as is my
work with the undergraduate CS students and that&amp;#39;s not counting the
extras that have worked their way onto my plate. The other part of it
I&amp;#39;m sure is Covid. I&amp;#39;m writing this because  many teachers are
overworked and add in this past year of Covid and I&amp;#39;m sure many are
feeling the same as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I love the CSTA conference but I&amp;#39;m just not feeling it. Same with a
lot of professional stuff - just not feeling the joy these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m hoping that come August I can turn everything off for a few weeks
and recharge a bit for next year and going back in person (safely)
will provide a boost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m betting teachers around the country are feeling rather burned out
so wanted to share publicly saying you&amp;#39;re not alone, it&amp;#39;s okay and
it&amp;#39;s okay to dial it back for our own mental and physical well being. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Already looking forward to a better next year and  CSTA2022, hopefully in person.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>