<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 11:49:58 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>StuyCS - Playing the long game</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-programs-the-long-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 11:49:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/cs-programs-the-long-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday, I was back at Stuy. I was there along with members of
the Alumni Association to host Stuy&amp;#39;s first tech meetup of the
season. I guess that&amp;#39;s the first &amp;#34;official&amp;#34; project I&amp;#39;m working on
since retirement. In the past, there had been various issues with
Stuy&amp;#39;s assorted alumni associations (yes, there were at one time three
competing entities) but for the past few years they&amp;#39;ve been under what
we can call &amp;#34;new management&amp;#34; - people I both like and trust so I&amp;#39;m
happy to be working with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This event was just a normal meetup - mostly networking time and a
couple of speakers. One of the speakers was my friend, former student,
former colleague, and successor as Coordinator of CS at Stuy - JonAlf.
JonAlf gave an update on the &amp;#34;state of StuyCS&amp;#34; going back to when I
first started to build things. I enjoyed the talk and since, as JonAlf
said, even though the audience collectively knew the development,
individually very few did. There were also a couple of old timers who
probably didn&amp;#39;t know any of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It made me think of how much education is playing the long game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Things started in Fall 1994 when I started teaching APCS-AB - the
one that was both a college CS1 and CS2 - four sections. Prior to that
there had been a single APCS class and a random programming elective
here or there but all taught by math teachers and all taught as one
offs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spring &amp;#39;95 brought graphics and Fall &amp;#39;95, Systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point, we, or I was just starting but I wouldn&amp;#39;t call it a
program. Three courses but I&amp;#39;m not sure I&amp;#39;d be able to claim any
strong coherence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
APCS was, well, APCS. Nothing special there except that we probably
covered more and more deeply than most high school programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Graphics was the terminal course - second term senior year. It had a
nice combination of the programming they had learned in APCS, Math
from precalc and a touch of calc, and a little of their physics. Much
like the rug, it tied things together nicely. That, plus the kids made
pretty pictures which helped stave off but didn&amp;#39;t eliminate
senioritis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Systems was just thrown in. It was based around Intel Assembly
programming in our lab of MS-DOS/Windows-95 machines I thought it
might be interesting and fun for the kids and I knew I could teach it
but there wasn&amp;#39;t any deep thought that went into why I created it as
opposed to some other course to fill that space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Around 1998 / 1999 things started to change. First, Systems had
changed. We had switched the labs over from the extremely overpriced
and obsolete IBM PS/2s (obsolete because IBM had stopped selling them
prior to selling them to Stuy) for regular PCs which we could install
Linux on. Since we could do much more with the platform I decided to
change up the course. I also had a few years of graduates now in
college and was able to get their thoughts on what was missing from
their CS sequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s how our new Systems class was born. It covered C programming
and an assortment of Systems topics. Some was similar to what they&amp;#39;d
cover in college but a lot was set up to support them in college. I
continued to get feedback from my grads on this and other courses from
that point on and it helped direct my approach to course building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also created the sophomore one semester intro course that would
later become a requirement. This class was designed as a new CS0 -
something that would be programming heavy but would both expose
students to a wider range of CS topics than a typical intro
programming class and also relate CS to other disciplines. In some
ways APCS-Principles which came around later had a similar intent but
I&amp;#39;d say my course was much more rigorous and much better for my population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The goal would be to provide something valuable to the majority of
students who might never take any more CS while at the same time,
inspiring and preparing those who would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now I&amp;#39;d say we had a program. It was still basically just me along
with a math teacher and then two  picking up some of the APCS classes
but we had a cohesive sequence of courses that made sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Intro would lead into APCS would lead into Systems/Graphics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Being a StuyCS grad meant something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few other selective schools also claimed CS programs at the time but
as far as I could tell they had intro programming followed by APCS
followed by just teaching the next college course or courses in high
school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t see the point of that. The kids would get algorithms,
theory, compilers etc. in college anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, Systems and Graphics made much more sense. My Systems was set
up to support the college classes and Graphics was typically an
elective so it would add to my kid&amp;#39;s backgrounds and not just be
something they&amp;#39;d take again. Besides, I ended up working some things
like parsing and automata into the graphics course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also started to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By 2007 we had 3 full time CS teachers plus five sections of CS
classes being taught by math teachers. Intro was a single semester
requirement. We had 12 intro classes each semester, 5 ACPS classes
(still teaching AB), 2 Systems/Graphics (Fall/Spring), plus one
research which was really a fake class to let me work with my kids to
run the network although I did do my best to support the kids who did
want to do legit research and within a few years, the class did morph
into a legit research class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s a little over 10 years. The long game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We gad a coherent three year sequence. It wasn&amp;#39;t random
electives. Being a StuyCS grad meant something. Now, I&amp;#39;m not saying
that my way was the only way or the right way for everyone but I think
for CS it made a world of sense. Contrast that with Stuy&amp;#39;s English
department. Through most of your four years, students could select
which English &amp;#34;selective&amp;#34; to take and they ranged wildly. You could
take Science Fiction, Women&amp;#39;s Voices, Children&amp;#39;s book authoring,
science writing, detective fiction and tons more. This means that Stuy
grads can have radically different English and Literature
experiences. For English. maybe that&amp;#39;s good. For a HS CS program, I
think a coherent sequence is better. I guess it&amp;#39;s also like having
area requirements for a Bachelors of Arts degree - take one from this
category, two from this etc. versus Columbia&amp;#39;s core curriculum where
everyone literally takes the same classes for the core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was confident though that it was working. At one point, I saw a
tweet by Morgan Missen. I don&amp;#39;t know her but was told that she was the
top tech team talent builder in the Bay Area. She tweeted &amp;#34;Stuyvesant,
the Stanford of the East.&amp;#34; I also started hearing from VCs, investors,
and founders about how they didn&amp;#39;t really like seeing a high school on
a graduate&amp;#39;s resume unless it was Stuyvesant. If they saw StuyCS, the
knew it meant something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By the time I left Stuy for Hunter College we were mostly
stable. Maybe one or two more APCS sections on any given year and I
did create a Software Engineering course called Software Development
to replace research. That course, like my others, was designed based
on what my graduates were saying they needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So it took twenty years of work but in this case slow and steady might
not have won the race, but it built the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;ve gone over why I left Stuy in some other posts but two
important reasons were my stagnating - I had done everything I felt I
could do and also, I felt that some of my team was also being held
back as they were too deferential to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, I left, JonAlf took over team leadership and here&amp;#39;s where
they are today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They now have an opt in full year CS requirement. Kids can either take
a full year of CS or one of CS and one of drafting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That translates to 13 sections of the full year course and 6 of the
single semester. They also rebranded intro and now call it
&amp;#34;foundations of CS.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also have 7 APCS classes and that&amp;#39;s probably the limit, at least
based on teaching the Stuy version that includes data structures. They
tried to have additional sections based on requests but that led to a
portion of the students really struggling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To address that, they created NeXTCS which covered APCS-A but at a
more relaxed pace and had a lot of fun projects. I think they were
using Processing. They&amp;#39;re running 4 sections of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On top of that add 2 Systems to go along with 2 of a new Cybersecurity
class as well as the usual 2 of softdev and a new Ethics class. The
only reason they aren&amp;#39;t running 2 graphics classes this year as well
is because they had a crunch in math and need to send a CS teacher
over to teach a couple of math classes - how times have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To run this, they have 8 full time CS teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s no doubt in my mind that my leaving was the right move. StuyCS
has gone on to new heights under new leadership and I couldn&amp;#39;t be
prouder of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It did take a span of just about 30 years to go from no CS to a three
year sequence, a full year required option, a coherent sequence of
electives and eight full time CS teachers. Just another indication
that education is a marathon not a sprint. Now, we&amp;#39;re in the infancy
of CS teacher certifications and much of the country isn&amp;#39;t even where
Stuy was thirty years ago in terms of courses. I expect it&amp;#39;ll be
another thirty years or probably more before it&amp;#39;s all worked out. I
guess for old timers like me (and some of my readers and friends) we get to be
Moses - we get to see the promised land but we won&amp;#39;t get to enter
it. It won&amp;#39;t be here for another few decades but that&amp;#39;s okay, that&amp;#39;s
just how education progresses. It&amp;#39;s gratifying to look back and see
how far we&amp;#39;ve come so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What they remember</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-remember/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 15:10:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-they-remember/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t blogged for a few weeks. Part of the reason is that I
haven&amp;#39;t felt that I&amp;#39;ve had too much to say. That&amp;#39;s in part because
it&amp;#39;s summer time and in part because I&amp;#39;m no longer teaching so that
means no new experiences with students, no new stories, and, at least
right now, no new CS education adventures. Part of it could also just
be that I&amp;#39;m following the trend - fewer CS Ed bloggers blogging less
frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another part of why I haven&amp;#39;t blogged for a few weeks is that I&amp;#39;ve
decided to try to write a book. Since retiring I&amp;#39;ve had a few people
mention it to me so I thought I&amp;#39;d give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been writing a few sample chapters over the last there weeks
(around 35,000 words , 75 pages so far). The plan is to alternate
chapters - one with a story from my career followed by one on teaching
something in CS or some CS pedagogical technique. Rinse and
repeat. The &amp;#34;story&amp;#34; chapters will also have some educational message
but it won&amp;#39;t be topic or in class specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ll see where it goes. Even if it comes together I have no idea how
I would go about trying to get it published&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since my memory isn&amp;#39;t what it was and even if it was, our memories are
malleable I decided to reach out to my network of former students. I
know that overall I&amp;#39;ve done a solid job as a CS teacher but what
specifically was memorable. I might have loved a topic or something I
did but maybe it was a flop. On the flip side, maybe there were things
that had a major impact - good or bad and I thought they were just
throwaways. I sent an email to my alumni list and posted to Facebook
asking for the stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I got as a result is what made me think about the title for this
post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of what I got wasn&amp;#39;t a surprise. The competitive kids enjoyed
things related to the USACO. Some talked about some of the bigger
themes in the advanced classes. Everyone loved Halloween!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was surprised though with other things that came up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A surprisingly large number of responses singled out my &amp;#34;Homer the
robot&amp;#34; lesson - my day one or two activity for new CS students. I used
to do &amp;#34;Homer the Robot&amp;#34; in APCS when students took AP without any
prior class and then moved it to Intro once that class was established
and a requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Basically, I would play the part of Homer the Robot, named after Homer
Simpson, largely due to Homer&amp;#39;s well known mental capacity and also
because I&amp;#39;ve always been a huge Simpsons fan - remember I started
teaching this lesson or a variant of it back in the mid to late
90s. I&amp;#39;d set up a simple scenario - instruct Homer so that he writes
today&amp;#39;s &lt;strong&gt;aim&lt;/strong&gt; on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They would shout out instructions and hilarity would ensue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The idea of course was to show that computers follow simple
instructions and follow them literally. As I always tell my classes
&amp;#34;computers are horrible at doing what you want them to do but they&amp;#39;re
great at doing what you tell them to do.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d interpret or rather, misinterpret the class&amp;#39;s instructions but
eventually we&amp;#39;d get an aim on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I know this isn&amp;#39;t a unique idea. I&amp;#39;m sure while I was coming up
with it in the 90s in New York City others were doing similar things
elsewhere. It&amp;#39;s like pair programming. Industry &amp;#34;invented&amp;#34; the idea as
part of agile programming but just about every CS teacher ever
invented a variation of pair programming prior to industry ever
dreaming of two people on one computer every time that teacher was in
a computer lab with more students than working machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays you can find similar unplugged exercises a simple web search
away - things like &amp;#34;the paper plane exercise&amp;#34; or the &amp;#34;peanut butter
and jelly sandwich exercise&amp;#34; come to mind. Still, I prefer my version
but if you want to know why, you&amp;#39;ll have to read my book if it ever
comes out :-).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When reading my student messages, I was surprised how often Homer came
up. Sure, it was fun and the class always got laughs but there were
plenty of other classes with more laughs. Maybe because it set the
stage. Many of the students who were subject to that lesson ended up
taking two and a half years of CS and many classes with me. Maybe
because it started to demystify computing. I can&amp;#39;t say for sure but
it&amp;#39;s something I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about. Why that lesson and not any
of the hundreds to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I said, it&amp;#39;s interesting what they remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another theme that came up in more responses than I would have
expected didn&amp;#39;t refer to a lesson, any particular activity, or
story. It had to do with the CS class, or in many cases, the CS office
area - room 301, being a &amp;#34;safe space.&amp;#34; Interesting because I don&amp;#39;t
think people even used that term back in the day. I found that
interesting because first, it again came from more students than I
would have expected. Second, it also came from some people who were
never my student but are now in my network. They were never in my
class but still found there way to the CS corner of Stuy. Third, I
never thought I did anything special or even really thought about
making a &amp;#34;safe space,&amp;#34; particularly since that can mean very different
things to different people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those were the two biggest surprises. Not that they were mentioned but
that they were mentioned more than I would have expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were plenty of other responses. Some I expected and some not and
lots of good memory triggers as I stroll down memory lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the new semester starting for teachers around the country it&amp;#39;s
worth spending a minute thinking about it - you&amp;#39;ll all have an impact
teaching your subject area but you&amp;#39;ll also have an impact in ways you
probably wouldn&amp;#39;t think about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Have a great semester everybody!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Danger of a Bad Teacher</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/danger-of-bad-teacher/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 10:51:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/danger-of-bad-teacher/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
For years I&amp;#39;ve been one of the few people banging the &amp;#34;CS teachers
must know CS&amp;#34; drum. There have been a few others out there but in
terms of being vocal about it, we&amp;#39;re in the minority. I get it. There
are many teachers who volunteered to teach CS and are working hard to
acquire the knowledge needed. There are also those who were voluntold
who are trying just as hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is, at least from what I&amp;#39;ve seen, there are far too many
CS teachers who after years of training still can&amp;#39;t navigate CS1 or
sometimes even CS0 level code and have very limited context when it
comes to CS. They know the bullet points in the scripted curriculum
they&amp;#39;re using but that&amp;#39;s about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also get that it&amp;#39;s not easy to be vocal about it. When I talk about
this, it can seem like I&amp;#39;m calling out my CS teaching colleagues and
while in a way I am, I&amp;#39;m talking about those who&amp;#39;ve stayed at barely
CS0 for multiple years, not those working to improve their CS
knowledge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded today why this is a problem, why people should be
paying more attention to it and why more should be calling it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was chatting with a young man today. He has a Math and CS
  background - was a double major, and is considering a career change from a non
  teaching job in to either teaching or something education adjacent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing that came up in our conversation was that he took a CS class
in high school and that almost caused him to drop the field. My new
friend mentioned that the teacher in question was a math teacher and a
pretty good one at that but noted that in addition to not knowing the
CS, the teacher didn&amp;#39;t know how to teach a CS class. Of course, my
friend acknowledged that he&amp;#39;s not a teacher himself but the end
result to him as a student was that he was turned off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In college, in spite of that bad experience, he decided to try CS
again and after a couple of nondescript courses he took one that he
described as life changing. A great instructor that reignited his love
for the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This happened to me as well but on the math side. I was always pretty
good at math and enjoyed it, until I wasn&amp;#39;t - this was Calc II. I
thought I just hit my wall and I started to dread math even though I
knew I&amp;#39;d need some to be a CS major. I figured it must be me. I
slogged through my required courses in college barely getting by until
I took Discrete Math - the instructor was &amp;#34;just&amp;#34; a grad student but he
was terrific. Turned me back on to math. I realized I could do this
stuff. A couple of years later, I realized that my problem wasn&amp;#39;t that
I was stupid but I had a bad teacher who didn&amp;#39;t teach me what I needed
to know to succeed in Calc II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We always here about that small handful of teachers that many of us
had who inspired us or set us up for our futures but there are also
many tales of that bad experience. That reason why someone is math
phobic or why they abandoned some prior passion. Maybe it was a bad
teacher, maybe a good teacher severely out of their element but
throwing kids into a CS class with an unprepared teacher just to say
they got to take CS might not be the best idea. We might be exposing
them to the field but we also might not and worse, we might be turning
them off. If the teacher is well
prepared, all good. If the teacher isn&amp;#39;t but recognizes
their deficiencies they can still pretty much ensure that they won&amp;#39;t
be harming students and some good will likely come out of the class.
An ill prepared teacher who doesn&amp;#39;t know any better can be a
dangerous thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This of course isn&amp;#39;t to say that there&amp;#39;s one way to prepare a teacher
or for a teacher to be prepared and certainly there are many ways for
said teacher to run their class. In my conversation today, my new
young friend shared thoughts on a few of his CS teachers noting how
many of them did things very differently from each other but they each
played to their strengths and to my friend&amp;#39;s view, the were effective. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d like to think that this situation will ultimately work itself out,
at least in states that have strong credentialing but even there, we
could have issues as I&amp;#39;ve seen CS credentialing programs that barely
cover CS0. If we want to make sure that ALL students receive strong CS
education, it&amp;#39;s up to all of us in the community to call out the
situations preventing that and that includes calling out bad prep
programs, bad PD, and schools and districts that tolerate or even
encourage CS teachers who don&amp;#39;t know CS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers learning, using, and teaching AI</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-and-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 16:33:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teachers-and-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
How do we prepare teachers to teach AI to their students, teach their
students to use AI effectively, and how to effectively use AI
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was having this discussion with a friend this morning and I&amp;#39;m sure
many educators have been having this and similar conversations over
the past year or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the discussion around AI is different from the discussion of CS,
after all an AI writing assistant can be used with zero understanding
of AI and in any subject area but AI is a subset of CS and there are a
number of parallels when thinking about preparing teachers in both
cases. Unfortunately, we&amp;#39;re still having the same discussions about CS
so while we can look at what&amp;#39;s been done so far, everything&amp;#39;s still
too new to know what works or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should students learn about AI in all of their classes or in specific
AI or CS focused classes? What about in a specific &amp;#34;Using AI&amp;#34; class?
Can &amp;#34;all teachers&amp;#34; learn sufficient AI to teach their students or do
we need specialists? Are the answers different for the early grades
than from high school? Will teachers learn on their own? Should we
provide professional development? What would that look like? Or, do we
need to integrate all of this into our teacher preparation programs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These are all issues we&amp;#39;ve been dealing with in CS education and we
don&amp;#39;t have any definitive answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t have any final answers but I though I&amp;#39;d share some of my
current thoughts both on delivery and also on training content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of delivery, the two options are Professional Development
(PD) or preservice coursework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While PD can be very valuable, quality PD is extremely rare, at least
if you listen to teachers. On the other hand, if you&amp;#39;re in a state
with minimal teach requirements or the powers that be can&amp;#39;t convince
the colleges and universities that prepare teachers to bring in AI (or
CS for that matter), then you&amp;#39;re left with PD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A local department of education, even one as large as NYC can also
roll out PD much more quickly and at a wide scale like what NYC has
done in their CSforAll program without requiring any changes at the
state level, in legislation or by including colleges or universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A good example of some good work being done here is what Nora
Burkhauser and Nick Yates are doing in Maryland. I wrote a bit about
it &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-4/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. They run a 2 part PD series. It doesn&amp;#39;t prepare teachers to
use AI effectively as it&amp;#39;s meant to educate them on what AI is but it
looks to do a great job at that. Part 1 is a great introduction for
non CS teachers of all grades and part 2 goes even further. Ideally
there would be even more for CS teachers, as I wrote about in my
earlier post, but that&amp;#39;s a limitation of the PD model and they&amp;#39;re
doing all they can do under their current system. They&amp;#39;re also doing
more than so many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, I&amp;#39;ve had an opportunity to really see the pros and
cons of the PD offered in NYC for their CSforAll program - here PD is
generally offered by a PD provide - that is, someone like code.org or
the College Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got to do a deep dive when I evaluated applications for the CS
Certification programs at Hunter College. I reviewed hundreds of
applications over a three year period. If I remember correctly over
100 each year and close to 200 multiple times. There was a small
amount of overlap each year in applicants but not much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Applicants needed rudimentary programming knowledge in any text based
language. Write a program that used a loop, had variables, a
conditional, a function, and used an array or list. That&amp;#39;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The vast majority of the applicants had NYC CSforAll training and
many, if not most had multiple years of this PD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In years one and two I could barely accept 20 per year. In the third
year I was able to accept close to 50 but that was by additionally
offering multiple bootcamp sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Clearly, the PD model wasn&amp;#39;t working. We had a large number of
teachers having gone through multiple years of training by the big
name players in the field yet far too many couldn&amp;#39;t tell the
difference between a for loop and a forklift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes PD is the best you can do and often it&amp;#39;s all you can do
&lt;strong&gt;right now&lt;/strong&gt; but it&amp;#39;s not the long term answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If this doesn&amp;#39;t convince you I&amp;#39;ll add that we all know that the
attrition rate for teachers is among the highest of all professions
and every time a teacher leaves the profession after two or three
years, all that effort is lost. A PD model at best is a never ending
treadmill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if you work AI into your preservice courses, you
have more time to cover it, the students (teachers) have some accountability
(which rarely exists in PD sessions as one basically becomes certified
by just showing up), and teachers enter the profession with AI as part
of their skill set. Of course, ongoing PD after that then becomes a
bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course the challenge then becomes convincing states to require it
and educational institutions to offer it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my Hunter programs, there&amp;#39;s certainly room for both AI as a CS
subject and also how to leverage using AI but my program is really
made for high school CS teachers. I&amp;#39;ve had elementary school teachers
but it goes so far beyond what they need to know in terms of content
and there&amp;#39;s less focus on their needs. It&amp;#39;s also made for CS
specialists so we&amp;#39;ll never get the history teacher for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, the topics and ethics CS classes both give platforms to
learn about AI. Even in 2020 we had a unit in the topics class on
neural nets and many in the ethics class on bias. Meanwhile the
methods classes and curriculum development class give a platform for
exploring and using the tools, although, again the focus in on a CS
class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can see a number of places we could work AI, from a generalists
point of view into a typical preservice program and, between you and
me, there&amp;#39;s enough cruft in most programs that nothing would be
lost. Even if you do have to cut something, AI isn&amp;#39;t going anywhere
so methods classes, for example, really will have to deal with AI
tools if they really want to prepare teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any case, the next question is what to teach the teachers. I can
think of a number of activities, both on the computer and unplugged
which would give teachers a basic understanding of some key AI
concepts. While not AI, a Markov Chain text generator show how you can
use statistics and probability to generate text. Now and LLM is much
more complex and uses a neural net on the inside but an unplugged
activity around this simple generator can go a long way in
demystifying an LLM and once demystified, they can be used more safely
and more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve done a number of other proto-AI lessons like &amp;#34;Who Played
Spiderman?&amp;#34; or my Caesar Cipher unit which can be converted into
unplugged activities to demystify other aspects of AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s also a good amount of low hanging fruit for other uses of AI
like generating discussion topics or having groups of students using
AI to generate or research content and then have them discuss or
debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another advantage of doing this in preservice is that you can spread
the AI over many courses and you&amp;#39;ll have the time to also discuss
issues like bias and dangers like using an AI tutor at the expense of
developing teamwork and interpersonal skills with your classmates. In
A PD time is much more limited and while there&amp;#39;s good work like the
Maryland project I spoke of above, far too much is given by vendors
who&amp;#39;s bottom line is selling a product. On top of that, things like
bias is really beyond AI - yes, AI exhibits all sort of bias but the
root is societal bias and where an AI PD is unlikely to be able to
sufficiently handle that, an entire masters program can at least make
a dent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, those are my thoughts for now. They&amp;#39;ll probably change and evolve
and in any case, given my current role as &amp;#34;retired guy&amp;#34; I&amp;#39;m not sure
when I&amp;#39;ll be able to act on any of this, though I do have some
thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI without guardrails</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-without-guardrails/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 14:37:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-without-guardrails/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
CSTA was only a week ago but I&amp;#39;ve already been trotting out things
learned there in conversations. Specifically, during the panel
keynote, one panelist, while discussing the affects of AI cited a
study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two groups of programmers were tasked with writing some safe and
secure code. One group used AI tools like copilot and chatGPT. The
other didn&amp;#39;t&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When all was said and done, the group that &lt;strong&gt;didn&amp;#39;t&lt;/strong&gt; use the AI tools
produced more secure code. The group that did use the AI tools not
only produced worse code but they were actually more confident in
their code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, this really didn&amp;#39;t come as a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today I was thinking about this again. My friend Bethany Crystal wrote
up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://paragraph.xyz/@bethanycrystal/beyond-the-classroom-leveraging-ai-for-educational-innovation&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on leveraging AI. Lots of good stuff in the post, one point
was when Bethany talks of when she was with StackOverflow and how it
became such an important part of developers workflows and how AI is
now becoming the same but beyond coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The post is a great post to get people thinking about using AI in
their workflows but we also have to be reminded that AI without
verification can be dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bethany gives an example of using chatGPT in a similar vein to
StackOverflow - as a timesaver to generate content from which she
would then build her actual work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To do this, she asks chatGPT:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, I&amp;#39;m a principal at a public high school in the South Bronx. Can
you help me make a case about the importance of project-based learning
to teachers who are skeptical about why we need to teach kids how to
code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If one is an educator and already knows their stuff on Project Based
Learning (PBL), the results are a nice start if you&amp;#39;re building a
presentation, going to address your faculty, or a number of other
tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if you&amp;#39;re someone who just got out of Teach for
America and are now making the next greatest education startup but
don&amp;#39;t really know the real deal in education, it&amp;#39;s not nearly as
helpful. I ran this query twice, the second time, the answer didn&amp;#39;t
talk at all about some of the problems with PBL - class size and time
issues, project storage over days for physical projects, prep time
needed to set up each experience and many more. The first time I ran
it, it mentioned some of the issues with PBL but just in the most
generic sense &amp;#34;make sure teachers have the support they need.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both answers also conflated coding and PBL so if the person using
chatGPT doesn&amp;#39;t have as strong education and in this case programming
background the chatGPT solution can do more harm than good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I then, for kicks, tried this prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi, I&amp;#39;m a principal at a public high school in the South Bronx. Can
you help me make a case about the importance of the use of lectures in
teaching who are skeptical about why we need to teach kids how to
code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had to change the wording a bit but it&amp;#39;s basically the same ask but
with the use of lectures instead of projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While parts of the response are very specific to lectures, the entire
answer actually reads very similarly to the PBL answers and its
justifications are just as strong (or weak depending on your point of
view).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All of my queries resulted in  some incorrect assertions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I&amp;#39;m not saying at all that one shouldn&amp;#39;t use these AI tools - we
should - if we already know about the domain we&amp;#39;re using them in. They
can be great at generating code for well understood algorithms - we
just have to make sure to verify what&amp;#39;s been generated. They can help
phrase a difficult paragraph or reframe an argument and assist us in
many other ways. The important thing, and the thing that that first
group of programmers from the experiment up top forgot, is that we
have to verify what these tools give us. We end up using them like a
curated library and it isn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tools like chatGPT look at a corpus of documents and probabilistically
generate its content. This means it&amp;#39;s basing its results on the
documents out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the case of code, we know that there&amp;#39;s a lot more bad code out
there than good. This means that while chatGPT can probably easily
generate code for a really well known algorithm like a sort, we&amp;#39;ve got
to question and test anything it puts out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Likewise for education issues, there&amp;#39;s a lot of bad material on
education out there. A lot of garbage has been published and treated
like &amp;#34;the true way&amp;#34; to teach and to run schools. Things that
&amp;#34;reformers&amp;#34; love because they cut costs but teachers know are
crap. Things that are likewise pet theories of education that have
become popular but are no better and are frequently worse than what
teachers know are tried and true methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s more a chatGPT response can lack nuance. I can picture someone
who&amp;#39;s starting a school - a non educator let&amp;#39;s say, heard from a
person that PBL is good. Now, I know some people who swear by PBL and
say to use it all the time - those are people in super selective
private schools with tremendous resources and ultra small classes. The
reality is that PBL is good and should be used as appropriate but
there are other good techniques that will be better under some
circumstances and worse under others. This person starting the school
then dives into the AI with queries like I made on PBL and get a very
one sided view. Now we have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I loved Bethany&amp;#39;s post and it got me thinking more of how I can
leverage AI, of course the problem for me is that I&amp;#39;m currently
between gigs so don&amp;#39;t have any work to apply it to. It also reminded
me of the dangers of using it blindly and without guardrails.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2024 final thoughts</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-final/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 15:10:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-final/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Got home last night. Only delayed a couple of hours so we were much
luckier than many friends who had to scramble and deal with canceled
flights. It helped that we flew JetBlue, an airline not affected by
the CrowdStrike issues and also because we were staying until Monday
anyway so as to play tourist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s left to cover. Let&amp;#39;s start with the exhibition hall with all
the vendors. There were the big companies - Google, Amazon, and
Microsoft, curriculum provers like CodeHS and CMU (CS Academy), and
lots of robots and robotics companies. There were a few others mixed
in as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t speak to too many vendors though as I&amp;#39;m not particularly
interested in using someone else curriculum and while some of the
robotics stuff looked very cool, it&amp;#39;s not something I&amp;#39;ll be using
since I&amp;#39;m no longer in a classroom and any toys I do want to play with
have to fit in my Manhattan apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I did spend some time with the people in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kira-learning.com/&#34;&gt;Kira&lt;/a&gt; booth. I thought I&amp;#39;d
check them out since they seem to be getting a bit of buzz
recently. Their home page touts Kira as &amp;#34;The AI platform for schools.&amp;#34;
There are courses which seem to basically be MOOCS, although they can
be used (and appear to be meant to be used) as a tool by a teacher
with a class. There are pre-made courses and units and teachers can
also build their own content. This all looks fine but seems similar to
other course platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They seem to want to differentiate themselves with their AI
piece. This comes as an auto-grader which I didn&amp;#39;t get to see along
with an AI tutor for the students. It looks cool but to be honest, I
don&amp;#39;t know if it&amp;#39;s even a good idea as a classroom tool. I think I&amp;#39;d
rather have a student talk with a neighbor first. I plan to do a
deeper dive into Kira sometime soon and then will probably report
back. Right now, if they keep the buzz, they&amp;#39;ll sell well but I&amp;#39;m not
yet sold. If I were still in the classroom, I think I&amp;#39;d stick to my
old school ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To me, CSTA has always been a people conference rather than a session
conference and this year was no exception. I got to see and spend time
with many old friends and met a couple of new ones. For the sessions
though, while I found a couple of great ones, many didn&amp;#39;t do much for
me. That&amp;#39;s not to say they were bad sessions. I think I even noted
that in my previous posts where I felt that a session would be great
for a teacher at another point in their career but it didn&amp;#39;t scratch
my itch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, given that any attendee can only go to one session per slot
and since descriptions don&amp;#39;t always tell the whole story, perceptions
vary. I just read Amy Ko&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/bits-and-behavior/csta-2024-trip-report-mixed-messages-20222112a788&#34;&gt;CSTA report&lt;/a&gt; and Amy lamented the lack of
equity and justice focus. I felt there was good coverage there. I on
the other hand felt that there should have been more coverage on
actual content and pedagogy. Both of us could be right, both of us
could be wrong. At the end of the day though, CSTA provided a platform
with CS teachers from across the country could discuss whatever issues
they desired with a diverse range of colleagues and that&amp;#39;s a pretty
special thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;d be remiss if I didn&amp;#39;t close with a few words on my tourist time. I
wasn&amp;#39;t excited to come to Las Vegas - I&amp;#39;m not into casinos and coming
from New York I&amp;#39;ve got better and cheaper food options as well as
pretty much any entertainment I want. In NY I also don&amp;#39;t feel like
then entire town is trying to scam me for my money. I don&amp;#39;t want to
come down though on residents of Las Vegas though since I do know a
couple of great people who live there so I&amp;#39;m sure people there are
just like everywhere else it&amp;#39;s just that the tourist industry there
isn&amp;#39;t for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, we did do a number of things we enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did a couple of day trips with Pink Jeep tours - one to Hoover Dam
and the other to Red Rock Canyon. Our Red Rock tour guide was the
better of the two but both were solid and both trips 100% worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also visited the Atomic Testing Museum and the Mob Museum. Both
were really interesting. I&amp;#39;ve always been interested in the mob thing,
particularly the Jewish Mob in New York so the Mob Museum was a
particular hit for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We walked Freemont Street, which was basically another touristy strip
but got a great apple fritter at a donut shop across from one of the
ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On our last afternoon, after our Red Rock tour we grabbed lunch at
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sayulitaseats.com/&#34;&gt;Sayulitas&lt;/a&gt; - a hole in the wall burrito place. I&amp;#39;ve got to say -
probably our best meal in Vegas.  All the strip stuff was overpriced
although some was tasty but Sayulitas was dynamite. When we got in, we
were concerned about the lack of seating but there was a huge crowd of
locals and pretty much no English being spoken - all good
signs. Hadn&amp;#39;t had burritos that good in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there we went to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pinballmuseum.org/&#34;&gt;Pinball Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt;. While I&amp;#39;m not into
casinos, I love pinball. Basically a pinball parlor with machines
ranging from the early days up until today. Also a bunch of novelty
machines like a vertical circus game with three mini pinball games in
it and a couple of two player games where each player is on opposite
sides and the playfield tilts back and forth. Super cool. Price per
game range from a quarter for some of the old machines to a dollar for
the new ones. Devorah and I spent a couple of hours and $20 and had a
super fun time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&amp;#39;s CSTA 2024. Before flying to Las Vegas, I was already not hot
on the town and also not so hot on some aspects of CSTA, the national
organization. I think the most positive thing I can say is that I left
the conference not only energized but thinking about proposing a
session or two for next year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2024 - the final day</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 19:51:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
The conference ended this past Friday. After a couple of morning
sessions I started to play tourist which included spending more time
in the 100+ degree out doors. Fun stuff that I&amp;#39;ll talk about later but
left me too drained Friday and Saturday evening to continue my write
ups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First up was another AI session &amp;#34;Unlocking AI: Teaching Artificial
Intelligence in K12.&amp;#34; Slides and other materials can be found
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/121zotqh5_kr7jSP3HdUQue-vyT-goWznqFvjTbyvcWE/edit#slide=id.g2df995fa4b0_0_417&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The speakers were Nora Burkhauser who gave the talk on &amp;#34;Machine
Learning for Kids&amp;#34; and Nick Yates. The talk focused on two
professional development opportunities they&amp;#39;ve developed to bring K12
teachers of all grade levels and all subjects up to speed on
Artificial Intelligence. Well really one PD opportunity split into two
part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part one, offered via remote sessions with interspersed assignments
followed by in person PD covered the basics. Basic definitions,
classic ML and AI, a typical AI pipeline. From where I sat, it looked
like this course provided a good overview for any teacher new to
AI. It didn&amp;#39;t, in my opinion cover enough for a CS teacher in a HS
class to do a full AI unit but given time constraints of a typical PD,
it&amp;#39;s a great start and looks like it provides plenty for the early
grade teachers and the non CS teachers while at least getting the CS
teachers on the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Part 2 goes over available AI curricula, touches on modern AI -
generative AI, neural nets etc., and also goes over applying AI. In
fact, they presented the same lesson, more or less, as was presented
in the &amp;#34;Machine Learning for Kids&amp;#34; talk I attended on Thursday. This
part 2 course certainly adds to the foundation for the early grade
teacher on non CS teacher, but still wouldn&amp;#39;t be enough, in my opinion
for the HS teacher. I understand that the speakers can only do so
much - they can&amp;#39;t offer one or more college or graduate level courses
in AI - they have to work within their state&amp;#39;s professional
development system but we have to become vocal about the fact that so
long as our CS teachers are not coming in with strong content
knowledge, add on professional development isn&amp;#39;t a solution, it&amp;#39;s just
window dressing. Sure, right now it&amp;#39;s frequently the best we can do
but more people have to start banging the drum that we &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; our CS
teachers to actually have a good amount of knowledge in, you know, CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before moving on, I do want to say again that this was another strong
session and the speakers are doing great work, they&amp;#39;re just trying to
do their best within the limitations of the system under which they
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After this AI talk I attended some lightening talks. The first was
given by a new teacher on  her just barely staying ahead of her
class. It was a nice talk but got me thinking that it might be useful
for CSTA to specifically set up an affinity meeting that combined
brand new CS teachers (particularly those with limited content
knowledge) and match them with groups of slightly more experienced
teachers - say those with 3 or 4 years experience. Teachers with
enough mileage so that they can provide encouragement and guidance to
the neophytes but not with so much experience that they&amp;#39;ve forgotten
the struggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another lightening talk was about creating a social media presence. I
was interested in this because the speaker was going to talk about
making short form videos and I&amp;#39;ve spent the past decade+ in the world
of blogs. Unfortunately, the talk was really more about how to tweak
your already existing video content to maximize viewers. Valuable if
you&amp;#39;ve already got a video presence but not the info I was hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn&amp;#39;t attend the last keynote so that was it for me but that&amp;#39;s not
it for my SIGCSE post. Next up, the exhibitors, Las Vegas and final
thoughts on the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2024 day 3 part 2 - AI and a keynote panel</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-3-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 09:56:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-3-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
So, I stopped my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-3/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; after my thoughts on the DEI talk. The actual
post wasn&amp;#39;t all that long, the reason I said for stopping the post but
rather because writing that post was emotionally draining. Can I talk
about that stuff? Will people interpret it the way I intended. Will
people who I don&amp;#39;t want to offend and don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;m offending, will
they be offended? Will the people I want to offend not be offended
(okay, just joking here). It&amp;#39;s really hard for people to have these
conversations and too many people these days don&amp;#39;t allow for nuance
but I felt it important to get my thoughts out there. Not so much
because my thoughts are anything special or that they&amp;#39;re right or
wrong but one, because the session was terrific and I am documenting
my conference experience and two because having these conversations
won&amp;#39;t get easier unless people are willing to put themselves out
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, back to our regular programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thursday afternoon I sat in on &amp;#34;AI Lessons using Machine Learning for
Kids.&amp;#34; &lt;a href=&#34;https://machinelearningforkids.co.uk/#!/login&#34;&gt;Machine Learning for Kids&lt;/a&gt; is a site/platform that allows people
to set up and train machine learning models. The speaker&amp;#39;s slide deck
with links to resources can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1AJ5sfkMVzl_JNnnVeTOnEZD__fe8b7LN_2sPTpFLH44/edit#slide=id.g272ca406bce_0_21&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The speaker walked us through how she used ML for kids with her
class. She basically teaches a typical Machine Learning pipeline, that
is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;collect data &amp;gt; prepare/clean &amp;gt; select model &amp;gt; train &amp;gt; validate
&amp;gt; predict&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Her specific project was sentiment analysis of text. The platform can also
work with images, sounds, and numbers. After logging in (or clicking
to try without registering) you start a project. You select the model
you&amp;#39;re using, &amp;#34;recognizing text&amp;#34; in this case. You then use their
interface to add data. The instructor, of course, would have to
provide guidance so that a student would know what and how to enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When finished, you click the train button and the platform builds the
model. I&amp;#39;m pretty sure you can then play with the model but I didn&amp;#39;t
actually test that. The cool thing, to me was that you can then have
the platform generate code - scratch, python, and a couple of other
platforms. I clicked the generate button and all of a sudden I got a
chunk of Python code that I could embed in a program. Specifically,
the code let you use your now trained model as a library (or more
specifically, web based API) and make calls with data and get your
results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While this is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; cool, it raised some questions. The big one for me
is that you can go through all of this and have almost zero knowledge
of the underlying machine learning. Contrast that with the session I
wrote up a couple of days ago where the students learned all the
little details of gradient descent for linear regression (more on this
later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is this really the right way to go?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The instructor noted that when we use a tool like ChatGPT we&amp;#39;re using
an already trained model so this is no different. That&amp;#39;s true but in a
class learning about, say sentiment analysis as an ML technique, I
think students should learn how the sausage is made. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, this approach of leaving the actual ML as a black box does still
allow for some good learning to go on.  Students will learn the
pipeline. They can also discuss issues like false positives and true
negatives - the effects of different training data, over training and
much more. They could also see, from a user point of view if different
models produce different results. A teacher might also have constraints
to keep them from diving deeper - insufficient time, toolset limits,
student backgrounds and I&amp;#39;m sure others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, I&amp;#39;m a firm believer in seeing what&amp;#39;s under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, going back to the Linear Regression talk from Wednesday, that
might be too much for an average high school class and almost
certainly too much for a pre APCS-A class so where do you draw the
line?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that in a CS0 class using a text based language like
Python, students can pretty easily write a simple sentiment analysis
system. You can also scaffold pretty thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The basic gist is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make two lists, one of positive words, one of negative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read in the text you want to test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split the text into words&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Count how many words are in the positive list and how many in the
negative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there are more positive than negative, it&amp;#39;s a positive piece,
otherwise negative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is extremely bare bones and has issues. For instance if a
document has &amp;#34;not bad&amp;#34; in it it&amp;#39;ll just see the word bad and classify
as negative but that&amp;#39;s something the class can talk about. The project
can also be easily extended in any number of ways. You can also
include all of the good things from the speakers lesson design - the
pipeline, different training sets, etc.. The important thing is that
the students will have a stronger understanding of how sentiment
analysis actually works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While this was a strong session, I&amp;#39;m a big believer in students
understanding the inner workings of things and I think this is going
to be even more important with the current AI craze - this is
something one of the end of day keynote panelists actually pointed out
(more on that down below). Of course, you have to know your
population, where they&amp;#39;re at, and what your restrictions are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In middle school with scratch, the black box approach is most likely
the way to go, particularly since ML for kids hooks in to
scratch. Teaching a High School class using Python? You should
probably do a unit where your class codes the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just my opinion and approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One final note before moving on to the rest of the day. I&amp;#39;ve noticed
that while there are plenty of sessions that, by description, talk
about ChatGPT tools - what&amp;#39;s considered the cutting edge of the AI
fad, there have been a few sessions on Machine Learning and more
traditional AI. This has been great to see as so much of what runs and
what will run the world operates using these techniques and
technologies and it&amp;#39;s important not to drop them in education for the
flavor of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That was it for the Thursday sessions for me, I spent the rest of the
session time looking at the posters and the hallway track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Thursday keynote was a panel moderated by education journalist
Natasha Singer. The panelists were (as seated left to right):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christy Crawford of the New York City Board of Ed&amp;#39;s CSforAll initiative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maggie Johnson, Global head and VP, Google.org&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mehram Sahami, Chair of the CS department, Stanford University&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kip Glazer, Principal, Mountain View High School &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving in to the panel, I&amp;#39;ve got to express more pride in my
Hunter CS Teacher Cert program graduates. While delivering some
opening comments, Natasha Singer gave a shout out to another Hunter CS
Certified teacher, Marisa Shuman citing some of the work Marisa&amp;#39;s done
bringing AI to her students in New York. Here&amp;#39;s Natasha&amp;#39;s article
about it: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sanjuandailystar.com/post/at-this-school-computer-science-class-now-includes-critiquing-chatbots&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now to the panel. Overall it was a great session but I did notice one
thing missing. There were no actual teachers on the panel. Maggie
Johnson&amp;#39;s from Google and he background&amp;#39;s in higher ed as is Mehram
Sahami&amp;#39;s. Christy Crawford doesn&amp;#39;t show any classroom teaching
experience on her linkedin. Only Kip Glazer listed any K12 teaching
experience on linkedin and that ended back in 2016 - about 11 years
total which is a nice chunk but in my mind generally not anywhere near
the time needed for mastery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It would have been nice to have at least one actual K12 teacher up
there. Even better if it were an experienced CS teacher who also had
strong content knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first question was on the overall impact of AI in
education. Mehram was first to respond and hit the nail on the head -
AI can&amp;#39;t transform education, only people (teachers can transform
education. Bravo. He added that AI can enhance teachers ability to
transform education but it&amp;#39;s just a tool. As a side note, I really
felt that Mehram was pretty much spot on throughout. I was very
impressed with his responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Christy chimed in with a common teacher&amp;#39;s fear - will AI replace them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think this was an interesting juxtaposition. You have the academic
speaking the truth of how things should be and the person immersed in
K12 noting the unfortunate reality that the politicians and private
interests are always looking to save money and turn a buck by cutting
teachers and directing money to private companies to &amp;#34;compensate.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next question asked were coding should live in K12 with tools like
copilot and other code generating LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Maggie noted that even if AI can generate code, it still needs to be
understood, checked, tested, extended, and embedded. She said she
didn&amp;#39;t know how much coding would be necessary but certainly it&amp;#39;s
something we much teach in K12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Mehran noted that teaching coding syntax is still important and that
we can use tools like chatGPT like a code library or API to enhance
our student&amp;#39;s work. This echoed something I wrote about when I wrote
up this year&amp;#39;s SIGCSE experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In response to Natasha Singer asking if there should be limits on
AI on AI Maggie spoke on how it&amp;#39;s something that Google talks about
top to bottom every day. When she followed up with &amp;#34;what about in the
classroom&amp;#34; Christy chimed in yes but added an oh so important &amp;#34;but not
on the backs of the teachers.&amp;#34; I do lament that there wasn&amp;#39;t an actual
teacher on the panel but applaud Christy for consistently having
teacher&amp;#39;s backs throughout the panel. It&amp;#39;s not a surprise, she&amp;#39;s
always had teacher&amp;#39;s backs in her role at CSforAll. I wish others in
the NY DOE would follow her lead more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Natasha also asked about corporate influences on curriculum as this is
something somewhat unique to CS. As a new field and a new field in
K12, few teachers and schools knew what to teach so for better or
worse, outsiders filled the void. That&amp;#39;s the college board, code.org,
organizations like PLTW, companies liked CODEHS. This doesn&amp;#39;t happen
in other older fields. A friend of mine later pointed out that it sort
of does but the outside influencers are the book publishers. Anyway,
Maggie posited that technology changes so fast that industry is needed
to keep curriculum up to date. I think she misinterpreted the question
though. I  believe Natasha was specifically talking about content
providers like those I listed above while Maggie was thinking about
pure tech companies informing curriculum which, if they did and if
they &amp;#34;stepped back&amp;#34; to go back to yesterday&amp;#39;s post would be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think Mehram also misinterpreted the question as he talked of the
symbiotic relationship between industry and education. I think he was
thinking more about the university industry relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once again, though, Christy had the teacher&amp;#39;s backs when she on the
one hand noted how important industry can be - they can inform,
provide opportunities like mentoring, and support but there has to be
a hard line. They should not be driving curriculum or
education. Again, bravo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point, we ran out of time. Great panel. As I said, I
particularly liked Mehram&amp;#39;s comments which included a number I didn&amp;#39;t
mention here as well as Christy&amp;#39;s constant defense of teachers but
everyone was terrific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s it for day 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the next day or so I&amp;#39;ll get to day 4, the exhibitors, and some
closing thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2024 day 3</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 17:37:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Started out today in a session titled &amp;#34;Keep Calm and AI on.&amp;#34; The panel
was made up of CSTA Equity Fellows. It turned out that the session
wasn&amp;#39;t what I was looking for. According to the description the panel
was supposed to cover &amp;#34;the promise and the challenges of various
artificial intelligence tools, especially generative AI tools such as
ChatGPT, Copilot, and Bard.&amp;#34; Instead it was a general panel and
discussion of the use of AI. To be frank, the session wasn&amp;#39;t really
focused on CS educators at all and could just as easily been plopped
down int a PD session for any subject or grade level. Now, that&amp;#39;s not
necessarily bad but it just wasn&amp;#39;t what I was hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The panel consisted of a number of questions where each panelist had
their say and then the moderator, also a panelist solicited thoughts
from the audience.  The questions they asked were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What ethical concerns do you have?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In your setting, how is AI used?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;#39;s one piece of advice you&amp;#39;d share?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What work have you seen being done for AI in education?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your call to action?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moderator ran the panel well and we got to share many points of
view. Personally, I was hoping for a discussion of some specifics with
using CS specific tools like copilot or issues or possibilities with
applying ore general tools like ChatGPT in a CS classroom or lesson
but I suspect that the panel as it went own was probably pretty
valuable to a lot of people in the audience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My second session was &amp;#34;The Power of Words in CS Education&amp;#34; - another
panel. As per the description, &amp;#34;this panel discussion aims to explore
the intricacies of intercommunication and confront uncomfortable
conversations&amp;#34; with the key word being DEI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The questions were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What comes to mind when you hear the term DEI?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who can talk about DEI?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What issues have you had speaking your truth in this space?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we need DEI offices and spaces?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who owns this space?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints, the panel never got to the last two quesitons
(other than a quick mention of question 4 where the consensus answer
in the room was &amp;#34;yes&amp;#34;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The panel was run much like the AI session I described with the
panelists sharing their thoughts and then the moderator (again, also a
panelist) solicited audience input and again the session was run
smoothly and effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I want to highlight some thoughts that came out on question 2 - who
can talk about DEI as well some thoughts I had based on something one
of the panelists said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One panelist commented that anyone can talk about DEI but talk is
cheap, we have to look at actions. My take is that you&amp;#39;ve got to walk
the walk and thought about all the companies who crow about their DEI
programs but really just pay lip service. Companies who claim they&amp;#39;re
pushing say black SWE hires but really only fight with with the other
top companies to monopolize the candidates from say Stanford. They
talk the talk but aren&amp;#39;t really doing anything to improve the
situation but rather they&amp;#39;re just trying to gobble up the low hanging
fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another panelist mentioned that we need white people involved
but they need to know when to step back. This is a tricky one. I get
it - I can&amp;#39;t understand the life experiences, situation, or needs of
say a black person in the USA and I certainly shouldn&amp;#39;t be telling one
what they should feel or what they need but on the other hand I might
actually have some background where I should be stepping in in a
complementary way or might be raising a relevant issue. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll share two personal situations where I was frozen out of a
community for not &amp;#34;stepping back.&amp;#34; One was a conversation with some
people about the LGBTQ+ pride parade in NYC. My position was that
while I&amp;#39;m all for the parade, I had a problem with what I saw at the
parade a number of years ago - near naked people on floats essentially
performing simulated sex. Apparently I wasn&amp;#39;t stepping back. Now to
me, I wasn&amp;#39;t telling anyone in this young subset of the LGBTQ+
community how to celebrate or behave and I wasn&amp;#39;t telling the members
of this set of LBGTQ+ community members how to live their lives. I
was conveying my opinion that as a parent I really didn&amp;#39;t want to have to start
explaining people having simulated sex mid day on a float to my young
kids. Please note, my objection wasn&amp;#39;t specific to this parade, I&amp;#39;ve
had the same complaint to other non LGBTQ+ parades that cut through
family areas during the day. Was I out of line? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other time was in a discussion of the SHSAT - the exam you take
for admission to Stuy/Science/Tech etc.. There&amp;#39;s long been a problem
with the low number of black students being admitted to these schools
and Stuy in particular. A number of ideas have been floated including
one particularly bad one - admit the valedictorian of each middle
school. I asserted why this was a horribly bad idea. I as accused of
being a racist and frozen out. To them, I wasn&amp;#39;t standing back. To me,
I was pointing out the reality that this solution didn&amp;#39;t get to the
root cause of the problem and also wouldn&amp;#39;t end well. I obviously
can&amp;#39;t walk in the footsteps of a black middle school student or their
parents but I had much greater knowledge of the test and test process,
what Stuy was like and how it operated and think I had and have a much
better understanding of what the outcome would be from this plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Was I out of line and should have stepped back or was I appropriately
contributing to the discussion. It can get complicated, particularly
if recognize that many of these situations are pretty nuanced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A final comment I&amp;#39;ll make is that one of the panelists mentioned that
they don&amp;#39;t want allies, they want co-conspirators. The difference
being that a co-conspirator will step in front of a car for them. I
get this and agree but it also irritated me. Not about the speaker or
the panel but something I&amp;#39;ve noticed going on with some subsets of DEI
supporting communities. I&amp;#39;m hoping that these subsets are small but
vocal minorities but it&amp;#39;s hard to believe that given what I&amp;#39;ve seen in
the media. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a white male Jew. Back in the day Jews were recognized as
co-conspirators with the black community and the LGBTQ+ community. We
would not only figuratively step in front of a car for those
communities but at times literally do so. Recently I&amp;#39;ve noticed the
rise of antisemitic voices coming from some of those communities. This
forces me to examine my relationship with these communities and makes
me sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really enjoyed this session but think it&amp;#39;s important to note that
this was another session that really had no focus on CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I still want to write about one more session I attended as well as the
Thursday keynote and the exhibit halls (including a bit on Kira
Learning) not to mention tomorrow but I think this is long enough for
today&amp;#39;s post. I&amp;#39;ll cover the rest in the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSTA 2024 day 2</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 23:01:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csta-2024-day-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
What, no day 1? Well, day one was all workshops followed by a keynote
and a reception. I generally don&amp;#39;t do workshops and got in too late
for the keynote but I did hit the reception but not too much to write
about there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year the CSTA conference is in Las Vegas. I&amp;#39;ve never been to
Vegas and there&amp;#39;s not really much of a draw here for me. I&amp;#39;m not into
gambling, the food, for a New Yorker is nothing special and while
there are a number of shows that are unique to Vegas, again, as a New
Yorker, it&amp;#39;s not like I&amp;#39;m lacking for local entertainment
options. That said, there are some things I&amp;#39;ll enjoy taking in while
I&amp;#39;m here - the spectacle of everything, the Mob museum, Hoover Dam,
and Red Rock Canyon in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, though, I really don&amp;#39;t get putting a teacher conference
here. Everything is &lt;strong&gt;so&lt;/strong&gt; expensive. The rooms were reasonable (even with
the resort fee) but everything is nickle and dime. The room only comes
with 2 WIFI connections so if you&amp;#39;re 2 teachers sharing a room and
each need a phone and computer on WIFI, that&amp;#39;s $30 extra a day. Then
you&amp;#39;ve got food. A medium coffee in the morning is going to set you
back $7 or $8 and today lunch cost me around $25 for a mediocre
sandwich and a cannoli - around $10 more than I&amp;#39;d pay in NYC which is
not a cheap town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I don&amp;#39;t get the location but I still really enjoyed the opening
reception, had a blast today as well and am a big fan of the CSTA
conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start out the day I sat in on John Dutton&amp;#39;s session &amp;#34;Creating a
toolkit for all CS learners.&amp;#34; I was hoping to avoid an AI talk since I
knew I&amp;#39;d get plenty of those later on but I really wasn&amp;#39;t sure where
this session would lead. It turns out I didn&amp;#39;t avoid an AI talk but
that was okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first half of John&amp;#39;s talk was on how he set up his class culture -
something that&amp;#39;s both very important and also frequently neglected. He
spoke about empowering the class by asking them how they would like
this class to be different than others they&amp;#39;ve had - it reminded me of
my friend and former student Davin, who, whenever he starts a new
company spends time with the founding team discussing what they did
and didn&amp;#39;t like about the culture of their past companies and then
uses their combined experiences to make a strong positive culture for
their new venture. John&amp;#39; talks about student &amp;#34;jobs&amp;#34; in the class and
more. I ran into John at lunch later and we chatted a bit. I felt that
our thoughts are pretty aligned on class culture being really
important but also confirmed my suspicion that he only had around 14
kids per class which affords him more opportunities to set a positive
culture than a teacher of say 34 per class in a crowded room. This is
not to take away anything from his work as he&amp;#39;s aware of this
advantage and appreciates it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
John also talked about some CS teaching techniques. Well, they&amp;#39;re not
really CS specific techniques but CS teachers frequently use them -
rubber duck debugging, asking classmates before asking the teacher and
a few other strategies. Then, the main event, a template to set up an
assignment that then used a script that used AI to take the data in
the form and create multiple, differentiated versions of the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, there wasn&amp;#39;t a lot in this session for me given that I&amp;#39;m
not teaching right now but for a new CS teacher, I could see a lot of
value. I think I thought there would be more actual CS in the
presentation but that&amp;#39;s neither here nor there. John shared &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1bUW03Qwvy2LvvUAIeH5j2n-K5jMxNk-M&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; link
with materials which includes along with his lesson template, lists of
frameworks and other resources, and a whole lot more. If you&amp;#39;re
relatively new to teaching CS I&amp;#39;d strongly recommend you click on the
link and check out everything provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was a teacher certification talk given by three educators fro
Gwinnett County Georgia. The talk covered the state of things in
Georgia and what they&amp;#39;ve been doing. I learned that in Georgia, one
has to have certification (or rather, an endorsement) to teach
CS. This can be earned either by taking an exam or by earning an
endorsement through an approved program. This group from Gwinnett
designed a one year and also acquired funding to cover costs. I like a
lot of what they&amp;#39;re trying to do. The Gwinnett team developed a one
year boot camp for current teachers and area trying to emphasize a
community model along with mentorship. Philosophically, at least from
the pedagogy and implementation side, their program sounds similar to
what I designed at Hunter in New York. My concern has to do with the
depth of CS knowledge they&amp;#39;re covering. This isn&amp;#39;t necessarily the
fault of the Gwinnett team though, it appears this is what Georgia&amp;#39;s
requiring and if they require content far deeper than Georgia
requires, the state might not approve of their program and teachers
might not attend. Their program maxes out at APCS-P which to me, is
way to elementary for a certified High School CS teacher. Those
teachers need, in my opinion, at least a bit beyond APCS-A along with
a good deal of breadth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was interesting to hear about what was going on in another state
and while it sounds like Gwinnett County Schools are doing some pretty
good work within the framework and constraints their state provides, I
fear that by setting the CS bar so low, Georgia is shortchanging their
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, I attended John Chapin&amp;#39;s session on &amp;#34;Machine Learning
Made (more) simple.&amp;#34; I loved this session. John&amp;#39;s material is all
&lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/CSTA-ML&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. John described and walked us through how he teachers linear
regression. His goal was to teach us (his students) how it works
rather than just use a library or black box toolkit. I&amp;#39;m 100% behind
this. Now, it is true that John&amp;#39;s at a public magnet school with high
achieving students just like I was at Stuyvesant and what he
presented, out of the box, probably can&amp;#39;t be  implemented in a typical
school but the approach and attitude certainly can and should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
John motivated the problem by asking what data would be helpful in
predicting home prices, he then had his class (us) work for a time in
groups to try to figure out relationships and even models to go from
the data to something to predict prices. He then stepped us through
unplugged hands on exercises that led us to and through gradient
descent. This in turn led to code and in the end, the class had both
written and understood a key machine learning technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Great session and I hope the attendees take this approach in some of
their CS classes. As I said, I don&amp;#39;t think this specific assignment
will go over well as is with all populations but I think the approach
can. I&amp;#39;ve successfully done similar things both my AP classes and in
pre AP programming classes like when I cover writing a Caesar Cipher
decryption program. The difference is that in the Linear Regression
lesson the class is learning a specific machine learning technique
that requires a certain level of mathematical sophistication to really
&amp;#34;get&amp;#34; while in my case, we do a simpler problem that uses many similar
techniques but with simpler mathematics and simpler application. My
problem sets the stage for that ML lesson a couple of years later. I
also do something similar in my &amp;#34;who played Spiderman&amp;#34; unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Great session. I was concerned that all of the AI sessions - and there
are many - will all be, taking out policy sessions about using
existing tools and libraries and not result in students really
understand what&amp;#39;s going on under the hood. This talk allayed that
concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I just hit the posters and exhibits for the last sessions and then
attended the closing keynote delivered by Gholdy Muhammid -
&amp;#34;Cultivating Genius and Joy in Education Through Culturally and
Historically Responsive Pedagogies.&amp;#34; I thoroughly enjoyed the
talk. Muhammid is an engaging, entertaining and funny speaker. My
takeaway was that our teaching should be evaluated by the Joy in the
classroom and the pursuit of knowledge as opposed to just the standards
based evaluation currently used which just measures facts and only
facts. Note that I say &amp;#34;just the standards&amp;#34; and not instead of
them. To her credit Ms. Muhammid noted that standards - the specifics,
the skills, the facts are important as well. This is critical. One of
my annoyances at a lot of the K12 CS movement is that there&amp;#39;s
frequently only emphasis on the joy and they ignore the facts that at
the end of the day the teacher must know some, I don&amp;#39;t know, actual CS
and that students must learn it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, Ms. Muhammid&amp;#39;s talk was really all about the type of
education reform we really need in our schools. I had a couple of
quibbles but it was a great talk. If CSTA releases a video, take the
time to watch it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The day ended with Devorah, who played tourist by day, and I went for
drinks and some light dinner with the New York contingent at the
conference. A highlight was getting together with four students from
my CS certification program at Hunter including Marisa - a CSTA Equity
Fellow and incoming CSTA-NYC board member, Jessica and Josh - both CSTA-NYC
board members, and Victoria - the first person in New York State to
earn a Masters in CS Education from an approved certification program
and earn the associated license. So proud to have been privileged to
work with all four of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/csta-2024.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/csta-2024.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/csta-2024.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Dino Podcast</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/dino-podcast/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 16:57:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/dino-podcast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I love talking shop but I don&amp;#39;t have the opportunity to do so as much
now that I&amp;#39;m retired. So, when my former student &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dino-beslic-1b761a63/&#34;&gt;Dino Beslic&lt;/a&gt; emailed
me and asked if I wanted to be on his podcast, &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/show/6dJKlNZKxdaN6D6yrtDHBq&#34;&gt;The Dino Podcast&lt;/a&gt;, I was
both honored and excited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dino was a student of mine in the early 2000s but we haven&amp;#39;t been in
touch for years. I reached out to his brother Denis, also a student of
mine, in order to connect yet another student to him for a job
referral. Denis talked to Dino and that ended up in me being invited
on the show. Of course, I&amp;#39;m also excited about being reconnected with
both Denis and Dino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Dino&amp;#39;s a Tech CFO and investor and his podcast is about &amp;#34;business,
technology, and geopolitics.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The tech job market has been in a downturn for the past couple of
years and at the same time, we&amp;#39;ve seen a rise in AI an AI based
programming assistants and related technologies. Dino and I spent a
little over an hour talking about reasons for the downturn, if and how
AI and the downturn were affecting the market and education. We also
projected a bit into the future and made some recommendations for
youngsters starting out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I particularly enjoyed the fact that we were talking about education
at the college level up into the workforce - most of my recent shop
talks have focused on K12 and while I&amp;#39;m passionate about my work
there, I&amp;#39;ve also done a lot with preparing students for the tech
workforce and navigating early careers and am wondering if that&amp;#39;s an
area I&amp;#39;ll go back to focusing on for my next adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, if you&amp;#39;ve got the time, check out the Dino Podcast. Here&amp;#39;s a link
to the episode I&amp;#39;m on: &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.spotify.com/episode/1MktTuxoD0QoWbwSh060CF&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hidden Communities of New York</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/hidden-communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 15:09:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/hidden-communities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Now that I&amp;#39;m not teaching CS every day, I find the desire to maybe
write about some other things. I&amp;#39;ve still got a bunch of CS and
education posts lined up, but for today, something different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was out for my morning run a couple of days ago. I usually leave my
apartment between 5:00 and 5:45, go to the Hudson River and run an out
and back. It&amp;#39;s still pretty quiet at that time. When I leave later,
the park is much more filled with runners, running groups, and bike
commuters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m heading south and walking north is an older couple. I
say older couple but let&amp;#39;s be fair, They&amp;#39;re probably around my age and
I&amp;#39;m just older than I care to admit although based on my current pace
and recovery time, I should know better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We wave good morning to each other and keep on our way. A little
later, I see a younger man walking and running south (it was really
hot and humid). We cross paths regularly but since we were going in
the same direction and frequently wave, I slowed to join him. I said
that after waving high for a couple of years, we might as well learn
each other&amp;#39;s names. We fist bumped, or rather he went for the bump, I
went for the handshake, we switched but then finally synced. So,
that&amp;#39;s how I met Chris. We chatted for a few minutes - we both live in
Chelsea, how we both get an energy boost whenever we see our &amp;#34;running
buddies&amp;#34; in the morning, and also about some of the other early
morning runners we&amp;#39;ve met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He named Vicky, who I&amp;#39;ve been waving to for three or four years. Then
I gave him Suki - the first person I started saying hello
to. Suki and I would cross paths near Stuy, her walking north, me
running south. She would greet &lt;strong&gt;everybody&lt;/strong&gt; with a warm smile, a wave and
a strong Good Morning! After a while, I slowed my run one day to get
to know here. We also talked about Priscilla, the Mayor of Hudson
River Park - at least to us early risers. Priscilla would always be
walking or running on the path along with her magnificent dog
Buddy. Unfortunately, Buddy passed about a year ago. We both lamented
that we haven&amp;#39;t seen Priscilla lately and we both hope it&amp;#39;s because
our schedules have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We talked of a few others and I noted that I really have to introduce
myself to that couple I passed earlier and then went we on to complete
our individual morning workouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got to thinking about this community. It&amp;#39;s not a normal
community. We don&amp;#39;t all know each others names and really very little
about each other but every morning, or at least a few times a week
we&amp;#39;ve come to expect to see each other and greet each other with a
smile, a happy hello, or a thumbs up or some other encouragement. We
get a boost when we do but we grow concerned when we don&amp;#39;t see our
morning amigos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In New York, we don&amp;#39;t have that small town everyone knows their neighbors
thing. Heck, I live in a 20 story apartment building and barely know
my neighbors. We also don&amp;#39;t have neighborhood schools and the mom and
pop store everywhere is a dying breed. Yet, we still have these weird
little communities that crop up. I look forward to seeing my running
buddies again early tomorrow morning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Schools for New Teachers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/good-schools-for-new-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 14:13:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/good-schools-for-new-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Usually, when I write about a teacher get together it&amp;#39;s either my
StuyCS people or CS educators. Last week, it was another group. Each
year, Devorah, along with a bunch of her former colleagues from the
Manhattan Center for Science and Math (MCSM) get together for a year
end celebration. They&amp;#39;ve been doing this for something like 20 years
even though most of the crew is retired now and all but I think one or
two have left MCSM. For the most part, they all started close to the
same time and most were in the Science department. I&amp;#39;ve joined in from
time to time and they usually get a good crowd of between one to two
dozen teachers. Last year, the gathering focused on Devorah&amp;#39;s
retirement and this year on another from the crew. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, I&amp;#39;m a little jealous. sure, we used to have periodic end
of term lunches at Stuy but to keep a group together even after so
many have left the fold is pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
David, a terrific Physics teacher in the group (and presumably the retiring
honoree next year) made a comment, noting that so many of the group
started at around the same time. He said that they were really lucky
because MCSM was a really good school for new teachers. He commented
on how much support he got across the board and how his colleagues,
supervisors, and administrators really helped him and others grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking. My first few years of teaching were at Seward
Park High School - actually, a school with some similarities to
MCSM. Both were large schools. Not giant monsters like Stuy or
Brooklyn Tech but still pretty large. Both also had a range of
students in terms of ethnicity as well as academic performance. In
those early days I had classes with kids on parole, drug dealers, and
thugs and I also had classes with the nicest kids you&amp;#39;d ever met. I
had kids who in 10th grade or beyond could barely add and I had super
high achieving honors students. All that and everything in between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest difference between MCSM and Seward Park is that at Seward most of
the faculty were at war with the administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been told often that &amp;#34;bad&amp;#34; schools - rough students and/or
horrid administrations frequently result in very close knit faculties
and that seemed to be true at Seward. They all banded together and as
a newbie, they took me under their wings. Now, I personally had no
problems with the administration - I got along very well with my
direct supervisor and he loved me but I still was adopted by so many
others. New teachers frequently get the worst program but my chairman
had a different approach - he rotated everybody - he worked to give
me - the new kid - some tough classes and some easier ones and worked
to get me through the entire math sequence quickly. As to the
faculty - they helped me with lessons, sat in on my class, and let me sit
in with them. They also saved me with discipline issues. I had one
particularly rough class and a colleague with nonchalantly wander in
to use a computer in the back of the room. He came in because he knew
his presence would help with the discipline. The kids settled down and
were non the wiser. Mike (his name as well), would then on a day to
day basis work with me between classes until I could handle things on
my own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Without the support of teachers like Mike, as well as a handful of
others, I would never have made it to year two let alone a three plus
decade career. Very little of this support I got was official but it
was critical in my staying in and succeeding as a teacher. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, MCSM didn&amp;#39;t have a dysfunctional administration. In fact, from
what I saw, they were pretty good. It wasn&amp;#39;t until three principals
later that they got their disaster, which ultimately prompted a
handful of retirements and many transfers so might be fairly unique
that Dave, Devorah, and all of them had a school with both a good
administration and a united faculty, or at least science department
that really fostered the development of new teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think something that also helped both at Seward for me and MCSM was
the size of the school. Being large schools, there were always
multiple teachers for each subject. That meant a new teacher was never
on an island. It also meant that there were many other teachers to
observe, learn from, and get support from. It also meant that there
was never just one or two of the more desirable classes so while new
teachers might have gotten less desirable programs, they didn&amp;#39;t get
the worst of the worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Contrast those two schools with Stuyvesant when I started. Stuy was
also a large school - in fact much larger, with few discipline
problems. I&amp;#39;d say that Stuy, back then, was much worse in terms of new teacher
development. Sure, teachers were nice enough - I became friends with a
number of them, but truth be told the most you&amp;#39;d get would be 
some notes from a previous semester or you could quietly sit in on
class. At Seward, I got that, plus debriefings but check ins and
more. At Stuy, I got the least desirable classes until I took over CS
(although even the worst classes at Stuy were pretty desirable) as
well as the worst rooming situation - I was running from the third
floor to the 7th and back between three periods early on. At Seward,
my program was pretty much the same as everyone else. 
I&amp;#39;d like to hope I helped foster a better environment as the CS
program grew and we brought in new teachers but I can&amp;#39;t say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another problem with Stuy, at least for new teachers, and this is
probably true at many high performing schools, both public and
private, is that new teachers don&amp;#39;t really have to learn how to
teach. They can be bad at their craft and the students will still pass
the standardized exams. I&amp;#39;ve seen new teachers at stuy who never
taught elsewhere who thought they were great but really weren&amp;#39;t - at
best they got by on the fact that they were young and had some
charisma. Their kids did alright but deserved better. Some were self
aware enough to figure it out but by and large it was an issue. Of
course at a tough school the new teacher would just leave the
profession while at the high performing school, the teacher in
question might go on to a career of just not teaching that well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In a profession with an extremely high attrition rate and also one
where much preservice preparation is, let&amp;#39;s say, limited, we have to
do better. Obviously the biggest issues are things like class size,
pay, and benefits but starting out at a school that&amp;#39;s friendly to new
teachers can be the difference maker.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I have (and haven&#39;t) been up to</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-ive-been-doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 11:42:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/what-ive-been-doing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s been about a year since I taught my last class. I miss working
with the kids and truth be told, I do miss working with other
educators and tech professionals on programs, policy items and related
but I don&amp;#39;t miss any of the bureaucratic nonsense, policies made by
people who don&amp;#39;t know what they&amp;#39;re doing, nor the record keeping, grading or
paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent the first few months in what I&amp;#39;ve been calling my retirement
hibernation but more recently it&amp;#39;s been time to emerge. Time to see
where, if anywhere, I now fit in the CS/Ed/Tech space moving
forward. That&amp;#39;s both in terms of where I&amp;#39;d like to be involved and of
course the flip side, if those places or people want me involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what have I been doing in that regards?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Connecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not me connecting with new people (although I love doing that, just
haven&amp;#39;t had new opportunities) but connecting other people. A big part
of this is connecting younger former students with older, more
experienced ones - frequently for referrals. I like doing this but to
be honest, I can no longer keep track of who&amp;#39;s where  too many
former students at too many companies. Still, this is an aspect of the
StuyCS and how HunterCS families that I&amp;#39;m really proud of building and
I really get nachas when more experienced family members are there for
the younger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I also had a former student who decided to spend this summer mentoring
college kids who couldn&amp;#39;t get an internship - he&amp;#39;s between jobs and
wanted to give something back. Trouble is, he wanted to work with too
many kids than would fit in his apartment. Fortunately, I was
introduced a couple of months ago to someone who just opened a new
co-working/learning space and was looking to support worthwhile
projects. I put them together and it&amp;#39;s been a win win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve been enjoying doing things like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Advising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is interesting, because I generally don&amp;#39;t actually give advice. I
try to repaint the picture of the advisee so as to be sure I
understand it and then I generally talk about the questions I would
ask if I were in that situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In one case, I was put in touch with a team building a workforce
exposure/entry experience for NYC high school students. They had a lot
of workforce program experience but little tech experience. I think I
was able to add value to their efforts given my tech background and
educational experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In another instance, a friend has been working on a new school
proposal. Now, I never actually started a new school but have been
involved in school design a few times and have certainly built out a
number of programs. It was a lot of fun talking to him about his
vision and school&amp;#39;s aspirations and to share with him my perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One other recent conversation was between me and a friend who&amp;#39;s been
building a company to help in both hiring and in leveling up
employees. This is someone who I really enjoy working with. She cold
emailed me around nine years ago when she was starting a direct CS
Education program and we&amp;#39;ve been friends ever since. I really enjoyed
this conversation because it wasn&amp;#39;t the usual &amp;#34;I want to start a
coding program&amp;#34; but was still something that, with my education
background and range from small kids through workforce, I think left
me with something of value to add.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I enjoy this type of &amp;#34;advising&amp;#34; or rather, as I look at it, talking
shop and I do think that my background - having been in multiple
levels of education from early grades through college as well as in
industry and having also build numerous programs lets me add
value. Maybe I should try to set it up as a consulting thing rather
than just being there for friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, then there&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;m not doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ll be less and less involved with the national aspect of the
CSTA. Note I&amp;#39;m talking here about the national CSTA. I&amp;#39;m looking
forward to continue to work with my local NYC and regional CSTA people
whom I both like and respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple of interactions this past year really rubbed me the
wrong way. Last year, they were looking for people to join their new
Imagining CS Pathways effort. I applied for one of the roles. I wasn&amp;#39;t
selected. Now, that&amp;#39;s fine. I mean, I personally felt, after I heard
who was selected, that I had more to offer than many but that could
just be my ego. What bothered me was that I was then sent an email
asking if I was interesting in participating in a capacity that I had
explicitly said I wasn&amp;#39;t. I also wasn&amp;#39;t particularly impressed with
the report once it came out. I felt it was lacking in actual
CS. Although I didn&amp;#39;t think about this at the time, I suspect the
people who built the committee already had an opinion as to what the
end report should look like and built the committee to match. If true,
not cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Later, I decided to throw my hat into the ring to run as an at large
member for the CSTA board. Now, again, I didn&amp;#39;t figure I&amp;#39;d be
elected - I think I&amp;#39;ve pissed off a number of people over the years
but I was put off when I got an email saying that they elected to
place other people on the ballot. Why did this bother me? Because it
says that there are people within the organization who can basically
shape the board by only allowing certain people on the ballot. Again,
not cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, CSTA can of course do what they want. They&amp;#39;re the big players who
get the Google money. I&amp;#39;m just a retired educator but since the
organization appears to be going in directions that I think are wrong,
there&amp;#39;s no reason for me to continue my involvement or show support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s what I won&amp;#39;t be doing. I guess it also appears that I&amp;#39;m
blogging less frequently but that seems to be the norm these
days. I&amp;#39;ll probably continue apace until something clicks and I&amp;#39;ll
do a deep dive somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philadelphia Freedom</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/philly-6-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 19:02:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/philly-6-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Time for another travel post. Figured that by posting here there&amp;#39;s
more permanence and search-ability than a Facebook or other post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, Devorah and I are spending a few days in Philly. We started coming
down here a year or so ago and this is our third trip. It&amp;#39;s a nearby
getaway from NYC and we&amp;#39;ve got friends here that we rarely get to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sports fans notwithstanding I&amp;#39;m surprised that Philly doesn&amp;#39;t get more
love from NYC people looking for relatively nearby travel. It&amp;#39;s under
2 hours away, is a very walkable city, and has the things we love, in
no particular order - food, culture, history, art, architecture, and
neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did a lot of the mainstream history, rah rah America stuff in our
last couple of visits along with such gems as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.barnesfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;Barnes Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.easternstate.org/&#34;&gt;Eastern State Penitentiary&lt;/a&gt; so this time we&amp;#39;ve been looking at
some less mainstream attractions so I thought I&amp;#39;d share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the way in, we stopped at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.americanswedish.org/&#34;&gt;American Swedish Historical Museum&lt;/a&gt; in
South Philly. Great museum in a gorgeous 100 year old building. The
museum covered the early Swedish/New World history (including, for New
Yorkers like me, interesting tie ins with Peter Minuet and Peter
Stuyvesant) but had so much more. They had a room on inventor John
Ericsson and another on Swedish Nightingale, Jenny Lind, brought over
to the USA by P.T. Barnum and played all over including at Castle
Garden (nee Fort/Castle Clinton) in lower Manhattan. Also lots more
including some sketches by painter Anders Zorn and a whole bunch of
artifacts. There was also a special exhibit on Swedish candy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The highlight for Devorah was an exhibit on Swedish weaving:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/swedish1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/swedish1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/swedish1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/swedish2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/swedish2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/swedish2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/swedish3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/swedish3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/swedish3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we started off at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nps.gov/inde/planyourvisit/benjaminfranklinmuseum.htm&#34;&gt;Ben Franklin Museum&lt;/a&gt;. Pretty cool but
nothing unexpected. I recently watched Ken Burn&amp;#39;s documentary on
Franklin so I was up on his life but it&amp;#39;s a nice little museum with
some neat artifacts and it was only $5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was a real gem - the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencehistory.org/&#34;&gt;Science History Institute&lt;/a&gt;. This free
museum has artifacts and the development of science from alchemy
through modern day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A special exhibit on dyes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-dye.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-dye.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-dye.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And education in science:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-kits.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-kits.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-kits.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-books.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-books.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-books.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, Devorah found the knitting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/science-knitting.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/science-knitting.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/science-knitting.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We were a little &amp;#34;museumed out&amp;#34; by the end so will have to come back
but this is a must visit museum!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up, a pit stop. We ended up at &lt;a href=&#34;https://shanecandies.com/&#34;&gt;Shane Confectionary&lt;/a&gt;. America&amp;#39;s
oldest continuously running candy store. They had some old-timey
candies but they&amp;#39;re really a chocolate place, making products from
bean to bar so to speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/shane3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/shane3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/shane3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/shane2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/shane2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/shane2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Had a great conversation with the person
working there, purchased way too much chocolate and headed off to our
next stop - another gem - &lt;a href=&#34;https://museumforartinwood.org/&#34;&gt;The Museum for Art in Wood&lt;/a&gt; - also another
freebie ($5 suggested donation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/wood.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/wood.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/wood.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/wood3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/wood3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/wood3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/wood4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/wood4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/wood4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, lunch time. We went to a hand pulled noodle shop that we had
visited two years ago. Really tasty and super inexpensive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/noodles.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/noodles.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/noodles.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our final stop was the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fabricworkshopandmuseum.org/&#34;&gt;Fabric Workshop Museum&lt;/a&gt;. Lots of interesting
stuff going on behind the scenes but for tourists like us, think of it
as a general art gallery where the medium is fabric. There were a
couple of really neat exhibits and again, free ($5 suggested). Another
winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We then picked up doughnuts for later at the Reading terminal market and
wandered back to our AirBnB. On the way, we saw a number of murals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/mural.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/mural.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/mural.jpg&#34; width=&#34;250px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And also these people holding up a skybridge:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/philly/bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/philly/bridge.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/philly/bridge.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Spent the evening relaxing, having reheated leftovers for dinner from
yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hope you enjoy some of these less known Philly attractions when you
get to town. Tomorrow we&amp;#39;re going back to the Philadelphia Museum of
Art for their special exhibit on Mary Cassatt and will also probabyl
hit the Rodin museum and then we&amp;#39;ll figure out Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Research by HS Students</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/research-in-k12-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 14:02:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/research-in-k12-cs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last week Devorah and I attended the Stuyvesant High School Alumni
Association&amp;#39;s annual fundraising gala. We were there as guests of the
Alumni Association since, as retired teachers, gala tickets are
generally out of our budget range. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had a great time. I spent time with a bunch of former students
spanning the years, some current teachers I hadn&amp;#39;t seen since I left
Stuy, as well as new Stuy alums and current students. I had a great
conversation with one particular young man, a graduating Stuy senior,
who&amp;#39;s working on an interesting app. He asked if he could contact me
to talk about it. I told him, I&amp;#39;d love to so I hope he reaches out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point, I was talking to a current Stuy teaching involved in
their research program - that is, the STEM research program, primarily
focused around the Regeneron Science Talent Search - Westinghouse to
us old timers. She lamented to me that she wished she could get one of
the CS teachers into the fold - to basically run a CS version of the
other research classes that already exist for Biology, Chemistry,
Physics, and Mathematics. Each of those classes target students in
their Junior years, hook them up with a researcher, and shepherd them
through the process of ultimately submitting a project to the big
competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I had to explain that I actually did run a CS &amp;#34;research&amp;#34; course back
in the day but it was actually a bogus cover course since I didn&amp;#39;t
think that high school students, even with Stuyvesant&amp;#39;s multi-year
program had sufficient CS and Math to by and large do good research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The class was created primarily because, at the time, I had set up and
was running Stuy&amp;#39;s network. I got neither pay nor time compensation
for this. I also typically worked with a handful of students. They
learned a lot about Linux and networking and helped keep things
running. They also got nothing for their troubles - no grade, no
pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The deal was that we&amp;#39;d create the class, they&amp;#39;d learn the networking
stuff and we&amp;#39;d all have some time to keep things running. The kids
would also get a nice high grade rewarding their work. They also had
to cobble together a &amp;#34;research&amp;#34; project that they could enter into
Westinghouse/Intel/Siemans/Regeneron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, the class had some students who wanted to do the
research thing and were not so much there for the networking
side. Those kids had to do a more legit research project. Now,
occasionally I had a kid who was able to do an excellent
project. Spike&amp;#39;s Sporknet project which was a design for a scalable,
anonymous network. Really good work and ahead of his time. Brad&amp;#39;s work
on Captcha was also really great. The thing is, though, that most kids
just didn&amp;#39;t have the background to do solid CS research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though Stuy&amp;#39;s program was and is arguably the most rigorous HS CS
program in the country, by second term Junior year, they&amp;#39;re just
finishing up CS1 (APCS-A). They&amp;#39;d be studying data structures during
the second half of 11th grade. Since the research projects were always
due in the early November, senior year courses don&amp;#39;t have much affect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the math side, some might be taking calculus during their junior
year but many will be in precalc. Few will have taken statistics and
none will have taken discrete math or linear algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These kids were and are tremendously talented but they just don&amp;#39;t have
the knowledge base yet. On top of that, on the programming side, they
haven&amp;#39;t yet gotten to the point where they can write large complex
programs reasonably quickly. That doesn&amp;#39;t typically happen until some
time senior year, or the semester after data structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, in the sciences, the kids were always hooked up with a researcher in a
lab. In the best case, they can do legit research. At Stuy, in all
areas, including CS, there are usually a couple of outlier kids who
had exposure early on and come in with a wealth of experience in their
resaerch field. In the worse case though, these kids become glorified
lab assistants. The thing is, though, this can be a really good
experience. They are there for the entire process and learn a lot. In
CS, the equivalent is basically having the kids implement an already
designed algorithm or create part of a software system that isn&amp;#39;t
really showing them the research process. From what I saw, it just
wasn&amp;#39;t as rich of an experience. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After a few years, I dropped the network - too many headaches and soon
after, got rid of the &amp;#34;research&amp;#34; course. I think it was the right
choice. The research course could have continued and been a good
experience for the couple of outlier kids each year who came in super
strong but that wouldn&amp;#39;t be a sensible use of resources with each
class having over 1000 students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, unfortunately, I wasn&amp;#39;t able to help this Stuy research teachers
case for CS research in high school. I did point out that the kids
might be able to leverage their CS and coding skills in their research
in other areas. I had one student who ultimately did Physics research
who made extensive use of his CS skills for data analysis and
visualization. I believe he was a semi-finalist. I&amp;#39;ve also had
former students do Astronomy research in college and grad school using
CS skills they got at Stuy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I guess that&amp;#39;s it. Am I wrong on this? I certainly could be. Maybe
I wasn&amp;#39;t back then but times have changed. Sure, if a school had
unlimited resources for unlimited classes, having a CS research class
would be great even if it only had a handful of students. With budget
and space constraints though, I think a full class of another advanced
elective is more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All this said, I&amp;#39;d love to hear differing opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s teacher appreciation week again</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-appreciation-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 11:34:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-appreciation-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s teacher appreciation week again so I thought I&amp;#39;d show some
appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the past, I&amp;#39;ve specifically &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher/&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about some of the teachers who
were particularly influential on me growing up. I&amp;#39;ve also &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teacher-appreciation-week/&#34;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; about
how I&amp;#39;m not a huge fan of teacher appreciation week as a whole. Today,
I wanted to talk about colleagues who deserve more appreciation from
their students and schools than they might be getting. Now, this isn&amp;#39;t
to say that they&amp;#39;re not getting the love but I wanted to add my two
cents to make sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, my partners in crime from my days at Stuy. People like JonAlf
Dyrland-Weaver, Sam Konstantinovich, and Topher Mykolyk. Not only are
they great teachers but whenever I&amp;#39;ve had a project that benefited
either kids or other teachers, they&amp;#39;ve gone above and beyond. Those
three were instrumental in helping build and run my teacher
certification program at Hunter college. They were way underpaid, way
overworked, and in some (but not) cases, underappreciated by some of
the students. Most of the students in the program were great but the
third cohort, if I&amp;#39;m to be honest, had a few, let&amp;#39;s say, challenging
participants and I&amp;#39;ll always appreciated my big three for working
through and providing the best experience possible for the majority of
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, I also had a number of other great teacher colleagues through the
years and I do appreciate them but I wanted to single out DW, Mr K,
and Topher (why am I blanking on what the kids call him now?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other teachers I wanted to single out today are the teachers who
went through my certification program. We had 20 in the first cohort,
20 more int he second, then 60 in the third. The program continues on
under the expert guidance of my friend and former student Edgar Troudt
but I&amp;#39;m focusing on the three cohorts I worked with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yes, all my advanced cert teachers received scholerships to cover
tuition but they &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; decided to give up a summer and spend all day
every day in July with me and my motley crew to learn more CS and how
to teach it. They then spent the following school year taking courses
as well as recording their classes, remote observing their fellow CS
teachers and in general supporting each other as they all worked to be
the best teachers and the best CS teachers they could become. They
worked hard and learned a lot. The teachers who participated who came
in with less CS content experience spent countless out of class hours
with classmates, TAs and instructors to develop their skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As it turned out, with the State&amp;#39;s SOCE, it turns out that some, maybe
even most of these teachers didn&amp;#39;t and might not need the actual
certification but they all took it upon themselves to work on
improving their content knowledge and their refining their pedagogical
techniques so they could be the best version of themselves for their
students. It&amp;#39;s also worth noting that they all elected to take on my
program which I feel is pretty rigorous. At the time, we were the only
game in town but if they decided to enroll in a certification program
now, they&amp;#39;d have the option of rigorous programs, like mine and a
couple of others or by taking one of the less rigorous programs that
have since been approved by the state which barely cover any legit CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t know if their students really know or appreciate that these
teachers have really gone above and beyond for them and I&amp;#39;m sure will
continue to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, hat&amp;#39;s off to them. A bunch of great teachers super worthy of
appreciation. Not just this week but throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should we use MongoDB in High School</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-hs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 11:14:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/mongodb-hs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Should we use MongoDB in High School? That&amp;#39;s the question. Usually
when I give a post such a title, I already have an opinion - it&amp;#39;ll be
a yes or no and if it&amp;#39;s yes, I&amp;#39;ll have a plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not this time. My gut tells me there&amp;#39;s a place for it but I&amp;#39;m not sure
where. Besides, that&amp;#39;s not what this post is really about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point during SIGCSE 2023, I stopped by the MongoDB booth. Had a
couple of great conversations with the people there. I wasn&amp;#39;t looking
for how I might use it in my classes - I knew I&amp;#39;d be retiring soon but
I did want to convey how much I liked the product and how supportive
they&amp;#39;ve been towards some of my efforts both K12 and while I was at
Hunter, I mean I still have more MongoDB shirts than pretty much any
other type of swag shirt from when they donated so many for some high
school hackathons I&amp;#39;ve run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This year, at SIGCSE, I reconnected with my new MongoDB friends from
2023 and we started asking if there were a place for MongoDB in a
typical High School. Clearly there was at Stuy but I covered MongoDB
there in a senior elective after the kids had already finished a CS0
class as well as a college CS1 and CS2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now MongoDB is much more advanced than when I started using it but
even back then there was a lot to like. It stored documents
essentially in dictionaries which made things much simpler than
SQL. You also formed dictionaries to form queries which might have
been trickier to &amp;#34;get&amp;#39; than SQL with things like &amp;#34;SELECT NAME from
PEOPLE where AGE=30&amp;#34; or something like that but much easier to debug
and automate since one deals with a data structure to do it in MongoDB
as opposed to string manipulation for old school SQL. It was also
helped from the fact that most student projects didn&amp;#39;t benefit from
the relational SQL model. There was also an open source server you
could install and self host.  Nowadays MongoDB is much more capable
for example it&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mongodb.com/resources/basics/databases/data-lake-vs-data-warehouse-vs-database&#34;&gt;data lake&lt;/a&gt; features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t think MongoDB is &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; tool to universally use in High School but
my gut tells me there&amp;#39;s a place for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The cool thing to me is that we&amp;#39;re now exploring this. Me, a
few teachers I&amp;#39;ve gathered, and some new friends at MongoDB. The
interesting thing is how it came about. Many of the K12 company based
initiatives were the result of the company (or college) deciding that
they wanted to do something in the K12 space. This frequently comes
with a certain level of hubris that they can do it better. Not always,
but frequently. The small companies and startups then work to generate
interest and ultimately market share. The big boys are more frequently
anointed since so few K12 CS educators are currently armed to really
evaluate what they&amp;#39;re seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This was different. Nothing coming from the top. What started as a
serindipidous conversation between someone on the education team at
Mongo and me, an old education curmudgeon. We both asked &amp;#34;does it make
sense?&amp;#34; We didn&amp;#39;t know the answer so we&amp;#39;re exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow morning I&amp;#39;ll be going to MongoDB World Local in New York and
hope to meet a couple more people on the MongoDB team. In the next few
weeks, I&amp;#39;ll be talking to some teachers who also hope to explore the
MongoDB in high school question. After that, maybe not until the Fall
if people are away for the summer, we&amp;#39;ll get together and start to get
to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Either we&amp;#39;ll see that MongoDB probably doesn&amp;#39;t make sense in high
school or we&amp;#39;ll figure out where and how. It&amp;#39;ll be a fun process and
if we do figure it out, you can bet it&amp;#39;ll make more sense than any of
the typical initiatives that come from above.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Certification - I should be exempt</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-should-be-exempt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 13:05:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/i-should-be-exempt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Over the past few years, a number of states have acknowledged Computer
Science as an academic area of study and have created pathways for
certification. The actual requirements vary from state to state and
indeed, even within a given state, there&amp;#39;s a lot of variation. Here in
New York, for instance there are some strong programs that will truly
prepare a candidate to teach CS in K12 but too many others that are
just &amp;#34;certificate mills&amp;#34; and the state doesn&amp;#39;t seem to care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The question that I noticed garnering discussion recently wasn&amp;#39;t the
creation of new certification areas but rather, what do we do with the
people currently teaching CS?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Do we grandfather them in? If so, do we do it indefinitely? Do we
force them to go through an entire certification program? How about
making them sit for an exam? How about something else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m writing about this now because on social media I noticed a post
from a teacher who was just informed they&amp;#39;d have to take the Praxis
exam in order to continue teaching CS. Here, and in other forums I&amp;#39;ve
heard some teachers shrug this off since they did similar or had to do
more, and some say that it was ridiculous to make someone already
teaching CS sit for an exam or take additional courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to push back on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just because someone has been teaching CS doesn&amp;#39;t mean they should. In
New York City, due to their CSforAll initiative hundreds of teachers
have been thrust into CS classes over the past few years with minimal
preparation. Many of them have worked super hard and have done a
yeoman&amp;#39;s job but the majority, from what I&amp;#39;ve seen, don&amp;#39;t know CS
beyond the super basics and haven&amp;#39;t really had the opportunity to
learn how to teach it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, there are some who indeed do have a solid CS
background and any additional exams or coursework are just a waste of
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the third hand, a teacher who has already been certified in some
other area and has been teaching CS in a public school shouldn&amp;#39;t have
to pay out of pocket to take additional coursework or exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is that you can&amp;#39;t really assess who knows their stuff and
who doesn&amp;#39;t just because &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;ve been doing it for the past ten years.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m comfortable saying that even though I&amp;#39;m certified in math, I&amp;#39;m a
very strong CS teacher but can I prove it? Test scores don&amp;#39;t
necessarily prove it. I taught for many years at Stuyvesant. Those
kids would do well on standardized tests if a potato taught the
class. In fact, over my career, I&amp;#39;ve seen, in regents classes where a
class taught by a horrible teacher ended up with some of the highest
regents scores. There are reasons for this but it&amp;#39;s not worth the time
to explain here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should we look for student testimonial? Maybe but that could just mean
that the teacher was popular and unless you&amp;#39;re going to find students
who are a bunch of years out, they might not have the perspective
to give a fair evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about observation reports from supervisors? Since supervisors
rarely know CS that won&amp;#39;t work either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a tough nut to crack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, we&amp;#39;re left with some states where they&amp;#39;re requiring sitting CS
teachers take an exam and/or classes which will be an inconvenience or
burden on the few teachers that already really know their stuff and
other states like NY where they&amp;#39;re fine with unqualified teachers for
the next ten years by having teachers merely fill out a form, which I
wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/soce/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Neither solution is ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Probably the best solution would be to have current CS teachers sit
for an exam like the CS Praxis exam and have the state pick up the
fee. I&amp;#39;m not a big fan of standardized exams but as far as they go,
the CS Praxis isn&amp;#39;t horrible and if you pass it, you should have the
CS knowledge necessary to teach most High School CS classes. If you
waive the fee, then it isn&amp;#39;t really a big ask for a qualified CS
teacher. Maybe you also only do this for teachers who&amp;#39;ve been teaching
CS classes for two or more years or something like that. Combine a no cost
exam with the teachers past CS teaching track record and you probably
hit the sweet spot - fair for the teacher and you have a pretty good
idea that your CS teachers know their stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Seems like an easy common sense solution and it wouldn&amp;#39;t cost that
much. Instead we get states requiring way too much of working teachers
or on the flip side, allowing teachers with no credentials to teach
our students. I guess we&amp;#39;ve learned not to expect more from our
governments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2024 - Papers, Experience Reports, and Lightening Talks</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-6-sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 19:36:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-6-sessions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last up we have paper sessions, which include experience reports and
lightening talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Probably won&amp;#39;t write as much on this - I&amp;#39;m a little SIGCSE posted out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One interesting note was a semi-recurring theme of &amp;#34;the hidden
curriculum.&amp;#34; I say semi-recurring because while it appeared in three
sessions I attended - two experience reports and one lightening talk,
each time, the speakers were referring to a different &amp;#34;hidden
curriculum.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first time was a talk from UCSD describing a projects course. It
was similar to many projects based courses - students are shepherded
through a large project, but in this class, students worked
exclusively on large existing open source projects. The hidden
curriculum consisted of all those real world tools and techniques not
covered in a typical CS sequence - testing, code maangement, tech
integration, navigating a code base and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The course sounds great. If given a single choice, I&amp;#39;m not sure if
it&amp;#39;s better for students to work on a large original project or to
learn how to work in an existing one as both skill sets are valuable
and important but do like what they described as going on at UCSD. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second time the hidden curriculum came up was in a lightening
talk from instructors at the Milwaukee School of Engineering. What was
interesting was that they were talking about something altogether
different from what UCSD considered their hidden curriculum. In tnis
case they were talking about things like study skills, stress
management, homework strategies, registration and advisement, time
management, and life after graduation. While I certainly appreciate
everything about the software engineering skills form the UCSD talk,
the skills talked about here are arguably more fundamental and they&amp;#39;re
skills that many students, particularly those from lower income
households have never had the opportunity to develop. This took me
back to our first keynote when the speaker mentioned that he while he
got great support from his family as the first one going to college,
he got very little help. His family supported him and wanted him to
succeed but as nobody else from the family had ever gone to college,
they didn&amp;#39;t have much to offer in terms of concrete help in
navigating this new world. At the school. the instructors taught their
hidden curriculum through extra curricular sessions during common free
times (providing free food to draw in the students). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The third hidden curriculum was a talk titled &amp;#34;From Degree to
Developer&amp;#34; In this case the hidden curriculum as interview prep
both in terms of the soft skills for interviewing and also the
technical interview skills - how to pass those LeetCode problems. The
solution in this case was like the first talk - create a course that
was essentially an algorithms course with interview style
implementations along with the soft skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What struck me here is that we&amp;#39;ve got three different institutions all
resorting to something outside of their school&amp;#39;s major requirements to
address a real student need (the two courses that were created were
free electives). Something&amp;#39;s wrong here and unless it&amp;#39;s addressed
we&amp;#39;ll see the gap between the haves and the have nots continue to
expand since well to do students at elite institutions are best able
to learn these hidden curricula on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I&amp;#39;ve found that if you&amp;#39;re strategic you can add a fair
amount of the software engineering practices to core CS classes
without too much hassle - certainly if you tweak the content a bit -
do we really need every single one of those data structures and do we
have to dive so deep into proof and theory? Maybe we should realize
that our programs are still set up for 100% percent of our grads to go
on to get their PhDs where the reality is that the majority want to
take tech skills to industry. I&amp;#39;m betting programs could easily
accommodate most of the hidden curricula with some sensible
re-evaluation of requirements and everyone would be better for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One other session that I want to mention before I wrap up was one on
&amp;#34;Creative labs in CS1&amp;#34; at Georgia Tech. This was interesting. In this course, they
added a handful of what they considered &amp;#34;fun&amp;#34; projects. The concepts
would not be tested on exams. These projects would not be in Python,
which I guess is the core language for the CS1 class. The first
project might be an HTML/CSS web site. The second, maybe adding some
JS. To be honest, I didn&amp;#39;t get this at first but then the speakers
explained that at Georgia Tech, CS1 is almost entirely made up of
non-majors. I&amp;#39;m still not sold on their plan here but I think I get
what they were trying for. What got me was the fact that this is a
real problem and not just for Georgia Tech. We&amp;#39;re seeing more and more
schools requiring students to essentially pre-declare in CS before
they&amp;#39;re even admitted to the school. Kids without sufficient
opportunities, as a result, are being locked out of the field. I know
we&amp;#39;ve got a booming enrollment problem but we&amp;#39;ve got to do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s it for the sessions. I think I&amp;#39;ll do one more SIGCSE post
as a general wrap up and talk about our Portland adventures. Then
it&amp;#39;ll be back to my usual curmudgeonly rantings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2024 - Panels</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-5-panels/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 14:23:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-5-panels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I generally enjoy both panels and special sessions at SIGCSE over
paper sessions. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, paper sessions can be great but
with those you can always read the paper and all to frequently there&amp;#39;s
not a lot of value added beyond the paper itself. Panels and special
sessions can&amp;#39;t just be read in the proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For one panel session I had to choose between&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enduring Lessons from Computer Science for All for AI Education in Schools&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI in Computing Education from Research to Practice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I opted for the latter. The panel was interesting but not what I
expected it to be based on the title and description. The moderator
provided a list of questions and the audience voted to order them
using an app. The moderator then asked the top ranked questions along
with additional audience questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many of the questions went over what is now well trodden ground - will
kids go into CS if AI will take their jobs? How can kids be motivated
to learn to program since they have AI assistents? How can we detect
the use of AI tools in assignments? What are useful current AI tools?
Not a lot new here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still there were some interesting points that came up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One panelist discussed how through the use of AI early CS classes, CS0
and CS1 can get much further - student can do more advanced work more
quickly. I started to wonder - has anyone actually checked this? I
mean, yes it&amp;#39;s easy to see that they can get through more material but
do they learn it? Have the later courses been adjusted to accomodate?
Has anyone studied the AI enhanced CS0/1 students vs those without it
in CS2?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve seen countless times where students seemingly achieve advanced
results through the use of libraries and other tools along with
extreme coaching. Many code schools as well as some highly lauded
youth programs do this but the students invariable have little
retention and hit a wall or regress soon after the class or camp ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now I&amp;#39;m not saying that you can&amp;#39;t make a better early CS experience
with AI. I&amp;#39;m just saying that one, it&amp;#39;s not as easy as saying &amp;#34;they
can do more&amp;#34; and two, the jury&amp;#39;s still out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another &amp;#34;positive&amp;#34; the panel brought up was that LLMS can help or
guide students at scale - LLM based TAs and tutors. Now, I&amp;#39;m all for
adding resources for students but people can be so hyped for some new
technology they miss the problems. In this case, adding LLM based
tutors to hide a courses shortcomings - something I wrote about
dealing with CS50 &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-replace-teaching/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Another potential danger I see is using LLM
based teachers and tutors to replace human interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another concern that came out of the panel when a panelist claimed
that AI tools will allow for the creation of a &amp;#34;curriculum in a box&amp;#34; -
the panelist framed this as a good thing - a school could offer a
class they otherwise couldn&amp;#39;t but I read it as another sign of the
deterioration of the craft of teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll end my thoughts on this panel though with an LLM strength - that
they can be multilingual. I haven&amp;#39;t seen this exploited yet but this
could certainly be a boon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My second panel was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data Science and Computer Science in K-12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The panel started with an interesting fact. In 2020 no states had
anything in their requirements or standards dealing with data
science. Now in 2024, nineteen do. That&amp;#39;s some pretty fast growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The panelists brought up a number of issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Science and Computer Science frequently overlap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Science provides opportunities to develop CS skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS has DS in their standards but frequently they need to be expanded
on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The question as to if DS (and CS) should be standalone classes or
embedded in other subject areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s doubtful that data science will spin off into its own discipline
in K12. It&amp;#39;s much more likely to be integrated into other subjects but
the placement of data science and computer science is an interesting
one. Currently, the trend in the early grades is integration. In the
later K12 grades you&amp;#39;ve got mainstream players like the College Board
with standalone classes like APCS-A and APCS Principles but also
integration efforts like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bootstrapworld.org/&#34;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; which integrates into classes like
high school algebra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, in general I&amp;#39;d love to see more subject integration but looking
at CS in particular, at least at the high school level, I&amp;#39;ve always
pushed for separate classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why? Well, first off, separate classes means separate teachers and
ultimately departments. Yes, this further silos the system but without
it, schools won&amp;#39;t have long term advocates for compute science and the
subject will be permanently relegated to second class citizen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another problem with integration is that subject teachers are
overloaded as it is. Now, a science teacher or history teacher might
already be doing some data science and can just relable things but CS
is another matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the panel, I thought of another reason. What happens when the
curriculum changes? Bootstrap is integrated into a typical algebra
curriculum. What happens when the curriculum changes. On the one hand,
if the curriculum is just tweaked, things will probably be fine but
what if there are bigger changes. Over the course of my career there
were changes to both the Geometry and Algebra 2 and Trig
curricula. Big enough that if the embedded curriculum is scripted and
the teacher doesn&amp;#39;t really know the CS well, that add on is going out
the window. This will likely be the case with minor changes - moving
or removing a single unit or changing an emphasis but what about
bigger changes - adding calculators in math or the types of changes
we&amp;#39;ve seen in APCS-A over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn&amp;#39;t even counting major changes like when we went from Algebra
to integrated math to a new version of integrated math back to Algebra
all in my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is all to say that integration probably isn&amp;#39;t sustainable if you&amp;#39;re just
providing a drop in and some PD. It can work if the teachers are truly trained to
know both their core subject and the CS or DS but that&amp;#39;s a big ask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So those are my thoughts on the two panels I attended. Good stuff and
good food for thought. Next up paper sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2024 Birds of a Feather Sessions</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-4-bofs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 10:30:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-4-bofs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw three keynotes, I also went to three Birds of a Feather sessions
(BOFS). Three was possible as SIGCSE added a third &amp;#34;flock&amp;#34; this
year. I didn&amp;#39;t take notes since BOFS should be pretty interactive so I
won&amp;#39;t be able to give too much in terms of content summaries bu
hopefully I&amp;#39;ll be able to convey the gist of what went on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two of the BOFS I attended were good, the third was, if I&amp;#39;m to be
honest, pretty awful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the rundown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first session I attended was &amp;#34;Creating University Teacher Training
Programs.&amp;#34; I figured I pretty much had to attend this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall, this was a good session but it did suffer from a couple of
insurmountable problems that I think all the BOF sessions had. First,
there were a lot of participants, second there just wasn&amp;#39;t enough
time. This meant that we just didn&amp;#39;t have that much time to get into
meaningful discussions. We were able to share some basic facts about
our state&amp;#39;s certification processes but we couldn&amp;#39;t get much further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of the BOFS I&amp;#39;ve attended at SIGCSE follow the same basic
format. The session leaders say a few things, the room splits into
groups of varying sizes, the leaders give questions, the groups
discuss. Between questions, there&amp;#39;s usually a share out. This takes a
lot of time. It might be worth it if SIGCSE made one flock of double
length rather than two flocks or if organizers split their sessions
into smaller groups and just let them have at it without the
intermittent reconvening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, this session covered the basics and was worthwhile but I
would have liked to have been able to talk about actual program
designs with the other session attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second BOF I attended was titled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K-12 CS Teacher Education: What are we teaching and to whom? How do we
know we are moving the needle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
with a sub heading that included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it is imperative that the CS education community understand the myriad
ways in which CS teacher education is enacted and begin developing
best practices for the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was hoping that this would be a dive into what and how different
programs were teaching. I couldn&amp;#39;t have been more wrong. The session
was run by two people but only one really facilitated. I won&amp;#39;t go into
details but I will say that the individual who actually ran the
session displayed poor teaching practices in working to direct the
groups in specific ways rather than facilitating an open discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I left midway through and had a much more valuable hallway track
discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My third BOF was the following day. It was titled &amp;#34;Computer Education
and Capitalism.&amp;#34; Like the first BOF I described, this was a good
session but fell short on time. The organizers framed the discussion
but as &amp;#34;computer education and capitalism&amp;#34; can mean many things, they
gave groups freedom to explore as each group wanted to. This meant we
could talk about education for jobs vs pure education, capitalist
influences on curricula, teacher prep, and how teachers have to teach
or pretty much anything else. Overall strong session. I think most
people, including myself left with a new wrinkle in our thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So that&amp;#39;s it for today. Two strong BOFS and one bad one. I think it
might be cool if there were a way for each BOF to summarize the
discussion to share back to attendees. Sometimes it feels like we come
together in a room, have a discussion with new friends and then it&amp;#39;s
all lost in the ether. Still worthwhile but maybe they could be
something more. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2024 - keynotes</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-3-keynotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 10:29:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-3-keynotes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I wrote about the first keynote in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-1/&#34;&gt;day 1 post&lt;/a&gt;. Today I&amp;#39;ll talk
about two more. There were two additional keynotes during luncheons
but I didn&amp;#39;t attend those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First up was Jane Plane titled &amp;#34;Find Your Drop and Add to the River.&amp;#34; Strong
keynote but it spoke to me in a very different way than the first
keynote. The first keynote was maybe the first talk I&amp;#39;ve heard by
someone thought of as an education expert who actually spoke the
measured truth rather than eduspeak propaganda. This keynote resonated
as I&amp;#39;ve recently been thinking a lot about the drops I&amp;#39;ve either
contributed or failed to contribute to the CS Education cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Drop by drop a river is made&amp;#34; was the lead quote. It&amp;#39;s a translation
of an Afghan proverb. Plane&amp;#39;s plea was for us all to find our drops to
contribute and when dealing with CS Educations major issues -
diversity, equity, and inclusion - it&amp;#39;s going to take all of us adding
our drops and while any one action might seem insignificant, they add
up over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The talk started with Plane&amp;#39;s journey. How she had the opportunity to
and then actually built the first Masters in CS program in Africa and
then later did built similar programs in Afghanistan. She also spoke
of the drops she added at Maryland and now in Wisconsin. One might say
that not everyone will have those opportunities but the truth is, most
people, if they did have them, probably wouldn&amp;#39;t have taken them nor
accomplished as much. Regardless, even more mundane sounding drops can
big time contribute to the river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the first keynote, Todd Zakrajsek told of how he almost dropped out
of college but the right words at the right time from one single
professor changed the course of his life. Without those words, none of
his drops would have been added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the micro-teaching session, one instructor mimed an interaction he
had with a student. Before &amp;#34;class&amp;#34; he asked what the student planned
to do after college. She said, she wasn&amp;#39;t sure. The instructor
encouraged her to come to office hours to discuss. The &amp;#34;student&amp;#34; was
at my table and said afterwards that the interaction was real and
ultimately it what led to her becoming a CS educator. That&amp;#39;s a lot
more drops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other day I noticed a comment on LinkedIn by my friend Leigh Ann
DeLyser. Leigh Ann commented about the number of &amp;#34;multipliers&amp;#34; at
SIGCSE. Made me think of the fact that teachers in general are
tremendous multipliers. One word can send a child in one direction or
another and the drops we add can turn into streams or more. As a high
school teacher, I was charged with 150 or so students each
semester. If even a small number, say, become teachers themselves, or
go into tech and as a result of my classes pay more attention to DEI,
well, that&amp;#39;s one drop that&amp;#39;s turned into a steady flow. We might not
all be creating new programs in other countries but every teacher has
an opportunity to be a tremendous influencer. We just don&amp;#39;t get credit
on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other keynote I attended was given by Rachel Rose of ILM. The talk
started as a journey talk - from early interests through college and
ultimately to ILM. One point was when Rose emphasized that
she collaborated more in her CS classes than in her other
classes. This was interesting. It makes sense - particularly in
project based courses but flies in the face of the stereotypes. It&amp;#39;s
also interesting in light of the ongoing tensions in schools between
collaboration, individual assessment, and academic honesty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second part of the talk was a showcase and inside look into the
technologies Rose&amp;#39;s team developed at ILM for use in productions like
&amp;#34;The Mandalorean&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;Solo,&amp;#34; and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was a talk about the Academy Software Foundation. How the
movie industry banded together to form a foundation and how each major
studio contributed open source platforms. Now the industry can use
standards and tools like materialx, opencolorio, and openfx. You can
check out ASFW &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aswf.io/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Looks really cool and having all the major
players rally around the virtues of open source is really cool. My
only issue with them is that their logo has an open comment with no
close comment and that just bothers me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The final theme, which appeared throughout the talk was the industry&amp;#39;s
work to increase diversity. A major point Rose made was that
youngsters have no idea as to what they can do within the movie
industry. Neither do they understand the educational path from school
to Hollywood be it in tech, the arts, or some hybrid of both. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All three keynotes were strong. All conveyed worthwhile messages and
all were delivered in an entertaining way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Good job SIGCSE2024!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still to come - BOFS, Panels, and Paper sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2024 - Microteaching</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-2-micro-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 23:42:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-2-micro-teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We stayed an extra day in Portland to do some site seeing. I&amp;#39;ll write
about the tourist side in my final SIGCSE2024 post. Right now, we&amp;#39;re
back in the hotel resting before dinner so I thought I&amp;#39;d start the
next part of my SIGCSE2024 report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For Day one&amp;#39;s first session, I attended &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/lewiscolleen/&#34;&gt;Colleen Lewis&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; Microteaching
session. I&amp;#39;ve wrote about this session &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2023-microteaching/&#34;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt; and also about
Colleen&amp;#39;s recent appearance on the CSEd podcast where she discussed
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/manipulatives/&#34;&gt;manipulatives.&lt;/a&gt; Much of Colleen&amp;#39;s public facing work involves CS
pedagogy and if you haven&amp;#39;t noticed, I&amp;#39;m a fan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Microteaching has fast become my favorite SIGCSE session. Six teachers
each give a quick, abbreviated mini-lesson and afterwards Colleen
highlights pedagogical techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s not perfect. The mini-lessons are taught out of context, the
audience aren&amp;#39;t the presenters real classes, and it&amp;#39;s only something
like a 10 minute snippet but still, it made for a great session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In one mini-lesson, Colleen pointed out that the presenter gave the
&amp;#34;class&amp;#34; (us) time to process a question before asking for
responses. Questioning technique and timing is an important part of
K12 teacher training and I&amp;#39;m betting it&amp;#39;s not covered nearly enough at
the college level. There&amp;#39;s a huge amount to explore on questioning but
a simple technique like this - waiting say, 10 seconds after asking a
question before entertaining a response can be huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In another lesson, Colleen commented how the teacher provided to
concrete but different examples to set the stage for a class
exercise. I liked that particular lesson, delivered by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/adam-blank-707669245/&#34;&gt;Adam Blank&lt;/a&gt;
because it wasn&amp;#39;t a core lesson in his class but rather a fun side
topic to set the stage for the cybersecurity work yet to come. He
elicited suggestions from the class how they could first crack a safe
(using the typical movie trope of listening with a stethoscope) and
how to crack a keypad lock by looking at the worn out keys on the
keypad. This led to a class &amp;#34;lab&amp;#34; where we had to figure out which
mystery toy was in an egg shell without opening it. All of this was to
teach the class about side channel attacks. It was terrific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This went on for six mini-lessons in all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was a great session but I had one thought that might make it
better. Instead of six mini-lessons, how about only three so that we&amp;#39;d
then have time to discuss the lessons. This could be tricky because it
puts the people presenting on the spot and open to criticism but it
could be &lt;strong&gt;so&lt;/strong&gt; valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example, in one of the mini-lessons, the instructor presented a
binary tree. Each node had a student name on it and also a priority
value.Later the teacher removed the names. Colleen highlighted that
putting the name in to the tree (along with priority values) was a
strong technique as was later removing them. I partially agreed with
this but also felt that removing the names could also have weakened
the lesson. We didn&amp;#39;t have full context so I can&amp;#39;t be sure. In any
event, this could have led to some really rich discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A second example, and one I loved was when one teacher engaged the
&amp;#34;class&amp;#34; prior to the lesson. He asked a student their future plans and
after an exchange invited the student to come to office hours to
discuss. This was a great example of a hidden technique for a number
of reasons. One reason in particular I&amp;#39;ll address when I talk about
the other SIGCSE keynotes but it&amp;#39;s also a technique that can be a
negative. On the plus side it&amp;#39;s a way to engage the class at a more
informal manner, it can be used to build class community and culture,
and also, if it&amp;#39;s a morning class, start to get sleep minds stirring
(not to mention the plus I&amp;#39;ll talk about later). On the other hand, if
you do this consistently with just a couple of students, you risk
building resentment or concern from the students that aren&amp;#39;t part of
the &amp;#34;in crowd.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all, a super session that gave attendees a chance to
see aspects of teaching that are never covered in research papers and
rarely talked about in general. Looking forward to next year&amp;#39;s
edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think I&amp;#39;ll organize the rest of my SIGCSE report into session
types - BOFs, paper sessions, and panels so stay tuned for more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE 2024 - Opening Day</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 22:34:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sigcse-2024-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last time I was in Portland Oregon was March 2020. Came in for SIGCSE - the
big CS Education conference. Got in a couple of days early, played
tourist, and then morning of, everything was canceled. Flew back to
NYC on a near empty jet and Covid became very, very real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
March 2024 and I&amp;#39;m back in Portland and SIGCSE&amp;#39;s giving it another
go. This time I came out with my daughter Batya who&amp;#39;s developed an
interest in CS education and my wife Devorah who&amp;#39;s been playing
tourist while we&amp;#39;ve been conferencing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The conference kicked off with a keynote by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/todd-zakrajsek-4b3654/&#34;&gt;Todd Zakrajsek&lt;/a&gt; of UNC. I
was ready to be disappointed. A researcher, that is, not a teacher
who&amp;#39;s spent decades all day every day in the classroom, who&amp;#39;s
published lots of books about how to teach and he&amp;#39;s going to tell me
how to teach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I couldn&amp;#39;t have been more wrong. Content wise, he was spot on. Maybe
the bet SIGCSE keynote I&amp;#39;ve attended. Delivery? He was great there as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He gave some backstory - first in family to go to college. Almost
flunked out, wanted to be a cop - never thought of becoming an
educator and over the talk also kept hitting a few key points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the overarching themes was that there is no single true
way. Right from the start, he emphasized, for instance that lecturing
wasn&amp;#39;t necessarily bad and that active learning wasn&amp;#39;t always
necessarily the best. Lecturing can be effective but good lecturing
with some good active learning smatterred in can be even more
effective. He later said &amp;#34;I love constructivism &lt;strong&gt;when I have the time&lt;/strong&gt;.&amp;#34;
I loved that. I spent five or six years around a decade ago hearing
from the &amp;#34;experts&amp;#34; that constructivism was the one true way ignoring
the fact that it was neither practical for most public school CS
teachers nor was it optimal due to a variety of constraints. It was
refreshing to hear this expert say what my team and I have been saying
for years. There are lots of ways to teach and what&amp;#39;s best at any
given time depends on a lot of factors and the most effective teachers
figure out what tool to use when and where.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Related to this, Zakrajsek emphasized that failure was a combination
of student and teacher. It&amp;#39;s not solely the student&amp;#39;s fault nor solely
the teacher&amp;#39;s. This is related to another pedagogical thought I&amp;#39;ve
long pitched - the best technique to use at any given time is best
determined by evaluating a combination of student needs and situation,
teacher&amp;#39;s strengths, and contextual circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though this first theme considered both teacher and student, it
came across to me as a teacher issue - ultimately, it was how to
teach. Another theme I felt was much more student centered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The focus was introvert and extrovert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Group work? Another &amp;#34;one true way&amp;#34; to teach that has been foisted upon
teachers on and off for decades. Zakrajsek claimed, and I agreed, that
while some students love and thrive under it, some hate it. Similarly
some like and do much better with lectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He also spoke of the extrovert who would raise their hand before the
question was even finished vs the introvert who took their time and
pondered before even considering responding and that as teachers we
must work to accommodate both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I chuckled when he told a story of when he was a guest speaker in a
class and when a student kept raising his hand before the question was
even finished, he&amp;#39;d call on him and ask him to answer. I chuckled
because what he did was very similar to how I handled a similar
student in my class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to the group work, another theme was that students don&amp;#39;t know how
to do it unless you teach them - the hidden curriculum and that&amp;#39;s
frequently ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This led Zakrajsek to another theme - that when he started he thought
teaching was about content but later he realized it was about learning
to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This resonated with me. Zakrajsek was 100% right but it&amp;#39;s 100% &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; how
teachers are prepared today. Too often teachers are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; given the
toolbox of methods and the deep content knowledge to develop
educational experiences appropriate for their populations. Rather
their given canned curricula, scripts, and instructions - what to
teach and how to teach it. Far too many of today&amp;#39;s teachers are
trained to deliver specific content in a specific way and far too few
are prepared to teach students how to learn how to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Todd Zakrajsek&amp;#39;s keynote was really amazing. Maybe I&amp;#39;m just saying it
because it echoed so many of my thoughts about teaching and teacher
preparation and he was really entertaining but I&amp;#39;ll stand by that
statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was a great way to kick off the conference. There was a lot more to
come on day 1. A great session on teaching, some papers on software
engineering, lightening talks, and then a god BOF and a really bad
one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ll save those for my next couple of posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For now, I&amp;#39;ll just say, if and when Todd Zakrajsek&amp;#39;s keynote is made
available online, watch it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The SAT - should it be required</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sat-required/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 15:15:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/sat-required/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw a few days ago that Yale was reinstating the SAT. They&amp;#39;re
joining Dartmouth and Brown of the Ivies as well as MIT. I have no
idea what percent of applicants, let alone percent those receiving
offers, took the exam anyway for other school applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of my friends thought this was great - a return to standards!!!!
Others felt it was a regressive move and it will hurt diversity and equity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me, I think it&amp;#39;s all about branding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As my friends know, I&amp;#39;m no fan of the college board. They make
standardized tests and do their best to both make money and to influence
education through programs like the SAT/PSAT and the AP
program. Many have noted that a high SAT score is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a reflection of
intelligence but rather of income. This makes sense. Children from
well to do backgrounds will have better educational opportunities,
more support at home, and be better prepared for a standardized
test. It also makes sense that these students will be better prepared
to face college where life is less forgiving than high school. It&amp;#39;s
not fair and it&amp;#39;s not right, but well to do kids are better set up for
college success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I had my druthers, both the SAT and the College Board would just go
away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, let&amp;#39;s dive in to why I believe that the whole SAT required vs SAT
optional isn&amp;#39;t really about building an incoming class, equitable or
otherwise, but rather about image and branding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; institutions, image and branding is huge. The truth is,
you can get a class for class equivalent education from a second or
third tier school as you can from Harvard at a fraction of the
cost. You can&amp;#39;t get the resources that Harvard provides due to its
immense wealth nor can you get the old boys club connections nor the
name that opens doors even if you&amp;#39;re less than competent. I&amp;#39;ve seen
this time and time again in industry where a candidate from an Ivy or
similar will get offers, opportunities and promotions while just not
being that good whereas someone from a no-name school has to actually
be good (yes, I know plenty of Ivy students are actually quite good
but I&amp;#39;ve met plenty of dopes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go SAT optional and you appease your more liberal fans. SAT required?
The elitists and &amp;#34;meritocracy&amp;#34; crowd will cheer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Image and PR win the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Take CS50 for example. It&amp;#39;s the golden CS0 course with all the hype
but if you look more closely it&amp;#39;s a flawed implementation of a flawed
course. Not horrible but nothing special. It wins because it&amp;#39;s from
Harvard&amp;#39;s rep and ballyhoo - a charismatic barker at the helm and a
class filled with students preculled to succeed by Harvard&amp;#39;s admission
process. Nevermind the huge waits for TAs when projects are due or all
that cheating we heard about a couple of years ago. It&amp;#39;s Harvard and
it has hype so it&amp;#39;s good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Same for the SAT. You&amp;#39;ve got a high SAT cut off? You must be elite!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Elite institutions can shape their incoming classes however they
want. A few years ago Harvey Mudd proudly achieved gender parity in
CS. Now, Harvey Mudd could have and probably did make some changes in
what they did once students were in their walls, but let&amp;#39;s look at
shaping the incoming class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I found data for  accepted students for Harvey Mudd online. I didn&amp;#39;t check the
year - it doesn&amp;#39;t matter. Here are the raw numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Applied&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Offered&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;Enrolled&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Men&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;2931&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;271&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;116&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Women&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;1509&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;322&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&#34;align-right&#34;&gt;121&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s  13% acceptance rate and a 40% yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They also boasted a 3.96 GPA and an average SAT score of 1520.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that more women were both offered and accepted in spite of only roughly
half the number applying. I don&amp;#39;t have older stats but I guess 10
years ago the offers skewed more male.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With just a 13% acceptance rate and Harvey Mudd&amp;#39;s reputation it&amp;#39;s easy
to imagine that a HUGE number of qualified applicants were rejected. I&amp;#39;ve never
looked at the numbers for Harvey Mudd applicants from Stuy but
typically, for elite schools, far more qualified applicants are
rejected from Stuy than are accepted. In any year, I might have five
students accepted to say MIT, another 20 or more  that were clearly qualified
and capable of doing great and a handful that probably were right to
be rejected. What&amp;#39;s more, each year there were some rejected and the
teachers all wondered, how did person &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; get accepted when person &lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt; didn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m betting it&amp;#39;s the same in general for the application pools for all
&amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; institutions. All Harvey Mudd had to do was skew their offers
more female noting that the applicants they offer should have an
inclination to go the CS route. They could do the same for minority
applicants. None of this really changes the big picture. They&amp;#39;re just
rearranging the deck chairs on the titanic - grabbing the high
performing CS inclined women who might otherwise go to, let&amp;#39;s say
Stanford or Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s like a friend who once lamented to me that even though the FANG
companies (yes, old acronym - old conversation) made all sorts of
claims about equity and diversity, their equity hiring program though
consisted of out battling the other FANG companies for the handful of
black CS students at &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Harvey Mudd or any of these institutions could probably keep the
handful of &amp;#34;superachievers&amp;#34; - Westinghouse winners, IOI and IMO team
members etc. from their class offers, throw everyone else out take the
next &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; students in and the class would probably be remarkably similar
and perform just as well. They could probably even do this a second
and maybe a third time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They can shape the classes however they want to achieve whatever look
or result they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They can even let in students that require more academic support and
still end up fine. All those division one athletes that didn&amp;#39;t &amp;#34;come
here to play school&amp;#34; are prime examples (of course, there are plenty of
D1 athletes that &lt;strong&gt;did&lt;/strong&gt; come to play school and are terrific students) -
they&amp;#39;re shunted to easier majors and receive &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; amounts of support
that regular students can&amp;#39;t dream of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Malcom Gladwell once wrote that the only fair way to form Harvard&amp;#39;s
incoming class would be for them to take &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the qualified applicants,
put them in a hat, and randomly select the offers. He was right and
given the way colleges run their processes they can do what they want
and come up with whatever they want, SAT or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Okay, so given this, it should be clear that requiring the SAT or not
is really a nothingburger but I&amp;#39;ll go further and say all requiring it
does is that it puts stress on high school students and money into the coffers
of the college board. It doesn&amp;#39;t really give you a &amp;#34;stronger&amp;#34; incoming
class, at least not if your admissions office is actually doing its
job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent my years at Hunter reading applications for my undergraduate
CS honors program. I also spent a few years reading applications for
the Macaulay Honors College - CUNY&amp;#39;s elite branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the first few years, we looked at SAT scores. For me, they were
only useful for one thing - a very coarse math cull. My students were
all coming in as intended CS majors. That meant they would have to
take calc 1, calc 2, discrete, linear and a couple more math
classes. If a student had a very low SAT math score, it was a red
flag. SAT score didn&amp;#39;t really tell me more than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even then, I had to match this against transcript data. If a kid was
struggling with geometry in 11th grade, they&amp;#39;ll probably struggle with
calc as a freshman so maybe not a good fit for my program. In fact,
the transcript information - what class, what grade, and what year was
&lt;strong&gt;far&lt;/strong&gt; more valuable than SAT score in determining if a student was
prepared for my program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now you might argue that high school grades are inconsistent and not
every state has course level standardized testing like the New York
State Regents Exams. I&amp;#39;ll tell you what, it doesn&amp;#39;t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In very short order, I got to know schools and classes. I also got to
know recommendation writers. By year three I knew what a grade in a
given class meant for most schools in my applicant pool and how to
read the recs. Sure, I&amp;#39;d have to merge in students from unknown
schools but after a while you get a feel. The SAT was a nice little
crutch but wholly unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But, you say - you only had a few hundred applications and they were
mostly local. Harvard and MIT have applicants from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yeah, they also have big admission offices with full staffs. I know
that the &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; colleges have specific people who read applications
for sets of schools. Over the years, I&amp;#39;ve met the people who read
Stuyvesant&amp;#39;s applications from a few of these institutions. Like me,
they knew what the courses meant at Stuy and their other schools and
they also knew the recommenders - who were straight shooters, who
dialed it in etc. As they say &amp;#34;you gotta know the territory&amp;#34; and they
did. I won&amp;#39;t name  names or schools but I bet if you honestly asked
these readers that I&amp;#39;ve met if they really needed SAT scores to make a
decision, they&amp;#39;d say no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, there you have it. SAT or no SAT? I&amp;#39;d be happy to get rid of it
but everyone should recognize that it&amp;#39;s really about image and not
about forming an equitable and/or diverse incoming class. Colleges can do that
already it&amp;#39;s just that many don&amp;#39;t really care to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Charleston days 3 and 4 - Plantation visits and more food</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston34/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 15:11:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csed-podcast-teaching-with-masters/&#34;&gt;CS-Ed Podcast&lt;/a&gt; post, yesterday was a
washout. Seriously scary storms. We ended up spending the entire day
in the hotel but was able to get to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.middletonplace.org/&#34;&gt;Middleton Place&lt;/a&gt; for dinner. The
original plan was to do the entire plantation during the afternoon but
that was a no go. Instead we got there a little before our reservation
time which did let us wander the grounds a little before heading in to
the restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/middleton.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/middleton.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/middleton.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We did this based on advise of friends and I highly recommend it. We
weren&amp;#39;t able to explore everything they have to offer but we got the
flavor of the gardens and landscaping and didn&amp;#39;t have to pay any
entrance fee. The meal was also extraordinary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was much better. We headed off to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.magnoliaplantation.com/&#34;&gt;Magnolia Plantation&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s
on most of the &amp;#34;must see&amp;#34; in Charleston lists kown for beautiful
gardens. It was nice and there was some history thrown in,
particularly when taking their included tour of the slave cabins but,
maybe since the flowers aren&amp;#39;t in full bloom yet, I wasn&amp;#39;t
overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/magnolia1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/magnolia2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/magnolia2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The limited parts of Middleton Place that we saw made a stronger
visual impact probably due to the greater amount of terracing and
landscaping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That said, Magnolia boasts a host of gardens incuding a bamboo garden
and a swamp garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Speaking of which, we did end up seeing a plethora of gators. So many
that I started to feel like Mick Dundee (gotta stay with  older
generation references rather than the slightly more contemporary Steve
Irwin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator4.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator4.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/gator1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/gator1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;200px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up was a late lunch at the Mason Jar by Fatboys, Finally got our
fried chicken fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day34/chicken.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/chicken.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day34/chicken.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the big reasons we chose Charleston was for the food. Food,
history, and culture are our big three for vacations. Walk-ability also
comes into play. We ended up at least trying pretty much all the local
food that we wanted to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hush puppies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She crab soup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrimp and grits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheese grits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried chicken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perloo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Biscuits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BBQ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fried green tomatos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrimp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Benne wafers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pimiento cheese&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pickled okra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to get dinner at a seafood place shortly and then home tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall a solid first post-retirement trip.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CS-Ed podcast - teaching college without a PhD</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csed-podcast-teaching-with-masters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 09:20:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/csed-podcast-teaching-with-masters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s our third day in Charleston and we&amp;#39;re stuck in our hotel. Stormy
rains and strong winds and a coastal flood alert telling everyone to
stay home. Our car is in the parking lot with water halfway up the
wheels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had tickets to go to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://iaamuseum.org/&#34;&gt;International African American Museum&lt;/a&gt; this
morning but got an email saying they won&amp;#39;t be open until the afternoon
and that our tickets would automatically be refunded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So while waiting and hoping that the rain subsides and the parking lot
drains I decided to listen to the latest episode of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://csedpodcast.org/ &#34;&gt;CS-Ed podcast&lt;/a&gt;
hosted by Kristin Stephens-Martinez with guest Adam Blank. The title
was &amp;#34;What is in a Teaching Faculty Job Title?&amp;#34; but it was really about
teaching at the college level without a PhD. Adam, the guest, has been
teaching full time at the college level with &amp;#34;only&amp;#34; a Masters. I say
&amp;#34;only&amp;#34; because faculty without a PhD isn&amp;#39;t the norm. I in no way mean to belittle his
degree or situation. I too &amp;#34;only&amp;#34; have a Masters in CS but, to be
honest, as soon as I joined Hunter College&amp;#39;s faculty, I was the
strongest teacher in the department and likely one of the strongest in
the whole faculty. Maybe not the nicest, most popular, or charismatic
but the strongest. Yeah, that maybe sounds a bit arrogant and
egotistical but after my 26 years of self reflection and work to
improve at my craft at the high school leve, I can say I&amp;#39;m one of the
better teachers overall out there and K12 teachers, by and large are
much better teachers than college faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, you should give the podcast a listen, here&amp;#39;s a direct link to
the episode (&lt;a href=&#34;https://csedpodcast.org/blog/s4e3_teaching_faculty_job_title/&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) and here are some of my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; Some of the things said on the podcast were given as the
opinions of the host or the guest and at other times they were stating
things that others have said. I&amp;#39;m doing my best not to mix those
things up but apologize in advance if I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both Kristin and Adam seem to believe that having a PhD doesn&amp;#39;t make
you a better prepared teacher than just having a Masters. I
wholeheartedly agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I agree with the sentiment but Kristin pushed back saying that one
could get a PhD in CS Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I disagree with that push back on a number of fronts. First off,
there&amp;#39;s still limited opportunities to do a PhD in CS Education,
second, education degrees, at least in the circles I&amp;#39;ve been exposed
to are sometimes not treated with the same respect as straight old
hardcore CS degrees and that brings us back to the whole point of the
podcast that a college instructor without a PhD shouldn&amp;#39;t be a second
class citizen. Finally, there&amp;#39;s the whole problem with education
education and education research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both Adam and Kristin felt that you can&amp;#39;t understand the
research on education if you haven&amp;#39;t done any research and this
understanding leads to one being a better teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I guess it can, but much better is actually teaching and reflecting
and acting on those reflections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In general, education research is held in very low regard. It&amp;#39;s
rarely reproduced and hardly ever accounts for the myriad variables
that influence a class. An education researcher looks in from the
outside and says &amp;#34;oh, this seems to work.&amp;#34; A teacher lives it and
either adapts or dies (1/3 of teachers leave the profession within 3 years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To put it another way. I like classic movies. I watch many of
them. I&amp;#39;ve read analyses and taken classes. I&amp;#39;ve criticized
performances and directorial choices. None of this will make me a good
or even bettor actor, director, or cinematographer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even closer to home for me is that I was a competitive fencer. I
watched other people train and bout and even studied film. None of
that improved me. At best, it would inform me as to what to work on
when I took lessons, practiced and competed but only with that
practice and competition did I really improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Want to become a better teacher? Teach, get feedback, reflect, improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Something else that got me thinking along these lines was a comment
Kristin made asking if teachers really needed to be up on the latest
research or if it were enough for them to wait until that research
were distilled into a teaching handbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking on how many times I was given a different &amp;#34;true
way&amp;#34; to teach based on the research.&amp;#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It also got me thinking about the typical teacher career
path. Teachers are most &amp;#34;up&amp;#34; on the research when the graduate from
their teacher education programs. When they&amp;#39;re new. It&amp;#39;s also when
they&amp;#39;re at their worst as teachers. They quickly learn that their best
instructors were the ones that said &amp;#34;this is what the research says,
this is what your supervisor wants to see, and now we&amp;#39;ll talk about
the reality of what you need in the classroom.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The teachers that get better might read the current research but more
likely they work on their craft, self reflect, and work with other,
frequently more experienced teachers. Teaching is very much a craft
and most of the master teachers you&amp;#39;ll find won&amp;#39;t be quoting the
research but developed in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings me back to the subject of the podcast. Our entire higher
ed system has evolved into a hierarchical system focused on
research. Even if you&amp;#39;re &amp;#34;teaching faculty&amp;#34; and don&amp;#39;t have many or any
research obligations, there exists this caste system and there&amp;#39;s
rarely anything in an institutions organizational structure to support
faculty members becoming better teachers. Sure, some faculty members
are great teachers and many work on their craft but it seems that
teacher development is normally something that an instructor is left
to do or not to do on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With this system, there&amp;#39;s absolutely no reason not to have a teaching
career path with the entry point being sufficient CS knowledge. I&amp;#39;d
prefer that plus some background in how to teach it but that&amp;#39;s likely
a bridge too far for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even had I not been an experienced teacher, the biggest difference
between me with my Masters in CS and the PhD&amp;#39;s I worked with is that
they had super deep knowledge in some very narrow area of CS. This
meant that maybe I couldn&amp;#39;t teach a small handful of super specialized
400 level electives but in practice I could teach many of them and as
my education and experience was more of a generalist, I could
generally teach a wider swath of classes at the entry to mid level
than many super specialized researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The PhD is nothing special, or maybe it is special but no more so than
someone who dedicated an equivalent number of years towards being a
great teacher, a great software engineer, or a great a lot of other
things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Hopefully one day higher education will realize this.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Charleston day 2 - Wrought Iron and Religion</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 19:04:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
We started day 2 with a walking tour. We&amp;#39;ve been using &lt;a href=&#34;https://freetoursbyfoot.com/&#34;&gt;Free Tours by
Foot&lt;/a&gt; or similar services. No fee or a small reservation fee up front
and then pay what you want at the end. We generally haven&amp;#39;t been
disappointed and also generally end up tipping voluntarily about the
same amount as what we&amp;#39;d pay for a pay up front tour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We walked around downtown getting more local and US history and
learning about the city. During one stop at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://charlestonstage.com/about-us/dock-street-theatre&#34;&gt;Dock Street Theater&lt;/a&gt; we
learned about Charleston&amp;#39;s preservation and architectural restoration
efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/theater.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/theater.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/theater.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also discussed Charleston&amp;#39;s history of religious tolerance, being
known as the Holy City due to the preponderance of churches and
acceptance of all religions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/church.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/church.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/church.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also got to see a whole lot of wrought iron created by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philip_Simmons&#34;&gt;Philip
Simmons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/iron1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron1.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron1.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/iron2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron2.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/iron3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron3.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/iron3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, Devorah and I visited &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kkbe.org/&#34;&gt;KKBE&lt;/a&gt; - America&amp;#39;s first reform
Jewish congregation. They give an interesting tour. Jews started
appearing in Charleston in the late sixteen, early seventeen
hundreds. They were of Sephardic descent. This was similar to the
first Jews in New Amsterdam who came for religious tolerance (but as a
New Yorker, I have to say that they got to us first :-) ). The first
reformers from Germany came to Charleston in the 1820s and KKBE, the
first Reform Congreation in America was formed in 1841.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/synagogue.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/synagogue.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/synagogue.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is interesting for two reasons. First, this congregation,
according to our docent didn&amp;#39;t specifically follow the lead of the
reform movement in Germany. Second, Isaac Mayer Wise is normally
credited with starting the Reform Judaism movement in America when he
settled in Albany in 1846, some five years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After the tour, we walked around, saw this storefront:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/scribnered.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/scribnered.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/scribnered.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Neither of us knew what the old Kress building was, now housing an H&amp;amp;M
but Devorah and I both thought &amp;#34;Damn, they were Scribnered&amp;#34; (if you
know, you know).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that S.H Kress owned a series of &amp;#34;five and dime&amp;#34; stores
and one was in this building. The store there was the cite of a noted
civil rights protest. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also saw some fountains in public parks including of course, the
Pineapple Fountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/fountain.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/fountain.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/fountain.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/selfie.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/selfie.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/selfie.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended the day passing the historic marker commemorating &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Smalls&#34;&gt;Robert
Smalls&lt;/a&gt;. How is there not a movie about this guy? I won&amp;#39;t tell the
story here but if you don&amp;#39;t know who he was go read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Smalls&#34;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/day2/smalls.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/smalls.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/day2/smalls.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finished off with dinner back at the Glass Onion which was again
superb. If you get down to Charleston, defiantly have a meal or two
there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow was supposed to be plantation day but there are supposed to
be nonstop thunder storms so it looks like we&amp;#39;ll probably go museum
hopping instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting Charleston</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 19:48:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/charleston/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Depending how you looked at things, I started my retirement this past
Fall. Part of the plan was for Devorah and I to travel a bit more -
something we rarely got to do when we were younger. I did have a great
trip with Batya to Holland and Belgium but Devorah and I, other than a
couple of weekend getaways, weren&amp;#39;t able to go anywhere. We planned to
finally have a trip in January but I broke a toe. Then there were a
few other niggling things that prevented getting away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, this week, we made it - our first retirement trip, and
spanning our anniversary no less!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We decided on Charleston South Carolina. Why? Well, why not. We wanted
to hit it in January since it would be somewhat warmer than NYC. We
figured that it wouldn&amp;#39;t be too hot visiting now in early March - it
would be alike an early Spring for us. Besides, at least on paper,
Charleston checks a lot of our travel buttons - history, food, culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first stop after flying in and lunch was &lt;a href=&#34;https://southcarolinaparks.com/charles-towne-landing&#34;&gt;Charles Towne Landing&lt;/a&gt; - Charleston&amp;#39;s
birthplace. Beautiful day, beautiful ground to walk around and our
first taste of Charleston history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/ctlanding.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/ctlanding.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/ctlanding.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there to our hotel. Dinner was at a local place - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ilovetheglassonion.com/&#34;&gt;The Glass
Onion&lt;/a&gt;. Really exceptional. We started with boudin balls then I had the
shrimp and grits and bread pudding for dessert. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/boudin.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/boudin.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/boudin.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/shrimp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/shrimp.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/shrimp.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/bread-pudding.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/bread-pudding.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/bread-pudding.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Devorah had the gumbo dinner. Super highly recommend. We might go back
tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We started today at &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fort_Sumter&#34;&gt;Fort Sumter&lt;/a&gt;. Obviously a lot of American Civil War
history but also earlier stuff and later. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/sumter.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/sumter.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/sumter.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the afternoon we went to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.charlestonmuseum.org/&#34;&gt;Charleson Museum&lt;/a&gt; for lots of local
history. They also have a natural history exhibit with a giant sloth
that I&amp;#39;m pretty sure is bigger than ours in Natural History:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/sloth.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/sloth.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/sloth.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and also a quilting and abstract art exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then on the way to the City Market, we stopped at Peace Pie for a
snack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/peace-pie.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/peace-pie.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/peace-pie.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nice place - custom ice cream / cookie sandwiches. Like Glass Onion,
also highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The City Market was pretty cool - lots of crafts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/seder.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/seder.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/seder.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, before heading home, we checked out their U.S. Customs House. Nice
to contrast it to our Customs House on Bowling Green and it&amp;#39;s
predecessor - Federal Hall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/customs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/customs.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/customs.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Overall a great day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The only two downers were when we passed a store with lots of anti
Biden T-shirts and also when we found out that the Civil War museum on
top of the City Market is run the Daughters of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Daughters_of_the_Confederacy&#34;&gt;United Daughters of
the Confederacy&lt;/a&gt;, fortunately, we decided to pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For dinner, we got our South Carolina Barbecue at Swig and Swine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/img/charleston/bbq.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;/img/charleston/bbq.jpg&#34; title=&#34;/img/charleston/bbq.jpg&#34; width=&#34;300px&#34;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow, a walking tour and Kahal Kadosh Beth Elohim&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers want to teach AI but how will we teach the teachers?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teach-ai-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 09:58:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/teach-ai-teachers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.edweek.org/technology/how-young-is-too-young-to-teach-students-about-ai-survey-reveals-differing-opinions/2024/02&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; earlier as posted on Linkedin by Pat Yongpradit of
code.org. According to the article, nine out of ten educators think
that students should be taught how AI works prior to graduating from
high school. How it works, not just how to use it. This is a good
thing. Sure, opinions vary as to when to teach it - elementary, high
school, or across the board but still, a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It did make me think though about a few things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, in a way this is really just saying &amp;#34;kids should learn computer
science.&amp;#34; This too is a good thing but the bad thing is that a lot of
people talking about learning about AI don&amp;#39;t get this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AI isn&amp;#39;t some new magic mystically appearing. It&amp;#39;s algorithms applied
on data on computers with a user interface. Sounds like CS to me, more
specifically a subset of CS. Sure the data sets are HUGE and the
algorithms, more complex than the bubble sort but at a technical
level, it&amp;#39;s a next step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AI applications can do some really impressive things but then so could
earlier computer solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AI can be filled with bias but computer systems have always been
infused with our societal biases (and we have to do better).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AI can either take away jobs or enhance productivity but the same can
be said with earlier computer innovations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, the call to teach how AI works is a good one but there&amp;#39;s a level
of concern that people don&amp;#39;t see that in a lot of ways this isn&amp;#39;t a
revolution but a next step and as my readers know, I fell we&amp;#39;ve gotten
some serious things wrong in the roll out of teaching CS, without
acknowledging that this comes from CS begs the question, what will we
do differently, or more specifically better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This brings me to my next thought, and this is the bigger one - if
teachers are going to teach all our students how AI works, how are we
going to teach all those teachers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s clear, at least to me, that the professional development, short
form training model favored by so many for CSforAll efforts is far
from ideal. It sets up content providers and politicians to be able to
say &amp;#34;we&amp;#39;ve trained all our teachers in just &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; years&amp;#34; with &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; being
some small number but the truth is, those teachers don&amp;#39;t really know
what they&amp;#39;re teaching and are doing a disservice to their students in
the long run &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-reference&#34;&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;footnote-reference-1&#34; href=&#34;#footnote-1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We also see Computational Thinking efforts where
elementary school teachers relabel things they already do with CT
labels - debugging for error fixing, for example. This can be a
stepping stone to true CT and CS concepts but I&amp;#39;ve seen
implementations where just the labeling is considered good
enough. Worse, at times the teachers delivering these CT enhanced
lessons aren&amp;#39;t using the CT definitions correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
CSforAll in New York City has been going on for nine years. Some
states are further along in bringing CS to their schools and some
started later. Still, after a decade, we have an extremely &lt;strong&gt;long&lt;/strong&gt; way to
go. The number of high school teachers that have a deep knowledge of
CS and how to teach it still pales in comparison to other subject
areas and while elementary school teachers don&amp;#39;t require the same
depth of knowledge, they, in my opinion, as a group are also far
behind where they should be when CS is a subject equal to all the
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m not blaming anyone for this (other than what I already said about
the acceptance and in fact enthusiasm of the short term PD model) but
rather noting that creating a new subject area from whole cloth where
those you intend to teach it never studied the subject themselves is a
multi decade process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#39;s worth thinking about now though, is what are we going to do
with AI? Are we going to double down on short form PD and pay lip
service to this emerging technology? Are we going to make some serious
decisions and decide that some meaty material has to be included in
per service programs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a skeptic. In a country where public school teaching is regularly
derided and even in New York there&amp;#39;s talk about removing the Masters
degree requirements I&amp;#39;m not hopeful. Will we, as a society, decide to
do what&amp;#39;s right for all of our students or will we pay lip service
while those who are well resources continue to get further ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr class=&#34;footnotes-separatator&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnote-definitions&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnote-definition&#34;&gt;
&lt;sup id=&#34;footnote-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#footnote-reference-1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnote-body&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PD as a first step is often necessary and can be a good start
but without meaningful long form preparation as a follow up it&amp;#39;s pure style over substance] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real world projects or made up ones?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/real-world-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 12:48:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/real-world-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
There was a discussion to day on a the Facebook CS Educators group
about project based learning. This was initiated based on the College
Board&amp;#39;s desire to more more project work in some classes including
APCS-A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most, actually I think all of the  educators on the forum agreed that
students creating projects are a good idea but the bone of contention
was over real world projects vs what I&amp;#39;ll call practice projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The thought is that a real world project would be a program that they
might do if they were at a business - a complete web app for instance
or a game, soup to nuts. A made up project might be implementing a
sort or a data structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the discussion some felt that all projects should be real world
arguing that students will be more engaged. Others felt that while real
world projects should be a goal, made up projects were more
appropriate at times - like how you&amp;#39;ll practice etudes on a musical
instrument when developing your chops rather than only ever working on
a piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#39;t agree with the stance that real world projects are more
engaging. Let&amp;#39;s take games - something always paraded out as real
world and engaging. Sure, to kids who like computer gaming. Not so
much for everyone else. Personally, I&amp;#39;m not huge on gaming and neither
were many of my students. That said, enough were so that it made sense
to explore game projects in some classes and to certainly allow them
on appropriate open ended projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s contrast that to made up projects. I&amp;#39;ve done assorted graphics
projects and many had zero real world ramifications but many (not
all) students found them super engaging. I&amp;#39;ve also frequently done a
computer Caesar Cipher decoder. Many students found it very
engaging. It wasn&amp;#39;t real world but it gave a level appropriate
foreshadowing of a lot to come - proto-AI, proto-math, proto-stats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not real world but very engaging and I&amp;#39;d argue, more valuable than
forcing a real world project that was less appropriate for what we
were learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Besides, let&amp;#39;s look at some real, real world projects. Here are some
projects that software engineers I know have worked on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make a round button that launches an already built feature of our
platform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I changed my mind, make it more of a rectangle with rounded
courners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move that UI component down 3 pixels and over 5.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change all the calls in our code base to function f so that it no
longer passes null as the final parameter so that it matches the
new API spec.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a function to check a string to make sure it conforms to our
input specification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list goes on. The truth is more real world programmers work on
small bits of a larger system. They&amp;#39;re working in teams (something I
think our students have to learn about, but not exclusively) on large
systems. Very rarely does someone in the real world go from concept to
completion all by themselves, although I think CS programs would
better serve their students if they did teach this manner of &amp;#34;software
architecting.&amp;#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, really, real world can be fine but it&amp;#39;s not the be all and end
all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some might mean &amp;#34;uses real world data&amp;#34; for real world and this can
certainly work. I frequently assign data based projects - find a data
source, collect it, clean it, and do something with it. If the
students can find data they like that can be super motivating but
again, it&amp;#39;s not a be all and end all. I&amp;#39;ve had students go nuts over
writing a Mandelbrot set explorer - no data there and not real world
but super exciting for some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven&amp;#39;t even really addressed group work or solo but I think this
post is long enough as it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The truth is, authentic assignments come in all shapes and sizes and
can be inspired by all sorts of things. Real world, whatever that
means can be great but are not always appropriate. In K12, most
schools top out with CS0 (APCS-P or similar) or CS1 (APCS-A or
similar) not much in the real world is CS0 level - real world data,
real world ideas, yes but not real, real world. Made up assignments
can be as good or better and freed from the constraints of real world
can be much more appropriate for a students development and just as if
not more motivating.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI in the classroom - it really isn&#39;t that simple</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-in-class-not-simple/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 15:49:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-in-class-not-simple/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today, I saw a linkedin post by Code.org&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/patyongpradit/&#34;&gt;Pat Yongpradit&lt;/a&gt;
summarizing a series of articles on AI in K12 classrooms in Ed Week. I
couldn&amp;#39;t get far into the articles due to paywall restrictions but
Pat&amp;#39;s summary and the ensuing comments and discussion let me to
writing this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing that stuck out in the comments, and this has been a
recurring theme in AI in K12 classroom discussions is that a teacher
who allows students to use AI, teaches AI, etc. will be more effective
than one who doesn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While I&amp;#39;m against an AI ban and if I were still in the classroom I
don&amp;#39;t doubt that I&amp;#39;d be exploring the tools, it&amp;#39;s not that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s look at elementary math education. When I was in grade school in
the 70s, we learned our math facts, long division, and all sorts of
things that were positively uncool when my kids were in school in the
early 2000s. They didn&amp;#39;t learn there math facts and teachers had very
different ways of approaching most of the topics. This struck me as,
well, not good, so I started to talking to my students who had gone
through this &amp;#34;new math&amp;#34; education as well as to parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While this wasn&amp;#39;t an official study, it certainly appeared that by the
time kids who were educated in this newfangled way using all the new
tools and tech were by and large more poorly prepared than students
who either had an old school teacher who bucked the trend and did
things the old way or had parents who supplemented on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How does this relate to AI in the classroom? Well, a teacher only has
so much time with their students and way more to teach than can
realistically be done in the time allotted. So, teacher A focuses on
the new hotness. Goes all in on AI - well, that&amp;#39;s great but
something&amp;#39;s got to give. At the same time, teacher B doesn&amp;#39;t do the AI
but goes old school - pen and paper and really focuses on teaching the
kids to write - that is - communicate effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward a few years and teacher A&amp;#39;s kids are proficient in what
was modern AI a few years ago. Maybe this will be a tremendous boon
but maybe we&amp;#39;ve moved on to the next thing. Teacher B&amp;#39;s kids, on the
other hand are stronger communicators regardless of medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Who&amp;#39;s better off? Maybe A&amp;#39;s kids, Maybe B&amp;#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To make things more complicated, teachers have not been educated in AT
and neither have administrators and just adding more and more to
teachers plates is both unjust and not sustainable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This hypothetical has played out before - with elementary math,
calculators, writing across the curriculum, CS4All and more. Over and
over again. There&amp;#39;s no simple answer. I wasn&amp;#39;t sure that calculators
were the way to go back when they came in. I&amp;#39;m still not and even if
they were the right move, why are kids and schools still forking money
over to TI when there are free and better alternatives on phones and
computers? Writing across the curriculum? Great idea but nobody carved
out anything from my required curricula to make room for it and while
I&amp;#39;d like to think I could do it, I&amp;#39;ve got nothing to show in my work
history or education to say that I was qualified to teach effective
writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yes - let&amp;#39;s work on AI policies - hopefully informed by people who
know both the tech an the teaching but let&amp;#39;s not be so fast to say
that a teacher who embraces AI is good while one who does not is bad.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neighbors, Community and David Bouley</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/neighbors-community-bouley/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 12:57:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/neighbors-community-bouley/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
I read this morning that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ny.eater.com/2024/2/14/24072381/david-bouley-death-bouley-montrachet-brushstroke&#34;&gt;David Bouley&lt;/a&gt; has passed away at
age 70. Bouley was an influential chef in New York city. A huge
influence on the fine dining scene that has developed in the last few
decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I, a retired computer science teacher writing about a decorated
chef? As fate had it, there are some connections between David Bouley
and Stuyvesant High School, specifically the new building, where I
spent most of my career. I started teaching during a teacher shortage,
particularly in math. Actually, had there not been a shortage, I never
would have been given an emergency license and who knows what career
path I would have gone down. This meant that I was younger than most
of the other teachers my departments. Somewhat at Seward and clearly
at Stuy. There was me and Bill in our twenties and most of the rest of
the department were in their upper forties or older. At some point that
switched, and Bill and I were the old farts towards the later stages
of my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was always a foodie but was never exposed to fine dining. This was
where &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich/&#34;&gt;Rich Geller&lt;/a&gt; came in. Rich taught calc and ran the math team. He
was also big into fine dining. Bruce Winokur, another much more
experienced math teacher had similar tastes. I don&amp;#39;t remember when but
we ended up going to Bouley&amp;#39;s restaurant &amp;#34;Bouley&amp;#34; - just a couple of
blocks form Stuy for a meal. It was a revelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turned out that Rich was friends with David Bouley - I think it
just started with him frequenting the restaurant and asking to speak
to the chef and that turned into something of a Stuy math department
connection. We had a biannual tradition - once during the January
regents week and again in June of taking a long lunch at Bouley. Me,
Rich, Bruce, Dawn and a rotating cast of others. And of course going
with Rich meant we always got a few bonus deserts or maybe an extra
course. It was a highlight of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Stuy/Bouley connection went further. Rich, as I mentioned ran
Stuy&amp;#39;s math team. In Spring &amp;#39;95 he arranged a special luncheon -
Stuy&amp;#39;s math team at Bouley. If I recall, the entire team was too large
so it was only the seniors. Unfortunately I couldn&amp;#39;t crash the party
but now, many years later, I&amp;#39;m friends with a number of those team
members and it was quite a memorable experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to post 9/11. We had been displaced due to the attacks
and had spent a month as guests at Brooklyn Tech. About a month
afterwards, certainly before Halloween, we were back at Stuy. It was
the evening of parent teacher conferences. Usually that evening, the
parents association hosts a dinner for the teachers. It&amp;#39;s cafeteria
style and teachers come and go at various times as long as they make
it to their room by the start of conferences. Usually it&amp;#39;s mostly pot
luck from the parents. Usually pretty tasty and certainly
appreciated. This time, as I went down the line, I said to myself
&amp;#34;Hey, I recognize that beef dish&amp;#34; Yep, that meal was catered by
David Bouley and we got many of his on the menu dishes - at least
those that lent themselves to prior preparation and transport to the
school. I don&amp;#39;t know if this was part of his general recovery work (he
did a lot to prepare food for the rescue/recovery workers), if this
was a special arrangement made by Rich or something else but it was
exceptional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The years continued as did the regents week lunches. Unfortunately, we
lost Rich to Cancer in the fall of 2011 (tribute post &lt;a href=&#34;https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Shortly before his passing,
David Bouley hosted a reception at Bouley for Rich, his wife Barbara,
his friends, and former students. A touching tribute for a master
teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why am I spending all this time about my friend Rich and David Bouley?
Well, it&amp;#39;s about community. Stuy isn&amp;#39;t a neighborhood school. In a
neighborhood or community school, teachers and students see each other
in passing. Not so at Stuy. Only a handful of teachers live in
Manhattan or even the five boroughs. The kids? Many have commutes well
over an hour each way. Yet still, here we had this little foodie math
community at Stuy. Mostly teachers, but students were touched as
well. While we lost Rich over a decade ago, reading about David
Bouley&amp;#39;s death really brought me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve had many fine dining experiences since Rich introduced me to
Bouley&amp;#39;s restaurants. I&amp;#39;ve had great food at Jean George, Daniel, and
Park Avenue Cafe and many others but my meals at Bouley have been
special - the best overall dining experiences. I also remember some
particularly special meals - Rich&amp;#39;s reception. The surprise lunch
for a special graduating senior, when Devorah and I took Jim and Helen
there to thank them for writing the kids college recs and a handful of
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that in a lot of cultures there&amp;#39;s a strong tie between food
and community and in this weird little circle community was created
between some CS people, Math people, a specialized high school, and a
great chef.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Emacs 82 - Conda and Direnv</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-82-conda-direnv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 11:31:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/using-emacs-82-conda-direnv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I want to do now that I have some time is get my
head around all the modern AI stuff. I&amp;#39;m starting with a review or
things I&amp;#39;ve already done  by going through Andrew Ng&amp;#39;s Coursera ML
class. I&amp;#39;ll probably continue with his courses but I&amp;#39;m certainly open
to any suggestions (specifically for a CS guy who&amp;#39;s not so strong on
the math side).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This means diving back into Python even though Clojure is usually my
weapon of choice. I thought I&amp;#39;d see how the platform has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First up &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.anaconda.com/&#34;&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt; which is a platform and package manager for
Python. I opted for &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.anaconda.com/free/miniconda/index.html&#34;&gt;Miniconda&lt;/a&gt; which just gives the basics and I can
always add anything missing later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
See the previous two links to install Anaconda or Miniconda. The video
goes over basic use. It&amp;#39;s a lot like virtualenv. You can set up an
Python environment with specific packages and then activate or
deactivate whichever environment you wish to work under.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the Emacs side, I installed the package conda as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34; data-lang=&#34;emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      (use-package conda :straight &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        :config
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (conda-env-initialize-interactive-shells)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (conda-env-initialize-eshell))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that was pretty much it. To activate an particular environment we
just use &lt;code&gt;conda-env-actiate&lt;/code&gt;. Again, this is covered in the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up is &lt;a href=&#34;https://direnv.net/&#34;&gt;direnv&lt;/a&gt;. This lets you customize your environment per
directory. You can do things like set specific environment variables
or even, in our case, activate a conda environment just by going into
a project directory. Basic installation instructions can be found on
the home page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To set up direnv to work with Anaconda/Miniconda though took a bit of
work. Between a few web sites and videos, I found that this worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, I had to create a file named &lt;code&gt;.direnvrc&lt;/code&gt; in my home directory
with these contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34; data-lang=&#34;emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  layout_conda() {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; Ref Url: https://github.com/direnv/direnv/wiki/Python
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; local ANACONDA_HOME=&lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;${HOME}/anaconda3&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    # PATH_add $ANACONDA_HOME/bin1
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    if [ -n &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;$1&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34; ]; then
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    # Explicit environment name from layout command.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    local env_name=&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;$1&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    source activate ${env_name}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    elif (grep -q name: environment.yml); then
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    # Detect environment name from `environment.yml` file in `.envrc` directory
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    source activate `grep name: environment.yml | sed -e s/name: // | cut -d
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;    &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34; -f 2 | cut -d &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; -f &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    else
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    (&amp;gt;&amp;amp;2 echo No environment specified)&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    exit &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    fi&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You might have to play with it if you&amp;#39;re not using the miniconda
installation defaults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, I had to edit my .zshrc:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-sh&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    export iam&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;whoami&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    export CONDA_HOME&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;/home/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;iam&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/miniconda3&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;PATH&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;:&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; !&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; *&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;CONDA_HOME&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/bin:&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;* &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; export PATH&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;CONDA_HOME&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/bin:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;PATH&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; my export init &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; conda initialize &amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# !! Contents within this block are managed by &amp;#39;conda init&amp;#39; !!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    __conda_setup&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;/home/zamansky/miniconda3/bin/conda&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;shell.zsh&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;hook&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; 2&amp;gt; /dev/null&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; $? -eq &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        eval &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;$__conda_setup&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; -f &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;/home/zamansky/miniconda3/etc/profile.d/conda.sh&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;            . &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;/home/zamansky/miniconda3/etc/profile.d/conda.sh&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;            export PATH&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;/home/zamansky/miniconda3/bin:&lt;/span&gt;$PATH&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    unset __conda_setup
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; conda initialize &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    export LANG&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;en_US.UTF-8
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    eval &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;direnv hook zsh&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of that was added when I installed direnv and followed those
directions. I think for the direnv Anaconda support I added the first
two lines and the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, in your project&amp;#39;s root directory create a file named &lt;code&gt;.envrc&lt;/code&gt;
which contains the line &lt;code&gt;layout conda name&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;strong&gt;name&lt;/strong&gt; is replaced with
the name of the conda environment you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first time you go into the directory it will tell you that you
haven&amp;#39;t allowed direnv to work there yet and you have to enter &lt;code&gt;direnv
allow&lt;/code&gt;. After you do that, every time you enter that directory it will
activate your conda environment, leave it, it will deactivate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In Emacs, I found two packages that worked pretty much the same. One
named &lt;code&gt;direnv&lt;/code&gt; and the other &lt;code&gt;envrc&lt;/code&gt;. I opted for envrc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You simply add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34; data-lang=&#34;emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (use-package envrc :straight &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    :config (envrc-global-mode))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
to your config and when you open a file in that directory, it will
use direnv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Important note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#39;s pretty much it. This all worked on my desktop but it&amp;#39;s giving
me problems on my laptop. It appears that conda mode isn&amp;#39;t working. It
allows me to select the environment but it doesn&amp;#39;t actually activate
it. I think it&amp;#39;s a path issue even though I think both my desktop and
laptop are the same. I&amp;#39;ll update this once I figure out what&amp;#39;s up on
the laptop side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all, I&amp;#39;m pretty happy with this. I love that I can
automatically start an environment just by accessing a file in the
directory. Too many times, I forget and mess things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The video steps through everything and demos both packages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/UrJoBaJv5kA?si=_W-OU3RG7o3K5LQ4&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting an AI panel at Stuy</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-panel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 11:15:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/ai-panel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Went back to school yesterday. Specifically, I was back at Stuy
running an AI panel discussion for the Stuy HS Alumni Association. I
figured it&amp;#39;s time for me to get back in the CS / CS Ed game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Plans started a few months ago when a member of my Stuy CS family
who&amp;#39;s also in the SHSAA board asked about doing something. I was game
but a little apprehensive, mostly because there have been, let&amp;#39;s say,
issues with the way the SHSAA had operated in the past. Still, this
was a new board with a new staff so I figured, worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Turns out the new Alumni Association ED is a former student of mine so
that rocketed the trust level of the association way up and we were
off to the races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Setting up any panel or tech event can be tricky. If you&amp;#39;re doing
something for your own classes it&amp;#39;s much easier - you&amp;#39;ve got a good
idea as to the classes experience as well as interest in whatever
event you&amp;#39;re planning. A panel like this, not so much. I had no idea
on the audience size but since it would be mostly Stuy grads along
with a few Stuy students and a low cost or free event it meant that
the room would be filled with nimble minds. The challenge was that
those nimble minds would be all over the place with regards to tech
experience. I was guessing we&amp;#39;d have adult tech pros and hard core CS
people, students who were into CS just finding their way, adults
wanting to learn more but who had no background in either CS or AI,
and probably a few alumna who just wanted to show up for an alumni
event. Turns out I think I got the audience range right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How to make a panel for that? You want to be able to do something of a
deep technical dive but you don&amp;#39;t want to lose the non-techies. You
also want to spend time on all sorts of societal issues - talking AI
is a lot more than just tensor flow, neural nets, transformers, and
LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I reached out the my StuyCS family, my alumni network for four
specific individuals. Oh, if you&amp;#39;re an AI person and part of the
family and wondering why I didn&amp;#39;t ask you - remember - this was a live
NY event so all you Pittsburgh, Seattle, and California AI folks,
sorry - geography made that decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alphabetically, first up was Ben - he was one of my technical
heavyweights. I was confident he could handle any technical curveballs
from the audience. He also has worked at both large companies and has
built startups so he could also give some management and
entrepreneurial context. Next, Doug - strong tech background but a lot of
experience as a technical manager. Been at a number of major and minor
companies from small to large. I figured he would anchor the
business/manager side.  Eugene was third - another technical anchor to
balance Ben but Eugene has more formal academic training and also
spent his entire career in a single major tech company. Finally,
Jamil who also brought startup and small/mid company experience but
has always been big on civic tech and equity related issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, all four overlapped. I joked that Jamil was the conscience
of the panel but truthfully those societal issues were important to
all of us. Likewise, all have had some managerial experience etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From the limited feedback I got so far, I think the mix worked. We
started &amp;#34;defining&amp;#34; AI, modern AI, LLMs (in lay terms) etc. and then
shifted to issues like the use of other peoples data in training, bias
in AI, and of course, recommendations for the youngsters just getting
started. The audience Q and A got more deeply into these issues along
with future jobs issues and if it&amp;#39;s even worth learning to code
anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I won&amp;#39;t recap all the specifics but a highlight to me was how the
panel painted the picture to show that while AI was new and shiny and
is opening new doors with both opportunities and challenges, at the
core, so many of the important issues are societal based, not
technical. Ben mentioning that in a startup the big cost drivers are still
things like personnel and that we&amp;#39;re still very much in the same
startup/funding/scaling model just with new tech and Jamil and others
emphasizing that it&amp;#39;s not that there are these new potential dangers
with bias, for instance with AI but rather that the bias is already
baked into our system and AI is the next frontier - a wake up call
that we can&amp;#39;t just sprinkle some equity sugar on AI but rather have to
deal with the hard societal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All in all, I think it was a terrific event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end I had a chance to informally spend time with both panelists
and audience and it was great to see a number of old friends. Between
the panelists and audience, I had students from the class of &amp;#39;95 up to
some of my most recent graduates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was a fun first event to come out of my retirement hibernation. Not
sure whats next but this one was both educational and fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which low level language to teach?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/which-low-level/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 07:09:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/which-low-level/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
A teacher in one of the CSEd forums I&amp;#39;m part of asked for thoughts on
what low level language to teach. She also asked about scripting but
I&amp;#39;m not going address that here. The question came, aparently due to
state guidelines which were somewhat vague. I couldn&amp;#39;t find the
specific guidelines but I did find old guidelines that indicated that
the course in question was intended to be post APCS-A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back at Stuy, I designed a systems programming course that was post
APCS-AB. I first used assembly language and then pivoted to C. That&amp;#39;s
where it stayed until I left and I&amp;#39;m guessing it&amp;#39;s still there. If I
were to design the course now, I&amp;#39;m not sure if I&amp;#39;d make the same
choice. If I were designing a unit in a post APCS-A class that had
some low-level work, I&amp;#39;m also not sure what I&amp;#39;d do but I found the
question interesting so I thought I&amp;#39;d noodle about it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first question I&amp;#39;d ask would be &amp;#34;should the language be low level
or is it any language suited for low level, that is, systems type
work?&amp;#34; If it&amp;#39;s the former, choices are pretty limited. If it&amp;#39;s the
latter, then most popular mainstream languages would work but
scripting languages like Python and JVM based languages like Java
probably miss the mark, at least philosophically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let&amp;#39;s explore some of the contenders:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Assembly
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is what I think of when I hear &amp;#34;low level language.&amp;#34; In some ways
assembly is simple. Each instruction does a specific thing. On the
other hand, since you&amp;#39;re giving the CPU explicit instructions to run,
as opposed to higher level &amp;#34;human&amp;#34; constructs, you need a lot of code
to do &amp;#34;simple&amp;#34; things. Assembly certainly gives a platform to explore
a machine at a low level but if we&amp;#39;re talking only a short unit, it
could be hard to get student buy in. Still, some students might love it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
C
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
C has long been my go to for low level. I like to think about it as
assembly with better constructs like loops, arrays, structs, and
similar. A nice thing is that it&amp;#39;s syntactically similar to Java which
would have been used in APCS-A. A not so nice thing is that it&amp;#39;s less
forgiving and more error prone. This &amp;#34;feature&amp;#34; does let you explore
concepts like memory management and how the computer arranges things
internally but it can also be incredibly frustrating for students and
programmers alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One really nice feature of using C is that it&amp;#39;s a small, simple
language. K&amp;amp;R - &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; book on C is only around 100 pages and the
complete reference manual is a short section in back. It also cleaning
compiles to assembly. A really nice unit is to take some C code and
use &lt;strong&gt;gdb&lt;/strong&gt; - the Gnu Debugger - a free debugging tool that can even be
run online to look at the assembly code generated and step through
it. This gives some of the benefits of studying assembly, a little bit
on how memory and the machine works, a touch of how C is translated
when compiled and is very accessible to students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
C++
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
C++ is newer and much larger than C. It used to be a C extension but
for a long time it&amp;#39;s been a language in its own right. An advantage of
using C++ is that it&amp;#39;s the core language used in many colleges (with
Java being the other main one) and while it&amp;#39;s a little more cumbersome
to use than C, it&amp;#39;s not much of a step up in complexity until you dive
in to the more advanced concepts. You can also do the &amp;#39;explore
assembly using gdb&amp;#39; stuff I described above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Given current markets, I&amp;#39;d be tempted to go C++ as opposed to C if I
were designing this unit today but for anyone doing so, I&amp;#39;d encourage
you, if you do this, to actually teach C++ sensibilities and not
merely C with C++ constructs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Go
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go&amp;#39;s an interesting one. If I remember correctly, it was designed as a
systems programming language to replace C but at the end of the day it
attracted more Python programmers than C programmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;ve only dabbled with it but there&amp;#39;s a lot to like. It&amp;#39;s a small,
simple, clean language. A friend described it as &amp;#34;a minimalist
language with libraries designed by really smart people with good
taste.&amp;#34; I think that&amp;#39;s fair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s a compiled language with a blazingly fast compiler and hosts some
nice teaching/learning aids. For instance, it comes with gofmt, a
program that indents go code consistently and design features like
having only one loop construct simplifies things. It also has a
terrific concurrency model but that might not be relevant for a past
APCS-A low level unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It also appears that you can gdb so I&amp;#39;m guessing it has the same
ability to be used to explore assembly as C and C++.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even though I&amp;#39;m a C guy from way back and taught C++ for the past 7
years at Hunter College, I&amp;#39;d be really tempted to look at Go if I were
exploring low level programming or system programming with a High
School post APCS-A class today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Rust
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rust is another interesting choice. It seems to be the up and coming
darling systems language of the day. That&amp;#39;s not to say it&amp;#39;s a fad -
there seems to be some solid substance underneath. Like with Go, I&amp;#39;ve
only dabbled and to an even lesser extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My big concern with it in a high school course, particularly for just
a unit in a high school course is there seems to be a fair amount of
overhead and cognitive load for a beginner.  This overhead gives you
some great protections when programming but it just seems to much
given the high school students lack of experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Others (Ada, Swift, Nim)
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are other choices as well. I worked with Ada a bit back in the
day and it would suit the bill. After all it was designed for embedded
systems but it&amp;#39;s less mainstream and is less streamlined than C, C++
or Go. Also, to be honest, I&amp;#39;m so out of date with Ada that I can&amp;#39;t
really say what it looks like today. Swift and Nim also came up as I
poked around for current systems programming languages this morning
but know neither and Swift being apple only would be a concern for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Conclusions
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, where would I fall if I had to design this student experience? If
I were pressed for time, I&amp;#39;d probably opt for C++ with C being my
second choice. If I had time to plan, I&amp;#39;d look at Go and Rust but my
gut tells me I&amp;#39;d settle on Go for its minimalism and clean design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it was an interesting question to ponder on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York - where actual teacher preparation in optional.</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/knowledge-optional/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 14:03:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/knowledge-optional/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read Arthur Goldstein&amp;#39;s latest &lt;a href=&#34;https://arthurgoldstein.substack.com/p/anybody-can-teach-newcomers-says&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Arthur, is a
relatively recently retired NYC public school teacher, a UFT
(United Federation of Teachers) chapter leader, and a frequent critic
of Michael Mulgrew, the current and long term UFT president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m a union guy through and through but I also, like Arthur, believe
that UFT&amp;#39;s leadership is neither pro-teacher nor pro-student but
rather pro-themselves. It&amp;#39;s a rather sad state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today, Arther shared Mulgrew&amp;#39;s latest &amp;#34;accomplishment.&amp;#34; He, along with
the city and state have relaxed the requirements for bilingual and ENL
(English as a new language) certifications. This is in response to the
recent massive influx of newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The deal has two parts. The first makes all the sense in the world. If
a teacher holds the credentials for multiple certifications - one for
bilingual and one not, they will be able to activate the bilingual
cert with no penalty - that is they won&amp;#39;t lose salary, tenure,
seniority or anything else. This should always have been the case and
it should in fact he true, or at least partially true for any
certification area. Maybe not the tenure thing but even in that case,
there should be some modified rule to encourage teachers to switch to
their most needed certification and not be penalized for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second part is the problematic one. They&amp;#39;re easing the
requirements for the bilingual certification. Now, instead of
completing the coursework and taking an standardized assessment, you
only have to do one or the other. That is, take a standardized test, a
single instance platform on which success certainly doesn&amp;#39;t indicate a
teacher is qualified or take a handful  of courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Arthur was lamenting over the exam, but given the number of education
programs in NY where you just show up and earn an &amp;#34;A&amp;#34; or even for some
you barely have to show up, this is basically just a rubber stamp for
bilingual teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s the language from the UFT&amp;#39;s release on the program:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certified teachers and pupil personnel services professionals (i.e.,
social workers, school counselors and psychologists) can now complete
either the examination requirement or the enrollment and education
requirements, instead of both. That means candidates can pass the
Bilingual Education Assessment and/or the Content Specialty Test in
ESOL, if available, in lieu of completing coursework and matriculating
in a registered program leading to a bilingual education extension
and/or an ENL certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This struck me as awfully similar to the CS SOCE (Statement of
Continued Eligibility). In New York State, even though we now have
computer science certification, they created the SOCE which basically
said that as long as you taught a single CS class in the last couple
of years, if you fill out a form, you&amp;#39;ll be essentially certified to
teach any CS in your school for the next 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both of these initiatives attempt to address the lack of qualified
teachers. Bilingual for the influx of new non native English speakers
and CS for the new field of study that the city and state have been
pushing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both of these initiatives will, and in the Case of CS have resulted in
students being served by unqualified teachers both now and for the
next decade and such actions should be criminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
True, some teachers thrown into a CS classroom know their stuff and
some are working diligently to learn but many aren&amp;#39;t there and to many
are making no serious move to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In each of my first to cohorts for Hunter&amp;#39;s advanced certificate
program, I had well over 100 applicants. These were supposed to be the
most prepared of the city&amp;#39;s CS teachers - all culled through the
CS4All program and most had completed multiple years of New York&amp;#39;s CS
training - much of which was provided by organizations like Code.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My CS prerequisites were pretty simple - a code sample in a text based
language that showed some basics. A program with a function that
returned the smallest value in an array or list of numbers would have
covered all the requirements and then some. That&amp;#39;s also a typical
early assignment in a CS0 class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Each year, only a very small number of applicants - something like
under 10, maybe under 15, could complete this, another handful were able
to, with the help of self study resources like the Runestone academy&amp;#39;s
Python or Java texts got up to speed. Each of the first two cohorts
had a little over 20 students including a handful of masters
candidates. All of the masters candidates came in with more than the
required CS background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, for those applicants who learned what they needed and were
accepted, my hat was off to them, they worked hard and did what they
had to do. They were great members of the cohort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, of the hundreds who never followed up, many had no
idea what I meant by &amp;#34;in a text based language like Python, Java, or
Javascript,&amp;#34; or similar parts of the application - and many of them
had been teaching CS for multiple years and attending DOE training for
multiple years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, New York State comes along and says that they can all teach CS
for 10 more years, no questions asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The kids will suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How can the state get away with this? They don&amp;#39;t care. Neither do the
teacher&amp;#39;s Unions (and again, I&amp;#39;m a big Union guy) - their current
teachers can do whatever they want and all is good. The students don&amp;#39;t
know how they&amp;#39;re being harmed and overall, parents are none the
wiser. I&amp;#39;ve mentioned that a number of my Hunter undergrads came in
having scored a 3, 4, or frequently 5 on APCS-Principals and while
some had a good background, way more than should have would have been
better off not taking anything. All these kids were super bright and
motivated. It wasn&amp;#39;t there fault they were sold a bill of goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to the bilingual issue - again, the DOE, NYSED and UFT can get
away with it because on the surface, it looks good - we can teach our
newcomers but they&amp;#39;re the ones who will suffer. And of course, they&amp;#39;re
a population with no voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should be criminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s my rant for the day. I promise, more CS teaching content
and positive posts to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Elisp 17 - a thesaurus mode</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/learning-elisp-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 08:45:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/learning-elisp-17/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
When we last left our heroes we had made the API call to
dictionaryapi.com, gotten the response and coverted the json string
into elisp data. Specifically an array that contained a hash table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today&amp;#39;s video will take us the rest of the way to our thesaurus mode -
run the function and we&amp;#39;ll get a list of synonyms for the word we&amp;#39;re
currently at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, we had to pull out the synonyms from the response. To do that
we used basic elisp data manipulation. We used &lt;strong&gt;(aref json-resp 0)&lt;/strong&gt; to
pull out the hash table, which was the 0&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;  element of the array
response, then wrap that in &lt;strong&gt;(gethash &amp;#34;meta&amp;#34;)&lt;/strong&gt; to pull out the
&amp;#34;meta&amp;#34; hash entry. That&amp;#39;s a hash table in its own right so we then
pull out the &amp;#34;syns&amp;#34; element with another &lt;strong&gt;gethash&lt;/strong&gt; and then finally,
since that&amp;#39;s an array with an array in it, another &lt;strong&gt;aref&lt;/strong&gt;. The
complete code is up at gitlab but it&amp;#39;s essentially:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34; data-lang=&#34;emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;aref&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;syns&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;meta&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;aref&lt;/span&gt; json-resp &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;))) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This gives us an array of synonym strings but we want it to be a list
so we used &lt;strong&gt;mapcar&lt;/strong&gt; to convert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34; data-lang=&#34;emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;mapcar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;#&amp;#39;identity&lt;/span&gt; word-list)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#39;s probably a better way to do this but that&amp;#39;s what came to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From there, the actual function to replace the word under the cursor
with its synonym is pretty straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;src src-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34; data-lang=&#34;emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defun word-to-syn (n)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (interactive &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;p&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (let* ( (word (current-word))
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;          (word-list (get-synonyms word))
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;          (new-word (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;completing-read&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Replacement:&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; word-list)))
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    (backward-word)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    (kill-word &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    (&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; new-word)))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;strong&gt;current-word&lt;/strong&gt; function returns the word at or before the cursor
location. We then use the &lt;strong&gt;get-synonyms&lt;/strong&gt; function that we just
completed and then use &lt;strong&gt;completing-read&lt;/strong&gt; which lets us select a word
from the synonym list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Once we have the replacement word, it&amp;#39;s just buffer manipulations to
delete the old word and insert the new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The rest of the video shows turning this into a mode and binding the
function to a key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, that&amp;#39;s it for the elisp series for now. I&amp;#39;ll do more if I can
think of interesting and fun things to do but no promises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can get all the code at the repo linked below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
Code:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The code for the series is still up here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/zamansky/learning-elisp-code&#34;&gt;https://gitlab.com/zamansky/learning-elisp-code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
The videos:
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZBN4Kphv-ac?si=lMyYassaUwz6ia8g&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Video link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBN4Kphv-ac&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBN4Kphv-ac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing History</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/observing-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 12:17:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/observing-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
When I was a kid, CS in K12 wasn&amp;#39;t a thing. Personal Computers were
just becoming available. I remember pilgrimages to the basement Polk
Hobby shop to play. I don&amp;#39;t even remember what those computers were
but soon, names like Apple, TRS-80 and Commodore PET were
appearing. Throughout my schooling, CS wasn&amp;#39;t a thing until High
School and even there it was a couple of random classes because
somehow Stuyvesant had an IBM-1130 - a punch card driven machine and a
couple of math teachers taught simple programming electives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my senior year, 1984, APCS came in but it wasn&amp;#39;t wide spread and it
was a single random class for a handful of students taught primarily
by math teachers. When I went into teaching after college and a short
stint at Goldman, not much has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What I&amp;#39;m getting at is that some of us - teachers of, um, let&amp;#39;s say,
an age have really gotten to witness history. We&amp;#39;ve been able to live
through the emergence of a new study area in K12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That doesn&amp;#39;t happen too often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At some levels I always realized this but in many ways I probably just
taught day to day without thinking about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We&amp;#39;ve witnessed something that didn&amp;#39;t even exist to starting to answer
questions like what should be taught? At what grade or grades?
Separate or as an add on to other subject areas? Who will teach it?
What must they know? What&amp;#39;s the point? Will this help solve the
achievement gap? And on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since America consists of fifty different education systems, if not
more, we&amp;#39;ve seen lots of different approaches - certification
questions, standards, or lack thereof, what counts as CS? CS vs Tech
Ed, requirements or electives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In some ways it&amp;#39;s amazing how far things have come but also amazing
how much further there is to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I&amp;#39;m in some ways amazed but also lament so many missed
opportunities. In many ways CS Education in K12 has gone the way of
other education. That&amp;#39;s a shame. Just like in Math, prior to NCLB
Math teachers had to &lt;strong&gt;know&lt;/strong&gt; math. Now. many take &amp;#34;math for math
teachers&amp;#34; and can barely pass local assessments. CS Ed in far too many
places seems to be going that route. CS Certification programs that
barely contain any real CS or even worse, just certifying based on
vendor driven professional development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#39;m also lamenting the frequency of the checkbox approach - Oh we do
that in this existing class - check, or we have this one course on the
books for a few self selecting students - check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But then, there&amp;#39;s also some good going on out there. The teachers that
applied to my cert program - even the ones that weren&amp;#39;t accepted were
all seeking out real CS knowledge and a network of CS teachers -
that&amp;#39;s inspiring and of course the fact that we&amp;#39;re discussing CS
availability and equity related issues means we&amp;#39;ve gotten things off
the ground and there are people paying attention, at least to that
side of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All this, is of course, ongoing. It&amp;#39;s going to be years, probably
decades before K12 CS is settled for better or worse. Some people will
want to be very involved - I&amp;#39;d like to think that my involvement has
been for the better, and some would rather just teach but pay
attention. We&amp;#39;re living through the evolution of a field of study and
really not many generations of teachers really get to be able to do
that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>