<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pedagogy on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://newblog/tags/pedagogy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pedagogy on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 12:44:43 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://newblog/tags/pedagogy/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    <item>
      <title>In Education, What&#39;s New is Old</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/old-is-new/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 12:44:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/old-is-new/</guid>
      <description>I noticed a tweet the other day talking about gamification of education. It got me thinking.
Gamification isn&amp;#39;t specifically the hot trend right now, at least not as &amp;#34;the one true way&amp;#34; to teach but every few years it surges as this great new idea to fix education.
When it surges, it&amp;#39;s always the hot new thing but it never really is.
Gamification has been around at least since I was in grade school and it was never a magic bullet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yes, deadlines do matter</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/late-assignments/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 08:28:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/late-assignments/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been seeing a few threads lately talking about the virtues of allowing students to hand in assignments late. Not just late but pretty much whenever they want. This attitude seems to be related with things like mastery or specification grading, which I believe in but it&amp;#39;s not the same thing.
The threads start with someone saying that assignments shouldn&amp;#39;t have deadlines or some variant and the thread proceeds with a bunch of people chiming in as to why a teacher who actually enforces deadlines is an inhuman monster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Memorable Lesson (at least for one student)</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/a-memorable-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 13:31:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/a-memorable-lesson/</guid>
      <description>Back to calling an audible.
Around seven years ago I was visiting with some former students at Google in Mountain View. One of them from way back in the late 90s, Pawel, out of the blue said there was one lesson I taught that was particularly memorable. Not memorable in the &amp;#34;that was fun&amp;#34; way like maybe my Halloween adventures but memorable in that he felt he got a lot more out of it than a normal lesson.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should every assignment be open ended?</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/creative-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 06:43:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/creative-projects/</guid>
      <description>This post by my friend Alfred caught my eye yesterday. It&amp;#39;s a good post - some good examples of inserting student creativity even into small intro level assignments. While I like the post and agree with the sentiment of open ended, student driven projects, I had to take issue with the lead quote Alfred used: “If you assign a project and get back 30 of the same thing, that’s not a project, that is a recipe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why it takes so long to become a better teacher</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/feedback-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2021 06:54:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/feedback-loop/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve written about how long it takes to become a master teacher and that even after 9 or 10 years most teachers are really just advanced beginners. A big reason for that is our long feedback loop. You do something and you can&amp;#39;t do it again for a year.
I was listening to a podcast on my morning run by the Hudson River and something came up about differences between quantities of items.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter College CS Teacher Certification Summer 2021</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-cohort-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 08:58:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-cohort-2/</guid>
      <description>Last Friday concluded the summer portion of Hunter&amp;#39;s CS Teacher Certification program. It was an intense month. All day every day from June 28th through July 30. On the one hand between burnout and covid fatigue it was a tough month and I&amp;#39;m dealing with some much needed recovery this week. On the other hand, working with JonAlf, Topher, new team member Genady along with around 25 amazing teachers and teacher candidates made it a highlight of the year.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designated Slacker</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/designated-slacker/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 12:42:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/designated-slacker/</guid>
      <description>Our teacher certification program is in full swing. All day every day through the end of the month. We finished off the first course about a week ago and are currently covering data structures and methods - teaching methods that is.
All day every day is pretty intense and doing it on Zoom doesn&amp;#39;t help so we try to change things up. As with many Zoom based classes, we make use of breakout rooms for small group work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Styles</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teaching-styles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 08:31:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teaching-styles/</guid>
      <description>My friend Emmanuel lamented over on Facebook on &amp;#34;Learning Styles,&amp;#34; or more specifically on how it&amp;#39;s still given credence. We all chimed in in agreement but not an hour later I saw a Twitter thread where education thought leaders extolled the virtues of Learning Styles all over again. I pointed out that it&amp;#39;s a great example as to why so many teachers scoff at &amp;#34;the research&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;research backed practices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Sort over Zoom</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/qsort-over-zoom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 12:10:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/qsort-over-zoom/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;#39;t been blogging much this year. Not sure why - probably pandemic fatigue. It&amp;#39;s also affected my blog reading - more scanning, less deep reading. I&amp;#39;ve also been trying to spend mode time off screen learning how to paint (with,let&amp;#39;s say mixed results :-) ) leaving less time and energy to blog. Hopefully I&amp;#39;ll pick up on both ends as more people get vaccinated and we can get to a more normal life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Less Engagement For More</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/less-engagement-for-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 09:01:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/less-engagement-for-more/</guid>
      <description>I think many of us are finding student engagement to be one of the more challenging aspects of remote teaching. I sure am.
In person it&amp;#39;s much easier to have in class discussions. You can read faces and body language, move around the room, encourage cross discussion and, well, you know, teach in the usual sense. Much harder on Zoom. The default behavior isn&amp;#39;t a room of people all together but rather a bunch of individual teacher student connections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarter Century Courses</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/quarter-century-courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 07:09:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/quarter-century-courses/</guid>
      <description>I was talking in our Curriculum Development class last week about the courses I&amp;#39;ve created over the years. From the first computer graphics course to the current teacher education courses. JonAlf pointed out that we missed an &amp;#34;important&amp;#34; occasion last spring - the twenty fifth offering of my computer graphics class at Stuy. I haven&amp;#39;t taught it in almost 10 years but it&amp;#39;s been running continuously for a quarter century since it first ran back in the mid 90s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - tools for remote instruction</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 06:07:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-tools/</guid>
      <description>Our summer intensive was supposed to be in person but COVID-19 changed that in a hurry. We had to scramble to redesign and figure out how we were going to run things.
We decided to go with the following:
Zoom for live meetings Slack for chat Git and GitHub
GitHub classroom for assignments GitHub repos for code distribution, class website and resource sharing. GitHub discussions for off hour and long form discussion While Zoom is a great platform it was lacking in a few areas so we also ended up using: Padlet as a collaborative writing space for groups Assorted whiteboarding tools.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS teachers - Curricula don&#39;t add richness, teachers do</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-topics-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 07:25:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-topics-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve frequently been asked for curricula. I&amp;#39;ll hear from a school or someone otherwise involved in a school or education and they&amp;#39;ll ask for a course they can drop in and teach.
I explain it doesn&amp;#39;t work that way. A syllabus or curriculum is only so good. A great curriculum with a bad teacher will still be bad but a great teacher can do a lot to salvage a horrible curriculum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - what to leave in, what to leave out</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 07:37:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-methods-choosing/</guid>
      <description>Teachers always make decisions in their courses - what to leave in, what to leave out. I&amp;#39;ve seen programming and data structure classes where everything is written from scratch and others where a few things are explained and the students just use built in types like the java LinkedList or Arrays.sort() method.
Do too much from scratch and you&amp;#39;ll never finish the curriculum. Do to little and the students won&amp;#39;t really understand what&amp;#39;s going on and walk a path towards being programmers or coders rather than computer scientists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS Teacher Certification - Topics in CS</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 07:13:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-topics/</guid>
      <description>Officially, the last course of the summer was &amp;#34;Modern Topics in Computer Science.&amp;#34; The idea was that K12 CS teachers on the one hand need depth beyond the typical terminal high school course, hence data structures and also breadth so that they could create electives, mix teasers in to the regular courses, or help precocious students with independent or semi-independant explorations. If someone was teaching this in a typical fall or spring semester course, they&amp;#39;d probably have a list of topics and spend a couple of weeks on each.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing CS Teachers - adding methods to our madness</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 06:47:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-methods/</guid>
      <description>Our summer intensive was, well, pretty intensive. We met all day every day for a month and knocked out four classes. Programming (CS1) Data Structures Topics Methods If you ever took or taught a summer session class, you know that time is tight and generally you cover a little less than in a fall or spring semester class. N credits in 5 weeks just isn&amp;#39;t the same as those same N credits spread over 13.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools matter when teaching (and learning)</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/tools-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 07:52:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/tools-matter/</guid>
      <description>One of our teacher certification cohort members asked for some help on our Slack the other day. It was about a side project - he was learning him so Javascript. It&amp;#39;s always very cool to see teachers exploring things that can help with their craft on their own.
The whole situation reminded me about how important good tooling is and why, in spite of its popularity, javascript has some severe issues as a learning language and I&amp;#39;m a guy that actually likes javascript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Merge Over Zoom - A Hunter CS Certification Program Update</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/merge-over-zoom/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 19:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/merge-over-zoom/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;#39;ve been talking sorting and searching in our teacher certification program and today was all about the merge sort. One of the strategies we use when teaching it in person involves sorting a deck of cards by Tom Sawyering it with the class. It&amp;#39;s fun and it&amp;#39;s effective but you can&amp;#39;t do it over Zoom. What to do? We didn&amp;#39;t want to just jump into the nuts and bolts of merge sort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hunter&#39;s CS Teacher Certification program Week 2</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:31:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-cert-week-2/</guid>
      <description>Time for some thoughts after week 2.
Since this is the inaugural edition of our program and there was no way to really know what the cohort would be like we&amp;#39;ve been adjusting on the fly. This was expected but we&amp;#39;re finally starting to settle in. We&amp;#39;re still finding more zoom heavy days but as we move towards the end of our data structures segment there should be fewer of those.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limitations Of Remote Teaching</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/limitations-of-remote-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:41:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/limitations-of-remote-teaching/</guid>
      <description>While tools like Zoom, Slack and others are a tremendous boon as we&amp;#39;re forced to do all our teaching remotely the limitations become apparent as we settle in and try to go beyond the basics of an offsite meeting.
Today was code review day in my CS1 class. It&amp;#39;s a lesson that I enjoy teaching and I think my students get a lot out of it. Today we had to do it remote.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Necessity is the mother of invention</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/mother-of-invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 18:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/mother-of-invention/</guid>
      <description>I didn&amp;#39;t expect to read a Fred Wilson post on teaching online but that&amp;#39;s what I found when I visited his blog this morning. Don&amp;#39;t get me wrong - I suspect that Fred has the makings of a great teacher, it&amp;#39;s just not what I expected to find. There have been many posts about education but I don&amp;#39;t recall any about teaching or more specifically the art of teaching. I did find this post though which actually speaks to some of the thoughts today&amp;#39;s post got churning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remote Classes</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/remote-classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 09:34:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/remote-classes/</guid>
      <description>Over at AVC Fred Wilson just posted about Outschool&amp;#39;s efforts to support students and teachers in the event of school closures due to the Coronavirus. All the details and relevant links are in the post. I looked a bit into Outschool when Fred first wrote about them but never had a chance to do a deep dive.
Now, internet based teaching is not going to be as effective as in person teaching but I was thinking about how far things have come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teacher Centric Teaching</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-centric-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 08:27:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-centric-teaching/</guid>
      <description>Every few years the experts give us some new magic bullet, some new teaching fad research based pedagogical technique. Teachers are trained in it, forced to use it - frequently as a one size fits all. If we do, we&amp;#39;re good teachers, if we don&amp;#39;t we get the dreaded ineffective on our annual ratings.
I was reminded of this when reading Mark Guzdial&amp;#39;s recent blog post on things he got wrong in Computing Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with texts part 1 - cleaning the data</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/cleaning-textx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 16:18:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/cleaning-textx/</guid>
      <description>I run periodic professional development sessions here in New York with my partner in crime JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver. I call them PD for &amp;#34;APCS-A, similar or beyond&amp;#34; and they&amp;#39;re designed to fill a professional development gap. We try to run them once a month but it&amp;#39;s a little less frequent than that.
The NYCDOE has taken on the monster task of CS for all and since they&amp;#39;re trying to get to everyone they have to run a bazillion sessions but all at an introductory level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My test grading policy</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/grading-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 17:13:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/grading-policy/</guid>
      <description>I was working on writing a midterm the other day so figured I&amp;#39;d talk a bit about my test grading policy.
Before getting to the specifics, let me set the stage. I spent most of my career at Stuyvesant - a public magnet school in NYC. There are many great students who are interested in learning but there&amp;#39;s also a focus on grades. and this leads to a non-insignificant portion of the student body that is grade obsessed and will do everything and anything for every point possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching techniques - industry to classroom and classroom to industry</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/industry-techniques-in-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2019 12:34:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/industry-techniques-in-class/</guid>
      <description>There are things we do in school and there are things we do in industry and they&amp;#39;re not always the same. In school we might use a learning language or an IDE which gives additional support and at times even take away language features while at work you might you might make heavy use of continuous integration tools. On the other hand, sometimes we use the same things. Java is used in schools and in industry, StackOverflow consulted in both and many schools use professional IDEs like Eclipse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pig Latin - a beginner lesson with some depth</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/piglatin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 17:11:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/piglatin/</guid>
      <description>I recently did a unit where I had my students convert words into Pig Latin. I like the problem because to start it only requires strings, functions and if statements but there is some depth to the unit.
We start with simplified rules:
If the word starts with a vowel, add &amp;#34;ay&amp;#34; to the end of the word If it starts with a consonant move the first latter to the end and add &amp;#34;ay&amp;#34; don&amp;#39;t worry about anything else Students usually start with something like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Is Good Teaching</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/what-is-good-teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 17:13:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/what-is-good-teaching/</guid>
      <description>I had a conversation with my principal during my last year at Stuy. She said &amp;#34;whenever the superintendent or high level education people come and ask to see our best teachers I can never bring them to Jim&amp;#39;s class.&amp;#34; Everyone knows that Jim is the best. I describe him as &amp;#34;the teacher I aspire to be.&amp;#34; What&amp;#39;s the problem? The problem is that Jim didn&amp;#39;t teach the way the powers that be wanted him to teach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Different languages, different techniques, different solutions</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/different-languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 17:33:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/different-languages/</guid>
      <description>I spent this weekend diving back into Clojure or more specifically, Clojurescript. For those who don&amp;#39;t know, Clojure is a Lisp that runs on the JVM. The solution it particularly seeks to &amp;#34;solve&amp;#34; is immutability. Clojurescript is Clojure that compiles to Javascript for web applications. Tooling aside, it&amp;#39;s all pretty neat.
I didn&amp;#39;t do anything earth shaking, just a quick implementation of Conway&amp;#39;s game of life and Snake. While the code isn&amp;#39;t particularly good, you can check them out here (Snake, Life).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do It First</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/do-it-first/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 08:00:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/do-it-first/</guid>
      <description>Reading Garth Flint&amp;#39;s end of year post and Alfred Thompson&amp;#39;s follow up had me thinking about a couple of things. One was spurred when Garth wrote &amp;#34;They also have to figure out the math before they code.&amp;#34; This made me think about all the details we sometimes take for for granted. Things that are hard for our students that we just know. It&amp;#39;s frequently math that we might find trivial but it could also be much simpler things.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing A Textbook</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/choosing-a-textbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 10:41:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/choosing-a-textbook/</guid>
      <description>Now and again there are requests on the assorted CS Education forums asking about which text book to use. These requests are usually for APCS-A. There are usually a number of &amp;#34;I&amp;#39;m very happy with …&amp;#34; replies but I thought I&amp;#39;d take a bit of a deeper dive into what teachers might want to consider when evaluating a textbook.
It was never an issue when I started as a math teacher.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>March PD for CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 15:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond-3-14-2019/</guid>
      <description>Back in December we ran our first PD session for CS teachers. This was to address the need for professional development for teachers who were more experienced in terms of computer science - we aimed this at people who were ready to teach APCS-A, similar, or beyond and also to start to build a community for these teachers. We had trouble setting things up for February but we&amp;#39;re good to go for March, April and May.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I use Github Classroom</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/github-classroom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Feb 2019 16:42:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/github-classroom/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s been an amazingly unproductive weekend. Mostly because I&amp;#39;ve been sick with the flu. It sucks but since the rest of the family&amp;#39;s away anway at least I&amp;#39;m not making everyone miserable.
I did manage to stage my next couple of classes and figured that writing this post wouldn&amp;#39;t take too much energy since it&amp;#39;s mostly a video.
Earlier, I talked about using GitHub and TravicCI and this time around I show how I use GitHub classroom to set up, disseminate, and collect assignments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Java Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/java-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Feb 2019 09:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/java-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Two of the hardest topics to make meaningful to students in APCS-A are inheritance and interfaces. It&amp;#39;s not that they&amp;#39;re super difficult topics but rather that they&amp;#39;re not often needed, useful, or superior to not using them on beginner assignments. More often than not the motivation is a bit forced as are the assignments. Inheritance is its own can of worms and to be honest, something I&amp;#39;ve not found to be all that useful or necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Github Classroom and Travis CI</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/github-classroom-travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 09:44:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/github-classroom-travis/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been using GitHub with my classes since GitHub&amp;#39;s early days. Over time I&amp;#39;ve gotten my workflows down. I use a combination of shell scripts - many just written on the fly, GitHub organizations, and some naming conventions and protocols that have served me well. A few years ago, the GitHub Education team started GitHub Classroom. I looked at it at the time. It was pretty cool but I had my workflow so I didn&amp;#39;t adopt it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sequencing Topics</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/sequencing-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 16:06:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/sequencing-topics/</guid>
      <description>Monday&amp;#39;s the start of the Spring semester. Other than the 8:00am start I&amp;#39;m looking forward to it. My 8:00am class is the honors/lab component that goes with CS1. I taught it last semester and during each of the past two years at Hunter. My second class is the follow up - more OOP / C++, data structures and some algorithms.
The material is old hat. I&amp;#39;ve taught it in Java more times than I can count and also in C++ albeit many years ago.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Professional Development - APCS-A, similar and beyond</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 08:56:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/pd-apcs-a-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>A while ago I wrote about our plans at Hunter to run professional development for CS teachers. Specifically, running once a month sessions for teachers who teach APCS-A, similar and beyond.
The idea started as a joke but morphed into a legit idea.
I was talking to some friends about CTLE hours and how ridiculous the system is. NY State teachers need 100 hours of CTLE credit (PD hours) every so many years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let Teachers Teach</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/let-teachers-teach/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 08:57:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/let-teachers-teach/</guid>
      <description>Mark Guzdial&amp;#39;s post the other day about direct isntruction struck a chord with me. Right up front, Mark said:
The research evidence is growing that students learn better through direct instruction rather than through a discovery-based method, where we expect students to figure things out for themselves.
Quite a surprise to the teachers who have been beaten over the head with &amp;#34;everything must be discovery&amp;#34; in recent years. At the end of the post, Mark writes:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compile Each Concept</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/compile-each-concept/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Oct 2018 14:46:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/compile-each-concept/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;#39;ve all been there:
Student: Teacher, I need help Teacher (comes over) Student (shows screen listing three bazillion errors)
The student has just written pages of code and finally decided to try to run it only to end up with pages of errors.
Error messages can at times be hard to read for beginners but to see and truth be told, they frequently don&amp;#39;t even read them but over the years I&amp;#39;ve developed a practice that I&amp;#39;ve found helpful as a software developer and if students adopt the same practice it can save them a lot of time and effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS vs CT vs Coding</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/cs-ct-cc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 12:08:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/cs-ct-cc/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;#39;s been a lot of buzz recently concernting Computational Thinking (CT) vs Computer Science (CS) vs Coding / Programming on the interwebs.
Some of the questions and concerns that I&amp;#39;ve seen recently include:
What is CT?? Will rich schools get CS and poor only CT? Will rich schools get CS and poor on coding? The first question is a big one and as a community we haven&amp;#39;t answered it yet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
