<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misc on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://newblog/categories/misc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in misc on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 08:52:49 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://newblog/categories/misc/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    <item>
      <title>The College Board wasn&#39;t cowardly</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/college-board-ap-aastudies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 08:52:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/college-board-ap-aastudies/</guid>
      <description>As I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;re aware, recently, in his latest racist, fascist proclamation, Ron DeSantis threatened to stop offering AP African American Studies (APAAS) in Florida because, well, we can&amp;#39;t actually teach our children anything resembling our actual rather checkered history.
I&amp;#39;m sure you&amp;#39;re also aware that the College Board just announced changes to APAAS which basically removed everything DeSantis found objectionable.
I&amp;#39;ve been seeing articles, blog posts, Tweets and more all calling the College Boards act a cowardly one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Layoffs and Workers Rights</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/tech-layoffs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 10:59:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/tech-layoffs/</guid>
      <description>Lots of layoffs in big tech recently. Overall lousy but I am encouraged by the number of people trying to organize the local community to be supportive in helping those affected.
Clearly this &amp;#34;correction&amp;#34; can turn current employees worlds upside down and place individuals and families in precarious financial situations but the effects also affect the incoming workforce. In addition to layoffs, internships and offers have been canceled left and right.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things they remember that we forgot</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/forgot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 06:43:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/forgot/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago I wrote about some of the things our students remember (link - sorry for the bad formatting). Lessons, concepts, stories, or even small jokes I remember telling but had no idea that they left a lasting impression on any students.
Fast forward to yesterday. I spent some time yesterday at a friend, a former student&amp;#39;s company for their holiday get together. My friend was telling a story about how I helped get him started - I won&amp;#39;t get into details but while I do remember the overall impression of including and encouraging him, I don&amp;#39;t remember the detailed specifics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retiring part 3 - What&#39;s Next</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/retiring-3-whats-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 19:40:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/retiring-3-whats-next/</guid>
      <description>Links to the three posts in this series: If you&amp;#39;re seeing this before the previous two posts, I&amp;#39;d encourage you to read post 1 and 2 first.
Post 1: Why I&amp;#39;m retiring Post 2: What was accomplished at Hunter Post 3: This post As I said at the start of these three posts, I do want to stay in the game. Maybe take a break and definately slow down but I still think I&amp;#39;ve got something to contribute.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retiring part 2 - Accomplishments</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 15:35:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/retiring-2-accomplishments/</guid>
      <description>Links to the posts in this series If you&amp;#39;re reading this before the previous post, I&amp;#39;d recommend going back and reading that one first. Post 1: Why I&amp;#39;m retiring Post 2: This post Post 3: What I think I&amp;#39;ll be looking for next I think I&amp;#39;ve carved out a somewhat unique career. Never set out to be a teacher and a couple of different turns here or there and things could have been very different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>After 7 years at Hunter College and 33 in NYC public schools, time for a change.</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/retiring-1-why/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 06:43:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/retiring-1-why/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been dropping mentions of this here and there for a while now but I think it&amp;#39;s time to come out more formally -
I&amp;#39;m planning on retiring from Hunter at the end of this Spring.
This doesn&amp;#39;t mean getting out of the CS or CS Ed game entirely - I could stay on in a part time capacity and, after some decompression I think I still have things to offer but the plan is retire, collect my pension, and then see where I can continue to be contribute to the Ed/CS Ed scene.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crafting a new major for tech</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/new-major/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 09:42:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/new-major/</guid>
      <description>Hunter College, like most colleges and universities is facing unprecedented demand for CS. It&amp;#39;s the hot major. Being a public college, we have an obligation to provide the best education possible to as many students as we can in our locality. This means we can&amp;#39;t just put a GPA requirement or other cap on the major and we can&amp;#39;t do things I&amp;#39;ve heard &amp;#34;elite&amp;#34; schools do like essentially making applicants apply to the major direct from HS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>College Recommendation Season</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/college-recs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 20:42:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/college-recs/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s fall so for HS teachers who taught juniors last year it&amp;#39;s recommendation writing season. For many of those teachers, they&amp;#39;re already well into the season with early decision deadlines being as early as November 1.
Writing recs is one thing I don&amp;#39;t miss now that I&amp;#39;m working at the college level. Sure, it was always an honor to be asked but it was a lot of work. Now I&amp;#39;m on the other side and reading the recs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 55</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/turning-55/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 15:15:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/turning-55/</guid>
      <description>So, I turned 55 today. Another year older. The changes? Well, I&amp;#39;m seeing more doctors and seeing them more frequently and to be honest, I&amp;#39;d love to have a day or two without some small niggling ache or pain but that&amp;#39;s life. Like many people my age, we&amp;#39;ve got our health issues but I&amp;#39;m pretty active and managing mine (hey, I had a great 8 mile run this morning :-) ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masters of CS Education</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/masters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 06:45:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/masters/</guid>
      <description>I was in the middle of writing a post on how early and often we should be teaching CS in our schools but had to jump in with a quick hit here.
As any reader here knows, Hunter was the first institution with state approved CS Teacher Education Masters and Certificate programs. Siena had the first Bachelors program (Hunter doesn&amp;#39;t have undergraduate education programs that lead to state certification).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CS - it isn&#39;t all that</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/cs-all-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 11:52:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/cs-all-that/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve dedicated my entire career - something like 32 years, to CS education and the spread of CS education. So, while I try to be a cheerleader I also think it&amp;#39;s important to call out things that we do or say that are maybe not so great.
So, I hope I don&amp;#39;t annoy too many people (or maybe I hope I do) with this post and maybe a few more to come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You can&#39;t workshop a lesson</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/workshop-a-lesson/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 10:02:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/workshop-a-lesson/</guid>
      <description>The other day, Natan scored tickets for us to see an interview with High Jackman and Sutton Foster. We&amp;#39;ll be seeing them in &amp;#34;The Music Man&amp;#34; come this fall.
It was fun but it was the taping for a radio interview so nothing earth shattering or surprising. Still, one thing stuck with me and got me thinking.
Jackman told a story about how, during rehearsals, he wandered down from his dressing room to find Foster was working with Jerry Zaks, the director on &amp;#34;My White Knight.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put It In The Books</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/put-it-in-the-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 17:20:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/put-it-in-the-books/</guid>
      <description>Just finished entering grades closing out my 32nd year teaching.
Whew!
It&amp;#39;s been a hard year for me and I&amp;#39;m sure even harder for the K12 teachers out there. Still this year I&amp;#39;m really missing what I was oh so many years ago - a regular teacher.
Teaching from September through June is a beast and from my first day on the job I had to work ten times harder than I ever had to as a software engineer and was commensurately exhausted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Critical Mass Of CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/a-critical-mass-of-cs-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 13:38:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/a-critical-mass-of-cs-teachers/</guid>
      <description>A big difficulty with creating CS opportunities for all our students is the lack of CS teachers. New York City addressed this problem with their CS4All program - quick form PD to get teachers into CS classrooms in a hurry. One can debate if that was the best way to go but it enabled NYC to create a whole lot of CS classes in a very short period of time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SIGCSE2022 - Things I plan to blog about</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/sigcse2022-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 20:07:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/sigcse2022-intro/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been up in Providence RI since this past Wednesday for SIGCSE2022. The big Computer Science Educators conference. Also, my first in person conference since pre-covid.
I wasn&amp;#39;t sure how I was going to feel about this big in person gathering but as it&amp;#39;s turned out, it&amp;#39;s been pretty comfortable.
So far, I&amp;#39;ve attended two terrific keynotes. One by Barbara Liskov and the other Barbara Ericson, some really interesting sessions and some less interesting ones and have had a great time discussing CS education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First live conference in 2 years</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/sigcse-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 08:13:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/sigcse-2022/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow I&amp;#39;ll be driving up to Providence Rhode Island for SIGSE 2022, basically the largest computer science education conference out there. I guess ITSE, a conference I&amp;#39;ve never attended, is larger but that&amp;#39;s really EdTech with some CS.
The last in person conference I went to was two almost exactly two years ago - also SIGCSE. I arrived in Portland and went to a pre-conference session and on the morning of the big start, about three hours before I ran my session, I saw an email saying we were canceled.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming Problem Solving And Crosswords</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/programming-problem-solving-and-crosswords/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 17:37:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/programming-problem-solving-and-crosswords/</guid>
      <description>I used to do the New York Times Crossword puzzle. I don&amp;#39;t remember when I started - some time late in Eugene Maleska&amp;#39;s tenure as the editor. I continued on a few years into Will Shortz&amp;#39;s puzzles. I stopped when the Times wanted to charge me for both print and online. I preferred reading the physical paper but liked printing the puzzle from their online site. I was also pissed at the Times coverage of a number of issues at the time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pension Consultations</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/pension/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 17:41:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/pension/</guid>
      <description>Devorah and I just got off a Zoom pension consultation. Very enlightening.
I&amp;#39;m 54 so regardless, can&amp;#39;t retire for another year but Devorah hit 55 last November and the DOE can really kill ones spirit and grind you down.
Overall I&amp;#39;ve been pretty happy at Hunter but I&amp;#39;ve written before about the fact that I&amp;#39;ve been feeling some burn out and have been basically doing 2+ full time jobs myself at Hunter for the past few years and that&amp;#39;s just not sustainable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning 54</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/turning-54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 13:59:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/turning-54/</guid>
      <description>So, tomorrow, October 19, is my birthday. The big 5 4. Okay, maybe it&amp;#39;s not a traditionally big one. It doesn&amp;#39;t end in a zero or a five but I think it rates.
Why? Because it&amp;#39;s one shy of 55.
That&amp;#39;s the magic age when I can retire collect my pension should I choose to do so. It&amp;#39;s what you get when start young and put in over 30 years of service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No CSTA conference for me this year</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/no-csta2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 17:08:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/no-csta2021/</guid>
      <description>Today is the start of CSTA&amp;#39;s annual conference. Like last year, it&amp;#39;s virtual. Unlike the past few years, this year I won&amp;#39;t be attending.
I&amp;#39;m a big fan of the CSTA conference. Jake and team have done an amazing job growing the conference and it&amp;#39;s been a highlight of my year every time I&amp;#39;ve attended.
I could say that I&amp;#39;m not attending due to my schedule - I&amp;#39;m pretty much spending all day every day during July teaching in my CS Teacher Certification program and at the end of the day I&amp;#39;m wiped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Election Thoughts - feeling hope but still concerned</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/election-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 06:56:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/election-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;#39;t usually talk politics on this blog but it is the news of the day. We truly are at a turning point in this country and we should all be concerned with the road we take.
Yesterday the media outlets called the election for Biden/Harris. It&amp;#39;s not over but I thought this would be as good a time as any to share some thoughts and more importantly concerns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>53 trips around the sun</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 20:36:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/birthday/</guid>
      <description>In the 10 plus years of this blog I&amp;#39;ve never done a post on my birthday. Okay, maybe I&amp;#39;ve written one on my birthday but never talked about it.
Why this year?
No particular reason. Maybe because I&amp;#39;m getting older. I&amp;#39;m 53 today. Devorah will turn 54 in a month - from there one year until she can retire. I can follow a year later. I&amp;#39;m pretty happy with what I&amp;#39;m doing but it&amp;#39;s nice to know that in two years I&amp;#39;ll have a lot of options on the table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unplugging with Bob Ross</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/unplugging-bob-ross/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 08:56:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/unplugging-bob-ross/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s been a long year since March. Many of us have not really been able to leave NYC for a variety of reasons - financial, professional, or family to name a few.
Other than a couple of small escapes in the last two weeks we&amp;#39;ve been home and working from home in our Manhattan apartment since this all started. Early on we didn&amp;#39;t get out much and we still aren&amp;#39;t and that does take its toll.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scared teachers can&#39;t teach and scared students won&#39;t learn</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/scared-teachers-scared-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 13:23:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/scared-teachers-scared-students/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been reading a lot of takes on NYC schools reopening. We&amp;#39;ve had daily conversations about it with our summer teachers but conversations abound on Facebook, Twitter and everywhere else.
Many salient points have been raised - given the DOE&amp;#39;s track record, can they make things safe and will they? Can they be trusted? Given that any policy needs all players to follow the rules - students, teachers, and staff how can that ever happen?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PSA on CSTA (NYC)</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/psa-for-csta/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 11:43:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/psa-for-csta/</guid>
      <description>Just a quick public service announcemnt.
Up until now CSTA-NYC has been using Meetup to organize and advertise events but now they&amp;#39;re moving over to using the CSTA site as their platform. If you&amp;#39;re a CS teacher you should be a part of CSTA. There&amp;#39;s both a free tier and a plus tier which costs $50 a year. I&amp;#39;ve been a plus member since that level became available. If you&amp;#39;re a NYC teacher, you should join the CSTA NYC chapter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting Our Students</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/supporting-our-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 12:22:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/supporting-our-students/</guid>
      <description>Austin Cory Bart put together a great post about supporting Black students in CS1. Cory asked about this on the SIGCSE mailing list and in his post he both breaks things down and shares all the resources that he compiled from the ensuing discussion. There&amp;#39;s a lot of good stuff both in the post and in the links but there&amp;#39;s a lot to get lost in. As teachers we can sometimes affect change at a department or school level but we can always make a difference in our classes and with our students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teachers and Police</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teachers-police/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 10:56:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teachers-police/</guid>
      <description>Teachers and Police It&amp;#39;s been an ugly few days but perhaps in some ways a hopeful few as people have been making their voices heard like never before in my lifetime. We&amp;#39;ve seen and endless stream of videos of peaceful protest and far too many instances of police officers overstepping their bounds. I keep hearing about violent protesters but those videos seem to be avoiding my feeds as are the videos of law enforcement going after the looters who are a separate group from the protestors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Before condemning try walking in their shoes</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/privilege/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 19:20:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/privilege/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve got some CS Ed stuff I want to write but can&amp;#39;t bring myself to writing about it today. I rarely post outside of my wheelhouse - CS, Education and the intersection of the two.
I don&amp;#39;t really think I&amp;#39;m qualified to say much about the current crisis. The out of control police, racism, class warfare, a failed government not only at the federal level but also in New York city and state but maybe I can share something worthwhile from my narrow experiences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Covid-19 Journey (so far)</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 07:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/covid/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;#39;t been posting much over the past couple of weeks and that&amp;#39;s partly because we&amp;#39;ve been under the weather.
Yep - Covid-19. First things first - we&amp;#39;re all either recovered or well on the way. I thought I&amp;#39;d write up our experience as it might be useful for others who are going through similar. This disease is weird and seems to affect people differently but three of us followed a similar path.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Email or USPS</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/email-or-usps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 14:00:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/email-or-usps/</guid>
      <description>USPS is in financial trouble. That&amp;#39;s been pretty well documented recently. Most reasonable people will recognize that the USPS is both an important service and while it receives no taxpayer support would be profitable were it not for the GOP imposing unfair and unrealistic pension funding requirements in 2006.
Although I&amp;#39;m an ardent supporter of the post office and feel that privatization of such an important intuition would be criminal today I want to talk about some small repercussions of so many things going to email rather than snail mail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Passover 2020</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/passover-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:59:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/passover-2020/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday was the start of Passover and like many others we weren&amp;#39;t able to physically gather with friends and family to celebrate. Since the Talmud, unlike the NYC Dept of Education, doesn&amp;#39;t seem to ban Zoom, like many others, we used Zoom to connect with family.
Tonight we&amp;#39;ll do it again.
In the meantime, I thought I&amp;#39;d share this small bit of research Natan did a couple of years ago on a traditional part of the seder: A Historically Informed Echad Mi Yodea</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brazilian Carrot Cake</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/carrot-cake/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 15:55:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/carrot-cake/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt;figure class=&amp;#34;z_image_center&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;#34;/img/carrot-cake.jpg&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/figure&amp;gt;
Not my normal post but these are not normal times. Besides, this isn&amp;#39;t the first recipe I&amp;#39;ve posted. I&amp;#39;m one of those that will, as long as supplies allow, bake and cook my way through our shelter in. Today I made Brazilian carrot cake. It&amp;#39;s not quite the same as an American carrot cake as you&amp;#39;ll see from the recipe below. First, carrot cake rules:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Career Directions - how a sad day changed mine</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/career-directions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 14:39:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/career-directions/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend yesterday who had just started doing grad work in school leadership. It got me thinking about my original career plans and how you never know where you&amp;#39;re going to end up.
Well, not my original original career plans. When I started on Wall Street I had no idea what the future would bring. For all I knew, I could have been a career professional programmer or even gone over to the business side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I&#39;m looking forward to in 2020</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/looking-forward-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 12:45:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/looking-forward-2020/</guid>
      <description>Happy new year to everyone.
I&amp;#39;ve been reading some prediction posts this morning on blogs and social media. Big national and world level stuff. I&amp;#39;ve never been much for predictions so I thought I&amp;#39;d share some more local and personal things I&amp;#39;m looking forward to in the coming year.
First a couple of big ones. I&amp;#39;m just about to complete my fourth year at Hunter. Time really does fly. It&amp;#39;s been a long road but late in 2019 NY State finally approved our CS Teacher Certification programs!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You Can&#39;t Win If You Don&#39;t Enter</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/you-cant-win-if-you-dont-enter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2019 17:19:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/you-cant-win-if-you-dont-enter/</guid>
      <description>Or, as Wayne Gretzky said &amp;#34;You miss 100% of the shots you don&amp;#39;t take.&amp;#34;
Why do I mention this? Because I&amp;#39;ve been hearing way too often from young people who are too quick to deny themselves opportunities and too often these are from students who have come from less advantaged backgrounds.
It&amp;#39;s Fall and I&amp;#39;ve been making my rounds visiting local schools to talk to seniors about colleges in general and Hunter CS in particular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waterfalls - a trip report</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/waterfalls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 19:18:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/waterfalls/</guid>
      <description>No, this post is not about the Waterfall development model. Devorah and I had a chance to take a little vacation up north.
First stop, Niagara Falls.
&amp;lt;br clear=&amp;#34;all&amp;#34;&amp;gt;
We did the Canada side 9 years ago when we did our Erie Canal bike trip (you can read about that by checking out some of my early blog posts). This time, the American side. My take is that the Canadian side is more polished and all private attractions - think Times Square or Disney.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni Anniversaries</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/alumni-anniversaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 07:32:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/alumni-anniversaries/</guid>
      <description>Two days ago, a teacher&amp;#39;s comment on a frustrating situation made me mad. Yesterday, I got to be part of something that made me very happy. Last night, Devorah and I ventured out to Coney Island to celebrate the twentieth wedding anniversary of two former students. It&amp;#39;s such a joy and an honor to be included in these types of life events and even more so to count the couple and so many other former students and friends.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeland 2019</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/codeland-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 19:46:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/codeland-2019/</guid>
      <description>I spent today at Codeland, a one day conference in NYC designed for developers in the early stages of their careers. Just as at CSTA, I was there with the GitHub contingent.
Codeland had talks and a keynote in a common auditorium, smaller breakout workshops and a couple of small vendor areas.
I spent most of the morning upstairs in the GitHub lounge so I onl caught part of one morning talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A 10X Student Story</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/ten-x-student-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 15:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/ten-x-student-story/</guid>
      <description>There were a bunch of threads on the 10X Developer recently. You know - that mythical beast that&amp;#39;s 10 times more productive than the regular software engineer. I didn&amp;#39;t see any of the original threads but I&amp;#39;m guessing they started with &amp;#34;your startup needs them&amp;#34; and then moved to the &amp;#34;they can&amp;#39;t work with anyone&amp;#34; along with tons of fun tongue and cheek 1X engineer tweets.
It got me thinking about 10X students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New(ish) Blog - cscheerleader.com</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/new-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 09:05:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/new-blog/</guid>
      <description>Many of us know Ria Galanos. Ria - a longtime friend and longtime CS teacher who has been very active in the APCS community has started a new chapter as a software engineer at Yext. Ria&amp;#39;s also started blogging about it.
I don&amp;#39;t know the direction the blog will take but I&amp;#39;m sure it will be influenced by Ria&amp;#39;s years as an educator. I&amp;#39;m also sure it will be worth reading.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
