<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>politics on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/politics/</link>
    <description>C&#39;est la Z (politics)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 13:54:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://cestlaz.github.io/tags/politics/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bringing Politics to your classroom?</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bringing-politics-to-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 13:54:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/post/bringing-politics-to-class/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
While perusing Reddit this morning, waiting for the stuffing to bake,
I came across &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Professors/comments/1819lan/does_anyone_know_more_about_what_happened_at/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently there was a todo at Berkeley
involving a CS instructor. Specifically a grad student teaching their
data structures course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can link from the first post to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/berkeley/comments/180yq0g/thoughts/?share_id=SOixfq7Qa35iw-TwjBLi1&#34;&gt;Berkeley subreddit post&lt;/a&gt; and can
listen to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wf63XKv77Mo&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; if you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It seems that this was the last day of class and the instructor
decided to end class early, announce that he was going to share some
of his own views so students should feel free to leave and then
proceeded to give a very one sided diatribe on the Israel/Palestine
situation and to say one sided is me being nice. The instructor said
that his opinions were his own but also noted that this would be his
last chance to share them. He also made a small attempt to tie it back
to CS citing ethics issues albeit in a general sense and not tied in
to the class &lt;a href=&#34;https://fa23.datastructur.es/index.html&#34;&gt;syllabus&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This raises an important question. Should teachers bring  politics
into their classrooms and if so, how and when.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my opinion, the instructor, in this case was extremely out of line
and I&amp;#39;m not just saying this because my views on the issue are very
much on the other side to his. I am in general, very pro Israel and
believe that much of what we&amp;#39;re seeing as pro-Palestinian  PR is in
fact antisemitic. The test to me is one, will they call out the
barbarism of Hamas, two, will they acknowledge that Jews are also
indigenous to the region and have a right to a Jewish state, and
three, will they call out with equal vigor anti arab actions brought
on by non-Jewish actors. Usually, but not always, the protesters fail
on all three counts. I also feel that it&amp;#39;s important for me to state
that I&amp;#39;m very much against Israel&amp;#39;s current right wing government and
many of their policies and they likewise need to be held accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back to this Berkeley situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this case, the instructor was way out of line. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He&amp;#39;s a CS PhD and has no actual expertise in the subject.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By ending class early, he used class time as well as his classroom
to share his political views. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even though he said the class was over and students could leave an
instructor is in a position of power and students likely felt
pressure to stay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similarly, his words carry more weight as he&amp;#39;s in a position of
power even though his words show only that he&amp;#39;s been exposed to one
sides propaganda (note, that this means he hasn&amp;#39;t heard either the
other side&amp;#39;s propaganda nor factual nor history information).  Of
course I could be wrong on this one but his words certainly sound
like I&amp;#39;m right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if this wasn&amp;#39;t on school time or property it might be a different
story. Similarly if this was really directly tied into a lesson it
might be different. Most importantly, if he presented all sides fairly
with factual information it might be different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alas, it wasn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If it were, though, it would still be tricky. I doubt I would have
shared my recent Israel/Palestine post or maybe even this one had I
not recently retired as it might influence the one or two stray
students who might happen upon this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#39;s also tricky because there aren&amp;#39;t always two sides. I am of the
opinion, for instance that the current Republican party is a serious
threat to American democracy. There aren&amp;#39;t two sides. There&amp;#39;s no
equivalence between &amp;#34;we want to raise minimum wage&amp;#34; on one side and
&amp;#34;we think LGBTQ people are a threat.&amp;#34; Sorry. No two sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many issues, though are in fact nuanced even if the scales are weighted
more on one side than the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The actual Israel/Palestine issue is one of those issues and in this
instance the instructor clearly overstepped their bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If I were to raise the issue in class (and I probably wouldn&amp;#39;t given
what I teach) I&amp;#39;d have to share historic context and resources from
both sides, share my biases, and perhaps bring in someone to present
the opposing side if I felt I couldn&amp;#39;t be fair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While not politics, I&amp;#39;ve always tried to take that stance on any
subjective issue I teach. Not as serious at all but when talking
coding style, I explain what I do, why I do it, what other people do
and why and then it&amp;#39;s up to the students to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#34;Non-CS&amp;#34; issues certainly have their place in CS classes. We should be
talking about ethics and equity and that should be across all our
classes. We should also bring topical issues and other fields into our
classes when we can. When we do, though we have to be careful that
we&amp;#39;re being teachers and not propagandists. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s not one issue, it&#39;s the President and his enablers</title>
      <link>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
Like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, I generally keep this
site clear of political issues with the exception of those that are
directly related to education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also, like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, this week has
provided a reason to break with that tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many people, including some friends, all more eloquent than I have
already posted, tweeted, and Facebooked  about the behavior of our
President and government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Long time blogger &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davewiner&#34;&gt;Dave Winer&lt;/a&gt; put together &lt;a href=&#34;http://trumpstatus.org/&#34;&gt;trumpstatus.org&lt;/a&gt; where he&amp;#39;s
collecting many of the issues that we&amp;#39;re all so alarmed with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I would add cabinet appointments to his list with my particular
personal concern over DeVos and the department of education. I&amp;#39;ve been
meaning to blog about that for a while - perhaps this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My concern for today is something else. Every day, I see a new Trump
induced crisis and every day I see a different subset of my circles
respond. It&amp;#39;s not quite as bad as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First they came for the Socialists, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Socialist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for the Trade Unionists, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Trade Unionist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Jew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for me—and there was no one left to speak for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People are indeed speaking out, but I am concerned that people
are going to rise up for their personal issue and when placated go
back to business as usual - this is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; the time for business as
usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the ACA repeal, I saw concerns from my working class friends and
friends that work with lower earning populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Going into the DeVos hearing, mostly educators - real educators not
astroturf reformers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With Friday&amp;#39;s order, the whole tech community came out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#39;s part of a thread by tech activist &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/anildash&#34;&gt;Anil Dash&lt;/a&gt; calling out,
calling on, and crediting assorted tech players.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;When net neutrality was the issue, Google, Twitter, Wikipedia, Reddit, Tumblr, etc. had a blackout, and it worked. This is far more grave.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anil Dash (@anildash) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/anildash/status/825414889908928517&#34;&gt;January 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;A powerful, straightforward statement from the CEO of Box — another publicly-traded company. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/wz5mQmTh6P&#34;&gt;https://t.co/wz5mQmTh6P&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anil Dash (@anildash) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/anildash/status/825470308463280130&#34;&gt;January 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We have to remember that all these order, policies, appointments, and
plans are coming from the same place - Donald Trump and those
politicians that are enabling him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If he backs off on immigration, education issues remain, if he backs
off there, we still have ACA, if that eases up, what about Women&amp;#39;s
rights and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This means we all have to get involved and stay involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What have I been doing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finally joined the ACLU and set up a monthly donation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;https://dailyaction.org&#34;&gt;Daily Action&lt;/a&gt; so that I get a reminder each day of&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;someone I can call to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;m starting to accumulate my representatives phone numbers as I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;make those calls and am trying to make at least a call a day to
remind our representatives who they work for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education and advocacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And if you suggestions for me - please post them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thus ends my not business as usual post. What&amp;#39;s going on in America is
not someone else&amp;#39;s problem - it&amp;#39;s all of our problem and we all have
to be active and vigilant to make it through tough times to come.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>