<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>certification on C&#39;est la Z</title>
    <link>https://newblog/tags/certification/</link>
    <description>Recent content in certification on C&#39;est la Z</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:39:37 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://newblog/tags/certification/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss" />
    <item>
      <title>Certified CS teachers - 2 flags in NY</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/certified-teacher-in-ny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:39:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/certified-teacher-in-ny/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;ve been running Hunter&amp;#39;s teacher certification program now for three years. We started with our Advanced Certificate which allows currently working teachers to earn an additional cert in CS and soon a few masters students joined the pipeline.
In three years we&amp;#39;ve made great progress. Approximately 45 New York City teachers are either state certified to teach CS or are qualified to recieve the certification once they file with the state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you build programs, teachers will come</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/people-will-teach-cs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 06:53:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/people-will-teach-cs/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s been a month since my last post. In fact it seems that most of the usual CS Ed bloggers are down in frequency this year. For me it&amp;#39;s probably been Covid fatigue and the resulting funk but I&amp;#39;m going to see if I can force myself to write more frequently.
So, the other day someone was asking about CS certification in NY state on Facebook. One comment caught my eye.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York City has Certified CS Teachers</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/certified-teachers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 19:35:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/certified-teachers/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m super proud to say that New York City now has state certified Computer Science Teachers!!!!!!
It&amp;#39;s been a long road - really long if you consider I got started on my CS Ed journey decades ago and there&amp;#39;s a long road ahead but we hit a major milestone. I started at Hunter a little over five years ago and creating teacher certification programs was one of the goals. Back then, the state had neither CS certification nor CS standards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics Teacher Wanted - must NOT know Physics</title>
      <link>https://newblog/post/teacher-creds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 19:00:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/post/teacher-creds/</guid>
      <description>There were a few posts over on Facebook this weekend about teacher certification. It started with a question - should teacher certification be based on an exam like APCS-A with the teacher correctly answering 85% or greater. A lively discussion followed. There was agreement and disagreement with responses ranging from:
good idea it&amp;#39;s too hard it&amp;#39;s not hard enough There was also a discussion of the importance of content knowledge vs knowing how to teach in general.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid>
      <description>About a week ago New York State&amp;#39;s new regulation creating a K12 CS teacher certification went live. Just the other day I was honored to be interviewed by Matt Flamm of Crain&amp;#39;s New York in a follow up piece about it.
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs that lead to certification is HUGE. In my view, it&amp;#39;s a game changer.
Let&amp;#39;s Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/ny-cs-certificate/</guid>
      <description>Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members of the New York State Department of Education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title>
      <link>https://newblog/posts/dont-self-certify/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://newblog/posts/dont-self-certify/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;#39;ve probably seen an image like this:
It&amp;#39;s what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web site itself certified itself as being secure.
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we don&amp;#39;t see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted source.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
